[
  {
    "question": "Pathophysiology is science about:",
    "options": [
      "etiology and pathogenesis",
      "symptoms and signs",
      "prophylaxis of disease",
      "treatment of disease",
      "sanogenesis of diseases"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "etiology and pathogenesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Part of pathophysiology about disease is called:",
    "options": [
      "terminology",
      "general nosology",
      "general pathology",
      "private pathologyprivate pathology",
      "private nosology"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "general nosology"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following options  General pathophysiology studies:",
    "options": [
      "pathology of nervous system",
      "pathology of the cardiovascular system",
      "pathology of endocrine system",
      "typical pathological processes",
      "pathology of reproductive system"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "typical pathological processes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following options is correct for definition of health by WHO:",
    "options": [
      "state of complete physical, mental and social wellbeing ",
      "state of absence of disease",
      "state of compensation of diseasestate of compensation of disease",
      "state of recovering",
      "no decompensation state"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "state of complete physical, mental and social wellbeing "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is component of etiology, but isn't component of pathogenesis in pathophysiology principles?",
    "options": [
      "cause-effect ratio",
      "vicious cycles",
      "compensation-decompensation",
      "cause of the disease",
      "local -systemic ratio"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cause of the disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of followin is component of pathogenesis, but isn’t cmponent of etiology in pathophysiology principles?",
    "options": [
      "cause-effect ratio",
      "internal causative factors",
      "external causative factors",
      "primary causes",
      "secondary causes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cause-effect ratio"
  },
  {
    "question": "Latent period of disease is characterized by: ",
    "options": [
      "no symptoms",
      "general symptoms",
      "recovery mechanisms",
      "extinction of clinical manifestations",
      "clinical manifestations"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "no symptoms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Prodromal period of disease is characterized by:",
    "options": [
      "no symptoms",
      "general symptoms",
      "recovery mechanisms",
      "extinction of clinical manifestations",
      "clinical manifestations"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "general symptoms"
  },
  {
    "question": "When response of the body, according pathogenesis, is same direction with injury it is:",
    "options": [
      "positive feedback",
      "negative feedback",
      "defensive response ",
      "neutral response",
      "compensatory effect"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "positive feedback"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of following is correct characteristic of disease?",
    "options": [
      "active adaptation",
      "loss of adaptive abilities",
      "physical wellbeing",
      "active compensation",
      "mental and social wellbeing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "loss of adaptive abilities"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term used for the cause of the disease?",
    "options": [
      "Etiology ",
      "Pathogenesis ",
      "Morphogenesis",
      "Pathomorphism ",
      "Thanatogenesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Etiology "
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term used for the mechanism of the disease?",
    "options": [
      "Etiology ",
      "Pathogenesis",
      "Morphogenesis ",
      "Pathomorphism ",
      "Thanatogenesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pathogenesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term used for the mechanism of death?",
    "options": [
      "Etiology ",
      "Pathogenesis",
      "Morphogenesis ",
      "Pathomorphism ",
      "Thanatogenesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Thanatogenesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term used for the pathology of treatment?",
    "options": [
      "Etiology ",
      "Pathogenesis",
      "Morphogenesis ",
      "Iatrogeny ",
      "Thanatogenesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Iatrogeny "
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term used for the mechanism of recovery?",
    "options": [
      "Etiology ",
      "Pathogenesis",
      "Morphogenesis ",
      "Sanogenesis",
      "Thanatogenesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Sanogenesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term is used for the designations of structural lesions in organs, tissues and cells?",
    "options": [
      "Etiology",
      "Pathomorphology",
      "Morphogenesis",
      "Pathomorphism ",
      "Thanatogenesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pathomorphology"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term is used for the postmortem examination?",
    "options": [
      "Biopsy ",
      "Microscopy",
      "Autopsy ",
      "Endoscopy",
      "Cytogenetics"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Autopsy "
  },
  {
    "question": "Whar does mean the term \"pathogenesis\"?",
    "options": [
      "complications ",
      "cause of development",
      "clinical manifestations",
      "the development mechanism",
      "mechanism of death "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "the development mechanism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does mean the term \"tanatogenesis\" ?",
    "options": [
      "complications ",
      "cause of development",
      "clinical manifestations",
      "the development mechanism",
      "mechanism of death "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "mechanism of death "
  },
  {
    "question": "What does mean the term \"etiology\" ?",
    "options": [
      "complications",
      "the mechanism of death",
      "the cause of development",
      "development mechanism",
      "clinical manifestations"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "the cause of development"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the correct definition of death?",
    "options": [
      "Stopping of vital activity of the organism",
      "Stop of breath and stop of blood circulation",
      "Programmed cell death ",
      "Necrosis of tissues which contacting with air and bacteria",
      "Deposition of calcium in dead tissue"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stopping of vital activity of the organism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sigh of death characterized by emptiness of arteries and overflowing veins with blood?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling",
      "Stop of breath",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric spots"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called sign of biologic death characterized by not dissappear by pressing to spot?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Imbibition",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Imbibition"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of programmed cell death?",
    "options": [
      "Coagulative necrosis",
      "Gangrene",
      "Cellular swelling ",
      "Fat necrosis ",
      "Apoptosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Apoptosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sign of biologic death is associated with decrease of body temperature?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling ",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots ",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric cooling "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sign of biologic death which associated with hardning of muscles?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling ",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots ",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rigor mortis"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called sign of biologic death which associated with evaporation of fluid? ",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling ",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots ",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric drying"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called sign of biologic death which associated with enzymatic destruction of tissues?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling ",
      "Cadaveric rigor mortis ",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots ",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric decomposition"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the characteristic sign of clinical death?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cessation of respiration ",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cessation of respiration "
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the characteristic sign of clinical death?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling",
      "Cessation of blood circulation ",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cessation of blood circulation "
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the type of necrosis which associated with formation of yellow-white hard areas?",
    "options": [
      "Coagulative necrosis",
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Gangrene",
      "Fat necrosis",
      "Fibrinoid necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Coagulative necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Infarction it is necrosis?",
    "options": [
      "with different etiology",
      "with curtain localization",
      "with vascular genesis (due to blood circulation disturbances)",
      "due to microcirculation disturbances",
      "in organ due to stopping of arterial blood flow"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "in organ due to stopping of arterial blood flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "What develops around the focus of necrosis in living tissues:",
    "options": [
      "autolysis",
      "tissue anemia",
      "demarcation inflammation",
      "necrobiosis",
      "calcification"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "necrobiosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Causes of direct necrosis?",
    "options": [
      "nerve damage",
      "standstill of blood flow",
      "spasm of blood vessels",
      "the effect of acids",
      "rupture of blood vessels"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "the effect of acids"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sigh of death characterized by emptiness of arteries and overflowing veins with blood?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling",
      "Stop of breath",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric spots"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called sign of biologic death which associated with enzymatic destruction of tissues?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling ",
      "Cadaveric rigor mortis ",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots ",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric decomposition"
  },
  {
    "question": "The organization is a favorable outcome of:",
    "options": [
      "embolism",
      "necrosis",
      "pathological accumulation ",
      "inflammation",
      "induration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sigh of death characterized by emptiness of arteries and overflowing veins with blood?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling",
      "Stop of breath",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric spots"
  },
  {
    "question": "What develops around the focus of necrosis in living tissues?",
    "options": [
      "autolysis",
      "tissue anemia",
      "demarcation inflammation",
      "necrobiosis",
      "calcification"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "necrobiosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Apoptotic bodies in the tissue are best seen in stainig:",
    "options": [
      "Sudan III ",
      "Hematoxylin and eosin",
      "Picrofuxin ",
      "Schiff (PAS) -reaction ",
      "Toluidine blue"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hematoxylin and eosin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Enzyme that take part in the autolysis of cell nuclei?",
    "options": [
      "acidic phosphotase",
      "DNAase",
      "alkaline phosphatase",
      "cytochrome oxidase",
      "transferase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "DNAase"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what disease often there is a vascular necrosis?",
    "options": [
      "tuberculosis",
      "atherosclerosis",
      "influenza",
      "anemia",
      "leprosy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "atherosclerosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is formed as a result of necrosis of cells and extracellular substance?",
    "options": [
      "pigments",
      "polysaccharides",
      "hemoglobin",
      "tissue detritus",
      "connective tissue"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "tissue detritus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Definition of the concept of \"necrobiosis\":",
    "options": [
      "spasm of blood vessels",
      "anemia of organs",
      "irreversible dystrophic processes",
      "autolysis",
      "pathobiosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "irreversible dystrophic processes"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called sign of biologic death which associated with evaporation of fluid? ",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling ",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots ",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric drying"
  },
  {
    "question": "Apoptotic bodies histologically look like?",
    "options": [
      "granular balls",
      "basophilic blots",
      "eosinophilic crystals",
      "basophilic oval corpuscles",
      "eosinophilic rounded masses"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "eosinophilic rounded masses"
  },
  {
    "question": "Characteristic of the demarcation zone:",
    "options": [
      "zone of ischemia ",
      "accumulation of leukocytes and hyperemia",
      "accumulation of erythrocytes",
      "accumulation of immunocompetent cells",
      "vascular spasm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "accumulation of leukocytes and hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "White infarction with red rim is usual for?",
    "options": [
      "intestine",
      "skin",
      "brain",
      "myocardium",
      "liver"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "myocardium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in the nucleus of the cell during apoptosis occur under the action of?",
    "options": [
      "aminotransferases",
      "hydrolytic enzymes",
      "proteolytic enzymes",
      "Ca-Mg-dependent endonucleases",
      "DNase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ca-Mg-dependent endonucleases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which outcome of necrosis is characterisc by formation of bone tissue?",
    "options": [
      "organization",
      "calcification",
      "ossification",
      "suppuration",
      "incapsulation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ossification"
  },
  {
    "question": "Main factor, which determine severity in electrical injury is:",
    "options": [
      "resistance of tissues",
      "intensity of electrical current",
      "duration of exposure",
      "loops of electrical injury ",
      "body reactivity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "intensity of electrical current"
  },
  {
    "question": "What of these is electrothermal mechanism of electrical current in pathogenesis of electrotrauma?",
    "options": [
      "lightning marks ",
      "muscle cramps",
      "tearing of tissues",
      "involuntary defecation and urination",
      "peripheral vasospasm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "lightning marks "
  },
  {
    "question": "What of these is electrobiological  mechanism of electrical current in pathogenesis of electrotrauma?",
    "options": [
      "rupture of tissues ",
      "peripherial vasospasm",
      "lightning marks ",
      "coagulative necrosis",
      "coliquation necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "peripherial vasospasm"
  },
  {
    "question": "What of these is electrochemical mechanism of electrical current in pathogenesis of electrotrauma?",
    "options": [
      "muscle cramps",
      "rupture of tissues ",
      "coagulative necrosis",
      "peripherial vasospasm",
      "involuntary urination"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "coagulative necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is degree of burns, if there are damages of muscle and even bone?",
    "options": [
      "first degree",
      "second degree",
      "third degree",
      "forth degree",
      "fifth degree"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "forth degree"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is degree of burns, if only epidermis is damged?",
    "options": [
      "first degree",
      "second degree",
      "third degree",
      "forth degree",
      "fifth degree"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "first degree"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is the external risk factors for environmental hyperthermia development?",
    "options": [
      "increased moisture of air",
      "heart disease",
      "young age",
      "diabetes mellitus",
      "body overweight"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased moisture of air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is the internal risk factors for environmental hyperthermia development?:",
    "options": [
      "increased moisture of air",
      "tight clothes ",
      "heart disease",
      "strenuous exercise ",
      "elevated ambient temperature"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "heart disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "What means electromechanical effect in electrical current injury?",
    "options": [
      "peripheral vasoconstriction",
      "rupture of tissues",
      "muscle cramps",
      "coagulative necrosis",
      "ventricular fibrillation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "rupture of tissues"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of electrical current effects is the most life threatening?",
    "options": [
      "muscle cramps",
      "vasoconstriction",
      "coagulative necrosis",
      "ventricular fibrillation ",
      "rupture of tissues"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ventricular fibrillation "
  },
  {
    "question": "Main in pathogenesis of burn shock is:",
    "options": [
      "loss of skin barrier",
      "loss of intestinal barrier",
      "intoxication of the body",
      "denatured tissue proteins",
      "increased capillary permeability"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased capillary permeability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypovolemia in first stage of burn disease is typically result of which one of following processes?",
    "options": [
      "loss of skin barrier",
      "loss of intestinal barrier",
      "loss of blood",
      "loss of plasma",
      "loss of water"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "loss of plasma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these characterises second stage of burn disease?",
    "options": [
      "loss of plasma",
      "hypovolemia",
      "loss of water",
      "hypervolemia",
      "loss of intestinal barrier"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "loss of intestinal barrier"
  },
  {
    "question": "In environmental hyperthermia the main branch of pathogenesis is:",
    "options": [
      "increased heat production",
      "not effective heat loss",
      "increased heat gain",
      "increased to set point in hypothalamus ",
      "change of to set point"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "not effective heat loss"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is principal factor, among following, for development second stage of burn disease?",
    "options": [
      "increased permeability of vessels",
      "vasodilation",
      "pain during burns",
      "cellular debris in burn area",
      "loss of plasma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cellular debris in burn area"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is principal factor, among following, for development third stage of burn disease?",
    "options": [
      "cellular debris in burn area",
      "loss of plasma",
      "protein metabolism disorders",
      "water balance disorders",
      "vasodilation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "protein metabolism disorders"
  },
  {
    "question": "Severe skeletal muscle contractions during electrotrrauma can cause one of following result:",
    "options": [
      "osteoporosis",
      "bones fracture and dislocations",
      "arthritis",
      "joint inflammationjoint inflammation",
      "cardiac failure"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "bones fracture and dislocations"
  },
  {
    "question": "If during burn injury will be formation of blister, what is degree of burn?",
    "options": [
      "first degree",
      "second degree",
      "third degree",
      "forth degree",
      "fifth degree"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "second degree"
  },
  {
    "question": "If during burn injury will be formation of erythema, what is degree of burn?",
    "options": [
      "first degree",
      "second degree",
      "third degree",
      "forth degree",
      "fifth degree"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "first degree"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is main mechanism of burn shock development in  burn injury?",
    "options": [
      "loss of skin barrier",
      "cardiovascular response to major burns",
      "loss of plasma proteins",
      "loss of intestinal barrier",
      "painful syndrome"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cardiovascular response to major burns"
  },
  {
    "question": "What human body organ or system damage can cause general oxygen deficiency –hypoxia, according to disorder of entering O2 ?",
    "options": [
      "respiratory system",
      "circulatory system",
      "GIT system",
      "blood system",
      "tissue itself"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "respiratory system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What human body organ or system damage can cause general oxygen deficiency –hypoxia, according to disorder of oxygen transport speed?",
    "options": [
      "respiratory system",
      "circulatory system",
      "GIT system",
      "blood system",
      "tissue itself"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "circulatory system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What human body organ or system damage can cause general oxygen deficiency –hypoxia, according to disorder of oxygen delivery to tissues?",
    "options": [
      "respiratory system",
      "circulatory system",
      "GIT system",
      "blood system",
      "tissue itself"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "blood system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Oxygen deficiency due to bronchial obstruction is known as:",
    "options": [
      "circulatory hypoxia",
      "tissue hypoxia",
      "methemoglobinemia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "hematogenous hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "respiratory hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following can cause tissue (histogenous) type of  hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "lung disease",
      "cyanide poisoning",
      "anemia syndrome",
      "liver disease",
      "cardiac failure"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cyanide poisoning"
  },
  {
    "question": "In high mountain conditions will develop:",
    "options": [
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "endogenous hypoxia",
      "blood hypoxia",
      "tissue hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "exogenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carbon monoxide poisoning results in which type of hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "blood hypoxia",
      "tissue hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "blood hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "During hypoxia one of the short-term compensatory responses is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "hyperplasia of alveoli",
      "alveolar metaplasia",
      "heart hyperthrophy",
      "hyperventilation",
      "hyperthrophy of spleen"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hyperventilation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is long term compensation response to hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "hyperventilation",
      "tachycardia",
      "hypertrophy of heart",
      "tachypnea",
      "reticulocytes in the blood"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypertrophy of heart"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the etiology of hemic    hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "cyanide poisoning",
      "decreased RBCs",
      "lung disease",
      "liver disease",
      "heart disease"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "decreased RBCs"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is initial response of cell to hypoxic injury?",
    "options": [
      "activation of PFK-1 ",
      "activation of proteases",
      "accumulation of Ca++",
      "accumulation of Na+",
      "edema of organelles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "activation of PFK-1 "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these characterizes changes in hypoxic cell injury?",
    "options": [
      "acidosis",
      "alkalosis",
      "does not change",
      "normal pH",
      "elevated pH"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "acidosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of  following mainly causes swelling of the cell in hypoxic cell injury?",
    "options": [
      "ionic pumps failure",
      "more production of water",
      "free radicals formation",
      "DNA damage",
      "Ca++ activates enzymes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ionic pumps failure"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is insufficient oxygen consumption from blood, what type of hypoxia is it?",
    "options": [
      "hemic hypoxia",
      "histigenous hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "histigenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is insufficient oxygen in atmospheric air what type of hypoxia is it?",
    "options": [
      "hemic hypoxia",
      "histigenous hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "exogenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air decreased oxygen in mountain high altitude  causes which one of compensatory reaction?",
    "options": [
      "hypoventilation",
      "hyperventilation",
      "uneven ventilation",
      "diffusion disturbance",
      "stopping of ventilation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hyperventilation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Respiratory hypoxia results in which one of gas composition change?",
    "options": [
      "decreasing PaO2 in alveolar air",
      "increasing PaO2 in alveolar air",
      "alkalosis in blood",
      "increasing PaO2 in blood",
      "no changes in blood gas composition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "decreasing PaO2 in alveolar air"
  },
  {
    "question": "In high altitude hypoxia hyperventilation starts due to which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "decreased PaO2 in blood",
      "decreased CO2 in blood",
      "increased CO2 in blood",
      "increased PaO2 in blood",
      "decreased CO2 in medulla oblongata"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "decreased PaO2 in blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of hypoxia is characterized by decrease in O2 arteriovenous difference?",
    "options": [
      "hemic hypoxia",
      "histogenous hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "histogenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of hypoxia is characterized by decrease in O2 arteriovenous difference?",
    "options": [
      "hemic hypoxia",
      "histogenous hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "histogenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is increased number of RBCs in patient who presence on high altitude, which of these responses to hypoxia is it?",
    "options": [
      "short term compensation",
      "decompensation",
      "adaptation",
      "BM damage",
      "fast compensation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "adaptation"
  },
  {
    "question": "If patient with hemic hypoxia has decreased blood oxygen binding capacity it  means insufficient formation of which type of Hb?",
    "options": [
      "oxyhemoglobin",
      "free hemoglobin",
      "carboxihemoglobin",
      "methhemoglobin",
      "deoxyhemoglobin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "oxyhemoglobin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following changes in partial gases pressure of blood is most common for congestion type of circulatory hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "decreased PvO2",
      "normal values of PvO2",
      "increased PvO2",
      "increased PaCO2",
      "decreased PaCO2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "decreased PvO2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following changes in partial gases pressure of blood is most common for ischemic type of circulatory hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "decreased PvO2",
      "normal values of PvO2",
      "increased PvO2",
      "increased PaCO2",
      "decreased PaCO2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "normal values of PvO2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alkalosis in high altitude hypoxia develops due to which one of following events?",
    "options": [
      "methemoglobinemia",
      "intoxication",
      "hypoventilation",
      "hyperventilation",
      "infarction"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hyperventilation"
  },
  {
    "question": "If patient has increased arterio-venous difference of O2, what is more probable reason for this type  of hypoxia? ",
    "options": [
      "carbon monoxide poisoning",
      "heart failure",
      "disorder of external breathing ",
      "cyanide poisoning",
      "iron deficiency"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "heart failure"
  },
  {
    "question": "If patient has decreased arterio-venous difference of O2, which type of hypoxia more probably is it?",
    "options": [
      "hemic hypoxia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "histogenous hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "histogenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is increased venous blood oxygen level, which type of hypoxia is it?",
    "options": [
      "hemic hypoxia",
      "histogenous hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "histogenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "If examination of blood shows hypocapnia, what type of hypoxia it can be?",
    "options": [
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "blood hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "tissue hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "exogenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of consequences of cell injury is noninflammatory?",
    "options": [
      "apoptosis",
      "necrosis",
      "gangrene",
      "lysislysis",
      "infarction"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "apoptosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which changes histologically occurs in necrotic cells?",
    "options": [
      "nuclei stained with eosin more",
      "cytoplasm is less basophilic than usual",
      "nuclei stained with hematoxylin less",
      "nuclei stained with hematoxylin more",
      "cytoplasm is stained with hematoxylin more"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "nuclei stained with hematoxylin more"
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in the nucleus of the cell during apoptosis occur under the action of?",
    "options": [
      "aminotransferases",
      "hydrolytic enzymes",
      "proteolytic enzymes",
      "Ca-Mg-dependent endonucleases",
      "DNase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ca-Mg-dependent endonucleases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Definition of \"gangrene\"?",
    "options": [
      "etiologic type of necrosis",
      "clinical and morphologic form of necrosis",
      "vascular necrosis",
      "necrosis of tissues in contact with the external environment",
      "toxic necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "necrosis of tissues in contact with the external environment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Etiological type of necrosis?",
    "options": [
      "infarction",
      "dry",
      "sequestration",
      "trophoneurotic",
      "Wet"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "trophoneurotic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the microscopic sign of necrosis of the cell nucleus?",
    "options": [
      "heterolysis",
      "karyopicnosis",
      "karyokinesis",
      "swelling of mitochondria",
      "thickening of the nuclear membrane "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "karyopicnosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Definition of the concept of \"necrobiosis\"?",
    "options": [
      "spasm of blood vessels",
      "anemia of organs",
      "irreversible dystrophic processes",
      "autolysis",
      "pathobiosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "irreversible dystrophic processes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Characteristic of tissues with dry gangrene?",
    "options": [
      "edema",
      "mummification",
      "anemia",
      "fullness",
      "flabby consistency"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "mummification"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called sign of biologic death which associated with enzymatic destruction of tissues?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling ",
      "Cadaveric rigor mortis ",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots ",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric decomposition"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called sign of biologic death characterized by not dissappear by pressing to spot?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Imbibition",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Imbibition"
  },
  {
    "question": "Histologically, in necrotic cells?",
    "options": [
      "nuclei stained with eosin more",
      "cytoplasm is less basophilic than usual",
      "nuclei stained with hematoxylin less",
      "nuclei stained with hematoxylin more",
      "cytoplasm is stained with hematoxylin more"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "nuclei stained with hematoxylin more"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the characteristic sign of clinical death?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling",
      "Cessation of blood circulation ",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cessation of blood circulation "
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the characteristic sign of clinical death?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cessation of respiration ",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cessation of respiration "
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called sign of biologic death which associated with enzymatic destruction of tissues?",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling ",
      "Cadaveric rigor mortis ",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots ",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric decomposition"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called sign of biologic death which associated with evaporation of fluid? ",
    "options": [
      "Cadaveric cooling ",
      "Rigor mortis",
      "Cadaveric drying",
      "Cadaveric spots ",
      "Cadaveric decomposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cadaveric drying"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which organ  gangrene can develop?",
    "options": [
      "lungs",
      "brain",
      "uterus",
      "liver",
      "heart "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "lungs"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which disease caseous necrosis develops?",
    "options": [
      "intestinal infections",
      "atherosclerosis",
      "tuberculosis",
      "typhoid fever",
      "arterial hypertension"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "tuberculosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The organization is a favorable outcome of:",
    "options": [
      "embolism",
      "necrosis",
      "pathological accumulation ",
      "inflammation",
      "induration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Etiological type of necrosis?",
    "options": [
      "infarction",
      "dry",
      "sequestration",
      "trophoneurotic",
      "Wet"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "trophoneurotic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Characteristic of the infarction?",
    "options": [
      "traumatic necrosis",
      "direct necrosis",
      "vascular necrosis",
      "trophoneurotic necrosis",
      "caseous necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "vascular necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Characteristic of tissues with dry gangrene:",
    "options": [
      "edema",
      "mummification",
      "anemia",
      "fullness",
      "flabby consistency"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "mummification"
  },
  {
    "question": "The organization is the outcome of necrosis, characterized by?",
    "options": [
      "replacement with connective tissue",
      "formation of a capsule",
      "deposition of calcium ",
      "formation of a cyst",
      "suppuration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "replacement with connective tissue"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term is used for the condensation and shrinkage of DNA into solid mass?",
    "options": [
      "Pyknosis",
      "Karyorrhexis",
      "Karyolysis",
      "Plasmorrhexis",
      "Plasmolysis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pyknosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term is used for the fading of basophilia of chromatin due to digestion of DNA by DNAses activated by decrease pH? ",
    "options": [
      "Pyknosis",
      "Karyorrhexis",
      "Karyolysis",
      "Plasmorrhexis",
      "Plasmolysis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Karyolysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called variant of reversible cell injury?",
    "options": [
      "Coagulative necrosis",
      "Gangrene",
      "Cellular swelling ",
      "Fat necrosis ",
      "Apoptosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cellular swelling "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of necrosis occurs in patients having a history of trauma?",
    "options": [
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Coagulative necrosis",
      "Gangrene",
      "Caseous necrosis",
      "Fat nonenzymatic necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fat nonenzymatic necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term is used for the fragmentation of condensed nuclear mass? ",
    "options": [
      "Pyknosis",
      "Karyorrhexis",
      "Karyolysis",
      "Plasmorrhexis",
      "Plasmolysis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Karyorrhexis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The primary localization of Liquefactive necrosis is?",
    "options": [
      "heart",
      "spleen",
      "brain",
      "kidney",
      "lower extremities"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "brain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of necrosis of arterioles associated with malignant arterial hypertension?",
    "options": [
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Coagulative necrosis",
      "Caseous necrosis",
      "Gangrene",
      "Fibrinoid necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrinoid necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Classification of necrosis by the mechanism of action of the etiologic factor:",
    "options": [
      "direct",
      "gangrene",
      "sequestration",
      "infarction",
      "bedsore"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "direct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which disease typicaly occurs fibrinoid necrosis?",
    "options": [
      "syphilis",
      "lymphogranulomatosis",
      "rheumatism",
      "tuberculosis",
      "acute pancreatitis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "rheumatism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of type of necrosis which usually occurs in connective tissue and blood vessels wall?",
    "options": [
      "Coagulative necrosis",
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Fat necrosis ",
      "Caseous necrosis ",
      "Fibrinoid necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrinoid necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of outcome of necrosis characterized by formation of scar?",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Calcification",
      "Ossification",
      "Cyst formation",
      "Suppuration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Organization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of type of necrosis which associated with formation of grey soft areas?",
    "options": [
      "Coagulative necrosis",
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Gangrene",
      "Fat necrosis",
      "Fibrinoid necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Liquefactive necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of outcome of necrosis characterized by formation of bone tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Calcification",
      "Ossification",
      "Cyst formation",
      "Suppuration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ossification"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of outcome of necrosis characterized by formation of pus due to action of bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Calcification",
      "Ossification",
      "Cyst formation",
      "Suppuration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Suppuration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of necrosis cause by Clostridium perfringens and other clostridial species?",
    "options": [
      "Dry gangrene",
      "Apoptosis",
      "Gas gangrene",
      "Caseous necrosis",
      "Fibrinoid necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gas gangrene"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of outcome of necrosis characterized by formation of cavity surrounded with thin capsule and filled with serous fluid?",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Calcification",
      "Ossification",
      "Cyst formation",
      "Suppuration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cyst formation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of outcome of necrosis characterized by formation defect of epithelium due to shed of dead epithelial cells?",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Ulceration",
      "Ossification",
      "Cyst formation",
      "Suppuration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ulceration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of programmed cell death?",
    "options": [
      "Coagulative necrosis",
      "Gangrene",
      "Cellular swelling ",
      "Fat necrosis ",
      "Apoptosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Apoptosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the correct definition of necrosis?",
    "options": [
      "Stopping of vital activity of the organism",
      "Stop of breath and stop of blood circulation",
      "Programmed cell death ",
      "Cell death in living tissue",
      "Deposition of calcium in dead tissue"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cell death in living tissue"
  },
  {
    "question": "Autopsy of a 60-year-old patient suffering from atherosclerosis. Gross morphology of brain: area of necrosis grey in color and soft consistency. Which type of necrosis is described in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Coagulative",
      "Enzymatic",
      "Caseous",
      "Liquefactive",
      "Fibrinoid"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Liquefactive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in the lungs were found in a patient - 38 year old who died of tuberculosis. Grossly: hard, white-yellow, cheese-like areas, 0.3 sm in size. Microscopically: amorphous granular debris composed of fragmented, coagulated cells. Which type of necrosis occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Fibrinoid necrosis",
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Fat necrosis",
      "Caseous necrosis",
      "Gangrene"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Caseous necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 50-year-old patient who died from acute heart failure was found to have myocardial changes. Grossly: area is yellow-white in color and hard consistence, size 2 х 2.5 sm. Microscopically: karyolysis in cardiomyocytes, plasmolysis and plasmorexis. Altered kaardiomyocytes surrounded by neutrophils and dilated vessels. What pathological process in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Apoptosis",
      "Inflammation",
      "Necrosis",
      "Dystrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 62-year-old patient who suffered from arterial hypertension and died as a result of a hypertensive crisis, vascular changes were found. Microscopically: the walls of the arterioles are thickened and represented by a homogeneous, bright pink necrotic material. What type of necrosis occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Fibrinoid necrosis",
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Fat necrosis",
      "Caseous necrosis",
      "Gangrene"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrinoid necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30-year-old patient developed acute abdominal pain after excessive alcohol consumption. The patient was taken to hospital, where he died from polyorganic failure. Autopsy revealed changes in the pancreas. Grossly: opaque chalky white plaques and nodules in the adipose tissue surrounding the pancreas. Microscopically: foci of dead adipose tissue, inflammatory infiltration with neutrophilic leukocytes is expressed. What type of necrosis occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Fibrinoid necrosis",
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Fat necrosis",
      "Caseous necrosis",
      "Gangrene"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fat necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an 82-year-old patient who suffered from arterial hypertension and died from chronic heart failure, in addition to the characteristic changes of this disease, changes in the brain were found: the cavity, surrounded by a thin capsule and filled with serous fluid, size 1x1 sm. What outcome of necrosis occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Organization  ",
      "Calcification ",
      "Ossification ",
      "Incapsulation ",
      "Cyst formation "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cyst formation "
  },
  {
    "question": "Examination of the patient revealed: on the back of the right foot, the injured area is black, dry and wrinkled, sharply delimited from adjacent viable tissues. What type of necrosis does the patient have?",
    "options": [
      "Coagulative necrosis",
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Fat necrosis",
      "Caseous necrosis",
      "Gangrene"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gangrene"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 54-year-old patient who suffered from pancreatitis and died as a result of a intoxication. The gross appearance is one of opaque chalky white plaques and nodules in the adipose tissue surrounding the pancreas. What type of necrosis occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Fibrinoid necrosis",
      "Liquefactive necrosis",
      "Gangrene",
      "Caseous necrosis",
      "Fat necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fat necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 58-year-old woman who suffered from atherosclerosis of aorta and meseterial arteries and died a result of intoxication an autopsy revealed changes in the intestine: reddish-black in color, without clearly demarcated zone from adjacent healthy tissue extensive liquefaction of tissue. Which type of necrosis occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Wet gangrene ",
      "Fibrinoid necrosis",
      "Fat necrosis",
      "Caseous necrosis",
      "Dry Gangrene"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Wet gangrene "
  },
  {
    "question": "A 22-year-old patient who suffered from repeated rheumatic fever and died from  heart failure. Microscopically in the valve: loss of normal structure and replacement by a homogenous, bright pink-staining necrotic material. Which type of necrosis occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Fibrinoid",
      "Liquefactive",
      "Coagulative",
      "Caseous ",
      "Gangrene"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrinoid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deficiency of which enzyme causes disorders of protein digestion in stomach?",
    "options": [
      "pepsin",
      "enterokinase",
      "trypsin",
      "dipeptidase",
      "amylase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "pepsin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deficiency of which factor causes disorders of protein digestion in duodenum?",
    "options": [
      "trypsin",
      "dipeptidase",
      "amylase",
      "pepsin",
      "hydrochloric acid"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "trypsin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which enzyme deficiency causes disorders of protein digestion in damage of duodenum?",
    "options": [
      "enterokinase",
      "dipeptidase",
      "trypsingen",
      "pepsinogen",
      "hydrochloric acid"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "enterokinase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Nitrogen balance changes if there is disorder of which of listed?",
    "options": [
      "water-salt metabolism",
      "carbohydrate metabolism ",
      "protein metabolism ",
      "lipid metabolism ",
      "acid base metaboism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "protein metabolism "
  },
  {
    "question": "Positive nitrogen balance characterizes by which one of following conditions?",
    "options": [
      "protein breakdown is more than normal",
      "protein synthesis is more than normal",
      "protein synthesis is less than normal",
      "protein synthesis and breakdown are equal",
      "protein breakdown not change"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "protein synthesis is more than normal"
  },
  {
    "question": "Negative nitrogen balance characterizes by which one of following conditions?",
    "options": [
      "protein breakdown is more than normal",
      "protein synthesis is more than normal",
      "protein synthesis is less than normal",
      "protein synthesis and breakdown are equal",
      "protein breakdown not change"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "protein breakdown is more than normal"
  },
  {
    "question": "If anabolism is more than catabolism what would it be means?",
    "options": [
      "decreased stabilized protein synthesis",
      "negative nitrogen  balance",
      "positive nitrogen balance",
      "decreased growth protein synthesis",
      "increased protein breakdown"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "positive nitrogen balance"
  },
  {
    "question": "If catabolism is more than anabolism what would it be means?",
    "options": [
      "increased stabilized protein synthesis",
      "negative nitrogen  balance",
      "positive nitrogen balance",
      "increased growth protein synthesis",
      "protein breakdown not change"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "negative nitrogen  balance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Positive nitrogen balance is observed when is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "growth of children",
      "starvation",
      "hyperthyroidism",
      "burns",
      "fever"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "growth of children"
  },
  {
    "question": "Negative nitrogen balance is observed when is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "growth of children",
      "starvation",
      "recovery",
      "after starvation",
      "pregnancy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "starvation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select which one is causative factor of negative nitrogen balance?",
    "options": [
      "after wasting disease",
      "in  wasting disease",
      "in pregnancy",
      "after starvation",
      "in children"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "in  wasting disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select which one is causative factor of positive nitrogen balance?",
    "options": [
      "in  wasting disease",
      "in starvation",
      "in burn disease",
      "in growth period",
      "in fever"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "in growth period"
  },
  {
    "question": "Azotemia means disorders of which of these metabolisms?",
    "options": [
      "water-salt ",
      "carbohydrate ",
      "protein",
      "lipid",
      "acid base "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "protein"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these is correct to define “Azotemia”?",
    "options": [
      "increased  urea level in blood",
      "increased  urea level in urine",
      "increased sodium level in blood",
      "increased sodium level in urine",
      "increased glucose level  in urine"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased  urea level in blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called decreased plasma proteins level in blood?  ",
    "options": [
      "hypoproteinemia",
      "paraproteinemia",
      "hyperproteinemi",
      "dysproteinemia",
      "hypercapnia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypoproteinemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called increased plasma proteins level in blood?   ",
    "options": [
      "hypoproteinemia",
      "paraproteinemia",
      "hyperproteinemi",
      "dysproteinemia",
      "hypercapnia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hyperproteinemi"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called disorders of albumins and  globulins ratio in blood plasma?",
    "options": [
      "hypoproteinemia",
      "paraproteinemia",
      "hyperproteinemi",
      "dysproteinemia",
      "hypercapnia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "dysproteinemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "If azotemia is characterized by elevation of urea component in BUN it could means which one of these pathologies?",
    "options": [
      "gut diseases",
      "liver diseases",
      "starvation",
      "kidney diseases",
      "blood disease"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "kidney diseases"
  },
  {
    "question": "If azotemia is characterized by elevation of ammonia component in BUN it could means which one of these pathologies?",
    "options": [
      "gut diseases",
      "liver diseases",
      "kidney diseases",
      "blood disease",
      "gout"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "liver diseases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hyperuricaemia means elevation which of these in blood?",
    "options": [
      "ammonia level ",
      "urea level ",
      "uric acid level ",
      "BUN level ",
      "creatinine level"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "uric acid level "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following organs damage hyperuricemia commonly causes?",
    "options": [
      "brain ",
      "liver ",
      "vessels ",
      "lungs",
      "joints "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "joints "
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which one of following causes  hyperuricemia?",
    "options": [
      "high sodium diet",
      "high purine diet",
      "low lipid diet",
      "low protein diet",
      "low carbohydrate diet"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "high purine diet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Formation of tophi in podagra is connected with urate crystals precipitation in which one of listed?",
    "options": [
      "in kidney",
      "in vessel walls",
      "in liver",
      "in intestine ",
      "in big toe"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "in big toe"
  },
  {
    "question": "Damage of liver can cause disorders of detoxification which one of following nitrogen wastes? ",
    "options": [
      "uric acid",
      "ammonia",
      "creatine",
      "urea",
      "ketones"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ammonia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is increased in hepatic type of azotemia?",
    "options": [
      "uric acid",
      "ammonia",
      "creatine",
      "urea",
      "amino acids"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ammonia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is increased in renal type of azotemia?",
    "options": [
      "uric acid",
      "ammonia",
      "creatine",
      "urea",
      "amino acids"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "urea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Decreased synthesis of albumins, which leads to hypoproteinemia, commonly is result of which one of listed?",
    "options": [
      "stomach damage",
      "liver damage",
      "loss of blood",
      "kidney damage ",
      "intestine damage"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "liver damage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Increased breakdown of proteins, which leads to hypoproteinemia, commonly is result of which one of listed? ",
    "options": [
      "stomach damage",
      "liver damage",
      "excess of growth hormone",
      "excess of cortisol ",
      "kidney damage "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "excess of cortisol "
  },
  {
    "question": "Loss proteins with urine (proteinuria) typically leads to which one of following types of edema?",
    "options": [
      "pulmonary edema",
      "face region ",
      "throughout body ",
      "abdominal cavity ",
      "legs region"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "throughout body "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following changes in blood, related to protein metabolism disorders, is commonly risk factor for formation of stones in urinary tract?  ",
    "options": [
      "hyperuricemia ",
      "paraproteinemia",
      "uremia",
      "dysproteinemia",
      "azotemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hyperuricemia "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following protein metabolism disorders can be caused by regular diet with lot of carbohydrates and deficiency of proteins in children?",
    "options": [
      "Kwashiorkor",
      "Diabetes mellitus",
      "Alimentary marasmus",
      "Albinism",
      "Podagra"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Kwashiorkor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following protein metabolism disorders can be caused by regular diet with lot of purines?",
    "options": [
      "Kwashiorkor",
      "Diabetes mellitus",
      "Alimentary marasmus",
      "Albinism",
      "Podagra"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Podagra"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following protein metabolism disorders can be caused by regular insufficient food intake in children?",
    "options": [
      "Kwashiorkor",
      "PKU",
      "Alimentary marasmus",
      "Albinism",
      "Podagra"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alimentary marasmus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following protein metabolism disorders can be caused by defect in enzyme tyrosinase?",
    "options": [
      "Kwashiorkor",
      "PKU",
      "Alimentary marasmus",
      "Albinism",
      "Podagra"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Albinism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following protein metabolism disorders can be caused by defect in enzyme homogentisate oxidase?",
    "options": [
      "Alkaptonuria",
      "Kwashiorkor",
      "PKU",
      "Alimentary marasmus",
      "Albinism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alkaptonuria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following protein metabolism disorders in children is characterized by lot of phenyl ketones in urine?",
    "options": [
      "Alkaptonuria",
      "Kwashiorkor",
      "PKU",
      "Alimentary marasmus",
      "Albinism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alimentary marasmus"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which one of following protein metabolism disorders urine samples after 1-2 hours in open air become black color?",
    "options": [
      "Alkaptonuria",
      "Kwashiorkor",
      "PKU",
      "Alimentary marasmus",
      "Albinism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alkaptonuria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which enzyme deficiency causes disorders of hydrolysis of polypeptides molecules up to short polypeptides during food proteins digestion?",
    "options": [
      "pepsin",
      "enterokinase",
      "trypsin",
      "brush border peptidases",
      "intracellular dipeptidase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "trypsin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which enzyme deficiency causes disorders of hydrolysis of short polypeptides molecules up to tripeptides and dipeptides during food proteins digestion?",
    "options": [
      "pepsin",
      "enterokinase",
      "trypsin",
      "brush border peptidases",
      "intracellular dipeptidase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "brush border peptidases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is characteristic sign of decreased albumin fraction in blood in protein metabolism disorders?",
    "options": [
      "hyperlipidemia",
      "hypercoagulation",
      "hypocoagulation",
      "low antibodies synthesis",
      "dehydration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hyperlipidemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is characteristic sign of decreased gamma globulin fraction in blood in protein metabolism disorders?",
    "options": [
      "hyperlipidemia",
      "hypercoagulation",
      "hypocoagulation",
      "low antibodies synthesis",
      "dehydration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "low antibodies synthesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is  possible consequences in myocytes when is insulin deficiency in diabetes mellitus?",
    "options": [
      "increased protein synthesis",
      "insufficient protein synthesis",
      "insufficient gluconeogenesis ",
      "increased glycogenesis",
      "increased glucose uptake"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "insufficient protein synthesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is  possible consequence in adipocytes when is insulin deficiency in diabetes mellitus?",
    "options": [
      "activation of lipogenesis",
      "increased lipolysis",
      "increased glucose uptake",
      "increased transport of GLUT4",
      "increased GLUT4 number"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased lipolysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which one of following relates to mechanisms of hyperglycemia in diabetes mellitus?",
    "options": [
      "increased glucose uptake by adipocytes",
      "increased glucose uptake by myocytes",
      "increased glycogenesis",
      "increased gluconeogenesis",
      "increased glucose reabsorption"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased gluconeogenesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which one of following relates to mechanisms of ketonemia in diabetes mellitus?",
    "options": [
      "increased glycogenesis",
      "decreased gluconeogenesis",
      "increased lipolysis",
      "decreased protein synthesis",
      "increased protein synthesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased lipolysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose what of these characterizes diabetic coma development in diabetes mellitus?",
    "options": [
      "increased glucose level in blood",
      "decreased glucose level in blood",
      "increased ketone bodies in blood",
      "decreased ketone bodies in blood",
      "increased protein synthesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased ketone bodies in blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who from these scientists during their experimental work first indicated to role of endocrine pancreas in DM development? ",
    "options": [
      "Mering and Minkovsky",
      "Banting and Best",
      "Chonheim",
      "Sobolev",
      "Mechnikoff"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Sobolev"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who from these scientists first created model of experimental DM after removing pancreas?",
    "options": [
      "Mering and Minkovsky",
      "Banting and Best",
      "Chonheim",
      "Sobolev",
      "Mechnikoff"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mering and Minkovsky"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who from these scientists firstly found out insulin production in beta cells of pancreas?",
    "options": [
      "Mering and Minkovsky",
      "Banting and Best",
      "Chonheim",
      "Sobolev",
      "Mechnikoff"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Banting and Best"
  },
  {
    "question": "Glucose cannot move into beta cells of pancreas, if there is disorder in which one of following glucose transporters?",
    "options": [
      "GLUT 1",
      "GLUT 2",
      "GLUT 4",
      "GLUT 5",
      "GLUT 6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "GLUT 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alteration in work of which one of following glucose transporter causes insulin effects deficiency? ",
    "options": [
      "GLUT 1",
      "GLUT 2",
      "GLUT 4",
      "GLUT 5",
      "GLUT 6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "GLUT 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following glucose transporter isn’t insulin dependent and allows glucose to move into neurons?",
    "options": [
      "GLUT 1",
      "GLUT 2",
      "GLUT 4",
      "GLUT 5",
      "GLUT 6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "GLUT 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Polyuria in diabetes mellitus is mainly result of which one of these factors?",
    "options": [
      "damage of PCT epithelial cells  ",
      "deficiency of ADH",
      "deficiency of insulin",
      "increased osmolality of filtered fluid",
      "damage of filtration membrane"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased osmolality of filtered fluid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Blindness in DM is mainly result of which one of following complications?",
    "options": [
      "neuropathy",
      "retinopathy",
      "nephropathy",
      "atherosclerosis",
      "hypertension"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "retinopathy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Accumulation of sorbitol in ECM and increased glycosylation in DM is result of which one of these changes?",
    "options": [
      "ketonemia",
      "episodes of hypoglycemia",
      "hyperlipidemia",
      "chronic hyperglycemia ",
      "polyuria"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "chronic hyperglycemia "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following complications of DM is more possible when there is accumulation of sorbitol in ECM and increased glycosylation ?",
    "options": [
      "peripheral neuropathy",
      "atherosclerosis",
      "ketoacidosis",
      "coronary heart diseases",
      "hypertension"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "peripheral neuropathy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Immune suppression in DM is result of disorders mainly in which type of metabolism?",
    "options": [
      "acid –base balance",
      "carbohydrate metabolism",
      "water-salt  metabolism",
      "lipid metabolism",
      "protein metabolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "protein metabolism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Diabetic coma in DM firstly is result of disorders mainly in which type of metabolism?",
    "options": [
      "acid –base balance",
      "carbohydrate metabolism",
      "water-salt  metabolism",
      "lipid metabolism",
      "protein metabolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "lipid metabolism"
  },
  {
    "question": "If DM onset is in adolescence after islet cells viral infection, which one of following features can characterize this type of DM?",
    "options": [
      "intact insulin receptors ",
      "previous islet amyloidosis",
      "insulin receptors resistance",
      "previous obesity",
      "intact beta cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "intact insulin receptors "
  },
  {
    "question": "When DM onset is in adolescence with appearance in blood islet cells antibodies, what type of DM can it be?",
    "options": [
      "steroid diabetes",
      "insulin dependent diabetes mellitus",
      "insulin independent diabetes mellitus",
      "secondary diabetes mellitus",
      "gestational diabetes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "insulin dependent diabetes mellitus"
  },
  {
    "question": "If DM onset is in middle age woman with overweight, which one of following features can characterize this type of DM?",
    "options": [
      "autoimmune destruction of beta cells",
      "destruction of insulin by enzymes",
      "adipose cells produce more resistin",
      "intact insulin receptors ",
      "increased insulin receptors number"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "adipose cells produce more resistin"
  },
  {
    "question": "When DM onset is in middle age woman with overweight, what type of DM can it be?",
    "options": [
      "steroid diabetes",
      "insulin dependent diabetes mellitus",
      "insulin independent diabetes mellitus",
      "secondary diabetes mellitus",
      "gestational diabetes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "insulin independent diabetes mellitus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these characterizes origin of DM type I?",
    "options": [
      "insulin receptors resistance",
      "previous obesity",
      "intact beta cells",
      "destruction of beta cells",
      "decreased insulin receptors number"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "destruction of beta cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these characterizes origin of DM type II?",
    "options": [
      "islet cells antibodies",
      "islet amyloidosis finally",
      "intact insulin receptors",
      "previous beta cells destruction",
      "adipose cells produce more leptin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "islet amyloidosis finally"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate what of these is cause of lipid digestion disorders in GIT?",
    "options": [
      "gastritis",
      "esophagitis",
      "hepatitis",
      "PUD",
      "enteritis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hepatitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose what of these is cause of lipid digestion disorders in GIT?",
    "options": [
      "cholecystitis",
      "gastritis",
      "esophagitis",
      "PUD",
      "enteritis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cholecystitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factor deficiency causes disorders of lipid digestion in pancreatitis?",
    "options": [
      "bile acid",
      "hydrochloric acid",
      "enterokinase",
      "lipase",
      "amylase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "lipase"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factor deficiency causes disorders of lipid digestion in in hepatitis?",
    "options": [
      "bile acid",
      "hydrochloric acid",
      "enterokinase",
      "lipase",
      "amylase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "bile acid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate what is first step of lipid absorption disorders when there is acholia?",
    "options": [
      "formation of mixed micelles",
      "formation of chylomicrons",
      "absorption into lymph vessels",
      "absorption into blood vessels",
      "transport through lymph "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "formation of mixed micelles"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is damage of chylomicrons formation, which link of pathogenesis of lipid metabolism disorder can it be?",
    "options": [
      "enterocytes injury",
      "bile production injury",
      "lipase deficiency",
      "LPL synthesis disorder",
      "lacteal of villi injury"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "enterocytes injury"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is damage of simple micelles formation, which link of pathogenesis of lipid metabolism disorder can it be?",
    "options": [
      "enterocytes injury",
      "bile production injury",
      "lipase deficiency",
      "LPL synthesis disorder",
      "lacteal of villi injury"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "bile production injury"
  },
  {
    "question": "Concerning lipid metabolism, chylomicrons absorption is damaged through which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "lacteal of villi ",
      "blood capillary",
      "bile capillary",
      "brush border of enterocytes",
      "lymph capillary"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "lacteal of villi "
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is damage of mixed micelles formation, which link of pathogenesis of lipid metabolism disorder can it be?",
    "options": [
      "enterocytes injury",
      "bile production injury",
      "lipase deficiency",
      "LPL synthesis disorder",
      "lacteal of villi injury"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "lipase deficiency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Macrophages replete by exceeded cholesterol are converted to which one of these cells type?",
    "options": [
      "plasma cells",
      "foam cells",
      "immunocytes",
      "phagocytes",
      "APC"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "foam cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of lipoproteins contains 50% of cholesterol in their structure, that is important for atherosclerosis development? ",
    "options": [
      "VLDLs",
      "LDLs",
      "Chylomicrons",
      "HDLs",
      "IDLs"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "LDLs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of lipoproteins contain 50% of proteins in their structure that is important for prevention of atherosclerosis development?",
    "options": [
      "VLDLs",
      "LDLs",
      "Chylomicrons",
      "HDLs",
      "IDLs"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "HDLs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deposition of cholesterol during atherosclerosis development is in which of following sites?",
    "options": [
      "in endothelial cells ",
      "beneath endothelial cells",
      "in epithelial cells ",
      "beneath epidermal cells",
      "in epidermal cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "beneath endothelial cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Atherosclerosis damages mainly which one of following structures?",
    "options": [
      "large veins",
      "heart valves",
      "large arteries",
      "middle size arteries ",
      "small arterioles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "middle size arteries "
  },
  {
    "question": "Atherosclerosis is deposition of cholesterol in which  one of following parts of vessel wall?",
    "options": [
      "endothelium",
      "intima",
      "media",
      "adventitia",
      "all layers "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "intima"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is first step of atherosclerotic plaque development?",
    "options": [
      "formation of fibrous cap",
      "formation of foam cells",
      "proliferation of smooth muscles cells",
      "cholesterol uptake through scavenger receptors",
      "thrombus formation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cholesterol uptake through scavenger receptors"
  },
  {
    "question": "What substances are accumulated within parenchymal cells in steatosis?",
    "options": [
      "Cholesterol",
      "Apoproteins",
      "triglycerides",
      "vitamines",
      "ketone bodies"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "triglycerides"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following organs fatty changes are not seen?",
    "options": [
      "Liver",
      "Heart",
      "Kidney",
      "Muscles",
      "Lungs"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lungs"
  },
  {
    "question": "What histologically signs of fatty changes are seen by light microscopy",
    "options": [
      "Intracellular granules",
      "Basophilic granules",
      "Extracellular granules",
      "Vacuoles in the cytoplasm around the nucleus",
      "Eosinophilic granules"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Vacuoles in the cytoplasm around the nucleus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which are the characteristics of fatty changes in the heart?",
    "options": [
      "Red heart",
      "Small size heart",
      "Tiger heart",
      "solid heart",
      "Goose heart"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tiger heart"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cells can accumulate cholesterol and cholesterol esters in atherosclerotic plaque?",
    "options": [
      "Macrophages and smooth muscle cells",
      "Leukocytes and fibroblasts",
      "Lymphocytes and erythrocytes",
      "Fibroblasts and leukocytes",
      "Erythrocytes and lymphocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Macrophages and smooth muscle cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of the cells accumulating fat within the intimal layer of aorta and large arteries in atherosclerotic plaques?",
    "options": [
      "Fibroblasts",
      "Epithelial cells",
      "Foam cells",
      "Lymphocytes",
      "Leukocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Foam cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the pathological process which is associated with               accumulation of cholesterol and cholesterol esters with formation of tumorous masses?",
    "options": [
      "Atheroma",
      "Xantoma",
      "Adenoma",
      "Papilloma",
      "Teratoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Xantoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What pathological process is characterized by derangements of glycogen metabolism?",
    "options": [
      "Atherosclerosis",
      "Diabetes Mellitus",
      "Viral hepatitis",
      "Arterial hypertension",
      "Goiter"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Diabetes Mellitus"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which organ occurs colloid degeneration?",
    "options": [
      "Salivary gland",
      "Prostate gland",
      "Thyroid gland",
      "Pituitary gland",
      "Parathyroid gland"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Thyroid gland"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which organ most common localization of fatty change?",
    "options": [
      "Liver",
      "Pancreas",
      "Stomach",
      "Brain",
      "Urinary Bladder"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": null
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 58-year-old woman who died of chronic alcohol intoxication, an autopsy revealed enlarged liver, soft consistency, and a yellowish color. Microscopically: in hepatocytes, the nuclei are displaced to the periphery, and in the cytoplasm - clear spaces. What type of dystrophy in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Fatty change",
      "Hyalinosis",
      "Mucoid change",
      "Fibrinoid change"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fatty change"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 48-year-old patient with glomerulonephritis has renal changes. Microscopically: pink formations in the form of drops in the epithelium of the kidney tubules. What pathological process developed in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulation of proteins",
      "Accumulation of lipids",
      "Accumulation of carbohydrates",
      "Accumulation of amyloid",
      "Accumulation of cholesterol"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Accumulation of proteins"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 68-year-old deceased had changes in the coronary vessels and aorta. Grossly: the walls of the vessels are thickened, hard, with plaques. What pathological process developed in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulation of proteins",
      "Accumulation of lipids",
      "Accumulation of carbohydrates",
      "Accumulation of amyloid",
      "Accumulation of cholesterol"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Accumulation of cholesterol"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 58-year-old man who died of chronic alcohol intoxication, an autopsy revealed changes in the liver. Microscopically: in hepatocytes amorphous formations of pink color. What type of dystrophy in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulation of proteins",
      "Accumulation of lipids",
      "Accumulation of carbohydrates",
      "Accumulation of amyloid",
      "Accumulation of cholesterol"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Accumulation of proteins"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 65-year-old man who died of chronic heart failure, an autopsy revealed changes in the myocardium. Grossly: enlarged, soft consistency, expanded cavities, «tiger effect» in myocardium. Microscopically: in myocardium cells the nuclei are displaced to the periphery, and in the cytoplasm clear spaces. What type of dystrophy in this case? ",
    "options": [
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Fatty change",
      "Hyalinosis",
      "Mucoid change",
      "Fibrinoid change"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fatty change"
  },
  {
    "question": "At autopsy of a 57-year-old man, who had suffered from pulmonary tuberculosis for a long time, revealed kidney changes: enlarged, yellowish-gray, hard, waxy appearance. What pathological process in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Necrosis",
      "Hyalinosis",
      "Hemochromatosis",
      "Hemosiderosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Amyloidosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 50-year-old patient suffering from hypertension died of cerebral hemorrhage. Microscopically revealed: the walls of the arterioles are thickened, represent a homogeneous mass of pink when stained with hematoxylin and eosin, the lumen of the vessels is narrowed. What type of dystrophy in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Fatty change",
      "Hyalinosis",
      "Hemochromatosis",
      "Hemosiderosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hyalinosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 50-year-old patient with chronic renal failure underwent biopsy. When staining with Congo-Red, it was revealed: extracellular, homogeneous, structure less, masses, red color. What type of dystrophy in this case? ",
    "options": [
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Fatty change",
      "Hyalinosis",
      "Hemochromatosis",
      "Hemosiderosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Amyloidosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a deceased patient suffering from rheumatic fever, microscopic examination of the mitral valve revealed: metachromasia and swelling of connective tissue fibers. What type of dystrophy in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Fatty change",
      "Hyalinosis",
      "Mucoid change",
      "Fibrinoid change"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mucoid change"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a deceased woman of 50 years old, often suffering from angina, changes in the mitral valve were found: deformation, the edges of the valve with homogeneous, translucent, solid formations of a whitish-gray color. What type of dystrophy in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Fatty change",
      "Hyalinosis",
      "Mucoid change",
      "Fibrinoid change"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hyalinosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of reversible process caused by accumulation of glycosaminoglycans in extracellular matrix due to the increase of vascular permeability?",
    "options": [
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Glycogenoses",
      "Hyalinosis",
      "Mucoid changes",
      "Fibrinoid changes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mucoid changes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of irreversible process caused by accumula­tion of proteins with high molecular weight associated with the destruction of connective tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Glycogenoses",
      "Hyalinosis",
      "Mucoid changes",
      "Fibrinoid changes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrinoid changes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of substance with fibrillary structure which forms under the pathological conditions?",
    "options": [
      "Reabsorbtion droplets",
      "Russell bodies",
      "Lipids",
      "Amyloid",
      "Calcificates"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Amyloid"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of pathologic proteinaceous substance, accumulating only between cells in different tissues and organs of the body?",
    "options": [
      "Glycogen",
      "Hyaline",
      "Water",
      "Amyloid",
      "Lipid"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Amyloid"
  },
  {
    "question": "What change grossly in the organs affected by amyloi­dosis does not occurs?",
    "options": [
      "Enlarged",
      "Hard",
      "Waxy in apperance",
      "Smooth",
      "Soft"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Soft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is name of specific method for diagnosis of amyloid in fresh tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Virchow test",
      "Rokitansky test",
      "Ewing test",
      "Halids test",
      "Masson test"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Virchow test"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of cause of obesity which associated with excessive nutrition?",
    "options": [
      "Primary",
      "Alimentary",
      "Cerebral",
      "Endocrine",
      "Hereditary"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alimentary"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the type of obesity characterized by deposition of fat in abdomen area?",
    "options": [
      "Upper type ",
      "Middle type ",
      "Lower type",
      "Simmetric type",
      "Diffuse type"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": null
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of the cells accumulating fat within the intimal layer of aorta and large arteries in atherosclerotic plaques?",
    "options": [
      "Fibroblasts",
      "Epithelial cells",
      "Foam cells",
      "Lymphocytes",
      "Leukocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Foam cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "What pathological process is characterized by derangements of glycogen metabolism?",
    "options": [
      "Atherosclerosis",
      "Diabetes mellitus",
      "Viral hepatitis",
      "Arterial hypertension",
      "Goiter"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Diabetes mellitus"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does extracellular accumulation differ from intracellular accumulation?",
    "options": [
      "Extracellular accumulation refers to the accumulation of substances outside of cells, while intracellular accumulation refers to the accumulation of substances inside of cells.",
      "Extracellular accumulation refers to the accumulation of substances inside of cells, while intracellular accumulation refers to the accumulation of substances outside of cells.",
      "Extracellular and intracellular accumulation are synonymous terms.",
      "Extracellular and intracellular accumulation refer to the same thing, but are used to describe different diseases.",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Extracellular accumulation refers to the accumulation of substances outside of cells, while intracellular accumulation refers to the accumulation of substances inside of cells."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a potential treatment option for a disease characterized by extracellular accumulation?",
    "options": [
      "Enzyme replacement therapy",
      "Gene therapy",
      "Immunotherapy",
      "Surgery to remove the accumulated material",
      "All of the above are potential treatment options"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "All of the above are potential treatment options"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a commonly used staining technique to visualize amyloid deposits in tissue samples?",
    "options": [
      "Hematoxylin and eosin (H&E) stain",
      "Gram stain",
      "Ziehl-Neelsen stain",
      "Congo red stain",
      "Wright's stain"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Congo red stain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following diseases is characterized by the accumulation of hyaline material in the glomeruli of the kidneys?",
    "options": [
      "Gaucher disease",
      "Alzheimer's disease",
      "Cystic fibrosis",
      "Nephrotic syndrome",
      "Fabry disease"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nephrotic syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient with a rare genetic disorder presents with extracellular accumulation of a specific type of protein. Which of the following treatments would be most effective in reducing the accumulation?",
    "options": [
      "Anti-inflammatory medication",
      "Antibiotics",
      "Enzyme replacement therapy",
      "Chemotherapy",
      "Radiation therapy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Enzyme replacement therapy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient presents with extracellular accumulation of lipids in their liver. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Atherosclerosis",
      "Steatohepatitis",
      "Wilson's disease",
      "Alcoholic liver disease",
      "Hemochromatosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Steatohepatitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient with a rare autoimmune disorder presents with extracellular accumulation of a specific type of antibody. Which of the following tests would be most useful in confirming the diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Complete blood count (CBC)",
      "Electrolyte panel",
      "Urinalysis",
      "Autoantibody panel",
      "Liver function tests"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Autoantibody panel"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following diseases is characterized by the accumulation of extracellular material in the liver?",
    "options": [
      "Cirrhosis",
      "Pancreatitis",
      "Asthma",
      "Arthritis",
      "Pneumonia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cirrhosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the genetic disorder characterized by the accumulation of glycosaminoglycans in the lysosomes of cells?",
    "options": [
      "Gaucher's disease",
      "Tay-Sachs disease",
      "Fabry disease",
      "Hurler syndrome",
      "Nephrotic syndrome"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hurler syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can extracellular accumulation contribute to the pathogenesis of a disease?",
    "options": [
      "By interfering with normal tissue structure and function",
      "By stimulating abnormal cell growth and proliferation",
      "By impairing the immune system's ability to fight infection",
      "By increasing blood flow to affecteda areas",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "By interfering with normal tissue structure and function"
  },
  {
    "question": "Accumulation of which pigment may leads to jaundice?",
    "options": [
      "Ferritin",
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Bilirubin",
      "Hemomelanin",
      "Porphyrin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bilirubin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Accumulation of which pigment may leads to decrease of blood pressure?",
    "options": [
      "Ferritin",
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Bilirubin",
      "Hemomelanin",
      "Porphyrin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ferritin"
  },
  {
    "question": "What causes of posthepatic jaundice?",
    "options": [
      "Obstruction of bile ducts by stones",
      "Hepatitis",
      "Heterohemotransfusions ",
      "Liver cirrhosis ",
      "Hemolytic disease of newborns"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Obstruction of bile ducts by stones"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which pigment derived from hemoglobin found in normal conditions?",
    "options": [
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Hematoidin",
      "Hemin",
      "Hemomelanin",
      "Porphyrin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hemosiderin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which pigment derived from hemoglobin found in normal conditions?",
    "options": [
      "Ferritin ",
      "Hematoidin",
      "Hemin",
      "Hemomelanin",
      "Porphyrin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ferritin "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which pigment derived from hemoglobin found in pathologic conditions? ",
    "options": [
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Porphyrin",
      "Ferritin ",
      "Bilirubin ",
      "Melanin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Porphyrin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which disorders cause by generalized melanin hyperpigmentation?",
    "options": [
      "Addison’s disease ",
      "Melanosis coli",
      "Lentigo",
      "Nevus",
      "Melanoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Addison’s disease "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term is used for general hypopigmentation by melanin?",
    "options": [
      "Leukoderma",
      "Albinism",
      "Vitiligo",
      "Cachexia",
      "Lentigo"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Albinism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which pigment is a result of reaction between hemoglobin and hydrochloric acid?",
    "options": [
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Hemin",
      "Ferritin",
      "Bilirubin",
      "Melanin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hemin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which pigment derived from hemoglobin found in pathologic conditions? ",
    "options": [
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Hematoidin",
      "Ferritin ",
      "Bilirubin",
      "Melanin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hematoidin"
  },
  {
    "question": "At 76-year-old patient has yellowness of the skin, intensely colored urine and discolored feces. Examination revealed a tumor of the common bile duct obturating its lumen. What pigment exchange disorder is there in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Hematoidin",
      "Hemomelanin",
      "Lipofuscin",
      "Bilirubin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lipofuscin"
  },
  {
    "question": "At 22-year-old patient has photosensitivity of skin, massive enlargement of liver with severe abdominal pain, red color of urine. What pigment exchange disorder is there in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Hematoidin",
      "Porphyrins",
      "Lipofuscin",
      "Bilirubin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Porphyrins"
  },
  {
    "question": "At 33-year-old patient have white skin color, blond hair, poor vision and severe photophobia. They are highly sensitive to sunlight. What pigment exchange disorder is there in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Hematoidin",
      "Porphyrins",
      "Melanin",
      "Bilirubin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Melanin"
  },
  {
    "question": "At 61-year-old patient died of cachexia (had cancer of the esophagus). An autopsy grossly:  dark brown heart and liver, decrease in size. Microscopically: cytoplasm of cardiomyocytes and hepatocytes around the nuclei revealed small brown pigment grains. What pigment is accumulated in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Hematoidin",
      "Hemomelanin",
      "Lipofuscin",
      "Bilirubin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lipofuscin"
  },
  {
    "question": "The biopsy was taken from a patient suffering from severe pain with swelling of the joints of the foot. Microscopically: the synovial membrane is infiltrated with lymphocytes, macrophages, cells of foreign bodies, and uric acid crystals are also found. What metabolic disorder typical for this pathology?",
    "options": [
      "Ferritin",
      "Nucleoproteins",
      "Glycoprotein",
      "Chromoproteins",
      "Lipoproteins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nucleoproteins"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient presents with hyperpigmentation on their face, neck, and arms. They report a history of chronic inflammation, such as from eczema or psoriasis. What is the most likely cause of their hyperpigmentation?",
    "options": [
      "Chronic inflammation",
      "Sun exposure",
      "Aging",
      "genetic ",
      "Previous injury or trauma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chronic inflammation"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient comes to you with dark spots on their skin. They report a history of a previous injury or trauma to the affected area. What is the most likely cause of their hyperpigmentation?",
    "options": [
      "Sun exposure",
      "Previous injury or trauma",
      "Aging",
      "genetic ",
      " Chronic kidney disease"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Previous injury or trauma"
  },
  {
    "question": "An autopsy of a deceased newborn who lived for 2 days revealed changes in the kidneys. Grossly: yellow-orange bands are found in the medulla of the kidneys. Microscopically: sodium urate and ammonium salts were found in the tubules and collecting ducts. What metabolic disorder typical for this pathology?",
    "options": [
      "Ferritin",
      "Nucleoproteins",
      "Glycoprotein",
      "Chromoproteins",
      "Lipoproteins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nucleoproteins"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient comes to you with dark patches on their skin. They report a history of chronic kidney disease. What is the most likely cause of their hyperpigmentation?",
    "options": [
      "Thyroid condition",
      "Sun exposure",
      "Previous injury or trauma",
      " Chronic kidney disease",
      "genetic "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Chronic kidney disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient presents with hyperpigmentation on their face and neck. They report a history of regular consumption of certain medications, such as nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). What is the most likely cause of their hyperpigmentation?",
    "options": [
      "Chronic inflammation",
      "Medication use",
      "genetic ",
      "Aging",
      "Sun exposure"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Medication use"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a deficiency disease caused by inadequate intake of vitamin C? ",
    "options": [
      "Beriberi",
      "Rickets",
      "Pellagra",
      "Scurvy",
      "Kwashiorkor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Scurvy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which environmental pathology is characterized by the abnormal accumulation of fluid in the lungs due to prolonged exposure to irritants? ",
    "options": [
      "Asthma",
      "Emphysema",
      "Pneumonia",
      "Bronchitis",
      "Pulmonary Edema"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pulmonary Edema"
  },
  {
    "question": "What environmental pathology is associated with prolonged exposure to high levels of lead in the environment? ",
    "options": [
      "Silicosis",
      "Asbestosis ",
      "Lead poisoning ",
      "Minamata disease ",
      "Black lung disease"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lead poisoning "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which nutritional pathology is a severe form of protein-energy malnutrition? ",
    "options": [
      "Marasmus",
      "Anemia",
      "Sickle cell disease ",
      "Celiac disease ",
      "Hypertension"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Marasmus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which environmental pathology is linked to prolonged exposure to radiation, especially in certain occupations like radiology? ",
    "options": [
      "Mesothelioma",
      "Leukemia",
      "Melanoma",
      "Osteosarcoma",
      "Thyroid cancer"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Leukemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which environmental pathology is caused by the inhalation of asbestos fibers, leading to lung scarring and breathing difficulties? ",
    "options": [
      "Silicosis ",
      "Asbestosis ",
      "Lead poisoning ",
      "Minamata disease ",
      "Black lung disease"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Asbestosis "
  },
  {
    "question": "What nutritional pathology results from a severe deficiency of vitamin D, leading to softening and weakening of bones? ",
    "options": [
      "Beriberi ",
      "Rickets ",
      "Pellagra",
      "Scurvy",
      " Kwashiorkor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rickets "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which environmental pathology is associated with contaminated water sources, causing severe gastrointestinal symptoms and dehydration? ",
    "options": [
      "Dysentery",
      "Cholera",
      "Typhoid fever ",
      "Botulism",
      "Giardiasis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cholera"
  },
  {
    "question": "What nutritional pathology is characterized by an insufficient intake of iodine, leading to an enlargement of the thyroid gland? ",
    "options": [
      "Cretinism",
      "Goiter ",
      "Hyperthyroidism",
      "Hypothyroidism",
      "Thyroiditis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Goiter "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which environmental pathology results from chronic exposure to mercury, causing neurological symptoms and impairments? ",
    "options": [
      "Minamata disease ",
      "Asbestosis",
      "Silicosis",
      "Black lung disease ",
      "Lead poisoning"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Minamata disease "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used for congenital incomplete development of thymus?",
    "options": [
      "Dysplasia ",
      "Hypoplasia ",
      "Neoplasia ",
      "Metaplasia",
      "Aplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypoplasia "
  },
  {
    "question": "What term is used to mean the replacement of one type of adult cells (epithelial or mesenchymal) with adult cells of another type?",
    "options": [
      "Metaplasia ",
      "Dysplasia ",
      "Anaplasia ",
      " Hyperplasia ",
      "Atrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Metaplasia "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used to mean an increase in the number of cells in an organ or tissue due to mitotic division, leading to an increase in the organ or tissue?",
    "options": [
      " Metaplasia ",
      "Dysplasia ",
      "Anaplasia ",
      "Hyperplasia ",
      "Atrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hyperplasia "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used to mean an increase in cell size and, as a result, an increase in organ size due to an increased synthesis of structural proteins and organelles?",
    "options": [
      " Metaplasia ",
      "Dysplasia ",
      "Atrophy",
      "Anaplasia ",
      "Hypertrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypertrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is name of atrophy of organ due to prolonged decrease of functional activity? ",
    "options": [
      "Neuropathic atrophy",
      "Endocrine atrophy",
      "Ischemic atrophy",
      "Disuse atrophy",
      "Pressure atrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Disuse atrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is name of atrophy of organ due to gradual decrease of blood supply?",
    "options": [
      "Endocrine atrophy",
      "Neuropathic atrophy",
      "Disuse atrophy",
      "Pressure atrophy",
      "Ischemic atrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ischemic atrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is name hypertrophy of one of paired organ after removal of another organ?",
    "options": [
      "Concentric",
      "Excentric",
      "Controlateral",
      "Endocrine",
      "Overworkloading"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Controlateral"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of atrophy of organ due to loss of trophic hormones?",
    "options": [
      "Endocrine atrophy",
      "Neuropathic atrophy",
      "Disuse atrophy",
      "Pressure atrophy",
      "Ischemic atrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Endocrine atrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of atrophy of organ due to loss of nerve supple?",
    "options": [
      "Endocrine atrophy",
      "Neuropathic atrophy",
      "Disuse atrophy",
      "Pressure atrophy",
      "Ischemic atrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Neuropathic atrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of atrophy of organ due to prolonged compression of organ?",
    "options": [
      "Endocrine atrophy",
      "Neuropathic atrophy",
      "Disuse atrophy",
      "Pressure atrophy",
      "Ischemic atrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pressure atrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "An autopsy of a deceased from chronic renal failure revealed one kidney measuring 15x10x10 cm, the pelvis of which is stretched, filled with urine, the thickness of the kidney substance is 0.5 cm. The ureter is narrowed. What is the type of atrophy in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Endocrine ",
      "Neuropathic ",
      "Disuse ",
      "Pressure",
      "Ischemic "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "The patient's right kidney was removed 10 years ago due to tumor. Ultrasound examination revealed increase in the size of the left kidney. What is the pathological process in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Hypertrophy",
      "Anaplasia ",
      " Metaplasia ",
      "Dysplasia ",
      "Atrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypertrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "The young athlete died suddenly. An autopsy revealed an increase in the weight of the heart (650.0 grams); an increase in its size (12.0 x 12.0 x 10.0 cm); thickening of the left ventricle wall (2.0 cm). the myocardium is flabby, pale red. The heart cavities are enlarged. Which is the pathological process in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Anaplasia ",
      "Hypertrophy",
      "Dysplasia ",
      "Atrophy",
      " Metaplasia "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypertrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "An autopsy of a deceased from chronic renal failure revealed one kidney measuring 15x10x10 cm, the pelvis of which was stretched, filled with urine, the thickness of the kidney substance was 0.5 cm. What is the name of this pathological process?",
    "options": [
      "Dysplasia",
      "Atrophy",
      "Metaplasia",
      "Hypertrophy",
      "Hyperplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Atrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "An autopsy of a 49-year-old man who died of stomach cancer revealed a sharp emaciation, a decrease in the thickness of subcutaneous fatty tissue, muscle atrophy, dry and flabby skin. The internal organs are reduced in size. Microscopic examination of the parenchymal cells of the internal organs revealed a large amount of lipofuscin. What type of atrophy developed in this case?",
    "options": [
      "central\n",
      "peripheral\n",
      "cachexia\n",
      "alimentary\n",
      "hormonal"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": null
  },
  {
    "question": "Morphological examination of a biopsy of the gastric mucosa of a 56-year-old patient revealed glands lined with colonic-type epithelium. What adaptive process has developed in the gastric mucosa?\n\n",
    "options": [
      "Hyperplasia\n",
      "atrophy\n",
      "metaplasia\n",
      "hypoplasia\n",
      "dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": null
  },
  {
    "question": "Morphological examination of the biopsy specimen of the mucous membrane of the vaginal part of the cervix of a 34-year-old patient revealed the following changes in the stratified squamous epithelium: loss of polarity of the epithelium with a preserved basement membrane, cell polymorphism with nuclear hyperchromia and the presence of a large number of mitoses. How this process called?",
    "options": [
      "Hyperplasia\n",
      "atrophy\n",
      "metaplasia\n",
      "hypoplasia\n",
      "dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "dysplasia"
  },
  {
    "question": "An autopsy of the deceased, who had been suffering from arterial hypertension for a long time, revealed an enlarged heart, weighing 415 g, with an increase in the thickness of the left ventricular wall up to 1.5 cm. What is the name of this process?",
    "options": [
      "hypertrophy\n",
      "atrophy\n",
      "metaplasia\n",
      "hypoplasia\n",
      "dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypertrophy\n"
  },
  {
    "question": "A biopsy of the bladder mucosa was taken from a patient suffering from chronic cystitis. Microscopically: foci of stratified squamous non-keratinizing epithelium. What is the pathological process in this case?",
    "options": [
      "hypertrophy\n",
      "atrophy\n",
      "metaplasia\n",
      "hypoplasia\n",
      "dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "metaplasia\n"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 35-year-old patient developed paralysis of the lower extremities after a car accident. After 4 years, the muscles of the lower extremities began to decrease in volume and became flabby. What pathological process in this case?",
    "options": [
      "atrophy\n",
      "hypertrophy\n",
      "dysplasia",
      "hypoplasia\n",
      "metaplasia\n"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "atrophy\n"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these characterizes arterial hyperemia as local circulation disorder?",
    "options": [
      "increased blood inflow",
      "decreased blood outflow",
      "decreased  blood inflow",
      "increased blood outflow",
      "low inflow and outflow"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased blood inflow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these is characteristic sign of arterial hyperemia in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "redness",
      "cyanosis",
      "paleness",
      "edema ",
      "low local temperature"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "redness"
  },
  {
    "question": "In arterial hyperemia can be seen which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "edema",
      "decreased turgor",
      "pulsation",
      "cyanosis",
      "pallor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "pulsation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is related to etiology of venous hyperemia?",
    "options": [
      "right heart failure",
      "stimulation of vasodilators",
      "left heart failure",
      "stimulation of vasoconstrictors",
      "block of vasodilators"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "right heart failure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these is characteristic sign of venous hyperemia in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "decreased rate of blood flow",
      "increased rate of blood flow",
      "increased blood oxygenation",
      "pulsation",
      "increased tissue turgor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "decreased rate of blood flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these is causative factor for venous hyperemia development in local circulation disorder?",
    "options": [
      "arterial thrombosis",
      "gas embolism",
      "vein compression",
      "atherosclerosis",
      "left heart failure"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "vein compression"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ischemia is local circulation disorder due to which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "arterial thrombosis",
      "right heart failure",
      "venous thrombosis",
      "vasodilation",
      "vein compression"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "arterial thrombosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which feature characterizes ischemia as a local circulation disorder?",
    "options": [
      "increased blood flow",
      "edema",
      "pallor",
      "cyanosis",
      "redness"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "pallor"
  },
  {
    "question": "In ischemia can be seen which one of local circulation disorders signs?",
    "options": [
      "increased number of functional vessels",
      "decreased number of functional vessels",
      "increased tissue turgor",
      "increased lymph flow",
      "increased oxygenation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "decreased number of functional vessels"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of local circulation disorders Claude-Bernar experiment shows?",
    "options": [
      "ischemia",
      "neuroparalytic hyperemia",
      "neurotonical hyperemia",
      "stasis",
      "venous hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "neuroparalytic hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these can cause vasodilation in local  circulation disorder?",
    "options": [
      "catecholamines",
      "angiotensin",
      "prostaglandins",
      "vasopressin",
      "epinephrine"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "prostaglandins"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is mechanism of neurotonical arterial hyperemia?",
    "options": [
      "block of vasodilators",
      "block of vasoconstrictors",
      "stimulation of vasodilators",
      "stimulation of vasoconstrictors",
      "cutting of nervus vagus"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "stimulation of vasodilators"
  },
  {
    "question": "Macro signs of arterial hyperemia is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "low local temperature",
      "increased tissue turgor",
      "decreased number of capillaries",
      "increased number of capillaries",
      "fast blood flow"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased tissue turgor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Micro sign of arterial hyperemia is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "redness",
      "increased tissue turgor",
      "low local temperature",
      "fast blood flow",
      "slow blood flow"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "fast blood flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there are increased tissue turgor and local temperature, which one of these local  circulation disorders is it?",
    "options": [
      "ischemia ",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "stasis",
      "embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "arterial hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there are decreased tissue turgor and local temperature, which one of these local  circulation disorders is it?",
    "options": [
      "ischemia ",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "stasis",
      "embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ischemia "
  },
  {
    "question": "Positive consequence of arterial hyperemia is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "fibrosis",
      "hemorrhage",
      "increased oxygenation",
      "sludge",
      "edema"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased oxygenation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Negative consequence of arterial hyperemia is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "fibrosis",
      "hemorrhage",
      "increased oxygenation",
      "sludge",
      "edema"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hemorrhage"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is mechanism of neuroparalytic arterial hyperemia?",
    "options": [
      "stimulation of vasodilators",
      "block of vasoconstrictors",
      "stimulation of vasoconstrictors",
      "block of vasodilators",
      "cutting of nervus vagus"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "block of vasoconstrictors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Macro sign of venous hyperemia in local circulation disorders  is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "slow blood flow",
      "twisted veins",
      "pulsation",
      "capillary distension",
      "decreased lymph flow"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "twisted veins"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these factors causes increased number of RBCs in long term hypoxia? ",
    "options": [
      "prolactin",
      "erythropoietin",
      "glucagon",
      "prostaglandin",
      "gastrin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "erythropoietin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is the short term compensation response during hypoxia? ",
    "options": [
      "tachycardia",
      "hypertrophy of heart",
      "capillary hyperplasia",
      "increased RBCs number",
      "alveolar hyperplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "tachycardia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which one is long term compensation response to hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "hyperventilation",
      "tachycardia",
      "reticulocytes in the blood",
      "tachypnea",
      "increased RBCs number"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased RBCs number"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is short term compensatory mechanism to exogenous hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "increased mitochondrial density within the cell",
      "polycythemia",
      "BM hyperplasia",
      "tachycardia",
      "alveolar hyperplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "tachycardia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following is long term compensatory mechanism to exogenous hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "hyperventilation",
      "tachycardia",
      "polycytemia",
      "pulmonary hypertension",
      "tachypnea"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "polycytemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is compensatory mechanism of adaptation to high altitude hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "increased heart rate",
      "heart hypertrophy",
      "heart failure",
      "lung edema",
      "increased respiration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "heart hypertrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which one is compensatory mechanism of adaptation to high altitude hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "increased blood flow rate",
      "increased heart rate",
      "BM hyperplasia",
      "lung edema",
      "increased respiratory rate"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "BM hyperplasia"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main buffer systems in the human body are not:",
    "options": [
      "Bicarbonate buffer system ",
      "chloride buffer system",
      "Phosphate buffer system ",
      "Hemoglobin buffer system ",
      "Protein buffer system"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "chloride buffer system"
  },
  {
    "question": "The role of physiological regulation of CBS is to remove excess acids or bases due to",
    "options": [
      "spleen",
      "endocrine glands",
      "kidney",
      "thymus",
      "pancreas"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": null
  },
  {
    "question": "Disorders of ABB include",
    "options": [
      "arthrosis",
      "hookworm",
      "asbestosis",
      "alkolosis",
      "alcoholism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "alkolosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following changes is typical sign of ABB disorder in exogenous hypobaric hypoxia?",
    "options": [
      "hypoxemia",
      "respiratory acidosis",
      "respiratory alkalosis",
      "metabolic acidosis",
      "metabolic alkalosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "respiratory alkalosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "If examination of blood shows hypocapnia, what type of hypoxia it can be?",
    "options": [
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "blood hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "tissue hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "exogenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "If patient has increased arterio-venous difference of O2, what is more probable reason for this type  of hypoxia? ",
    "options": [
      "carbon monoxide poisoning",
      "heart failure",
      "disorder of external breathing ",
      "cyanide poisoning",
      "iron deficiency"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "heart failure"
  },
  {
    "question": "If patient has decreased arterio-venous difference of O2, which type of hypoxia more probably is it?",
    "options": [
      "hemic hypoxia",
      "respiratory hypoxia",
      "histogenous hypoxia",
      "exogenous hypoxia",
      "circulatory hypoxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "histogenous hypoxia"
  },
  {
    "question": "ABB violations include:",
    "options": [
      "violations of cellular potential",
      "violations of nuclear permeability",
      "violation of ADP production",
      "disturbances in hormonal activity",
      "disturbances in enzyme activity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "disturbances in enzyme activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "CHARACTERISTICS OF RESPIRATORY ACIDosis include",
    "options": [
      "Alveolar ventilation is primary increase",
      "Pa CO2 decreases>45 mmHg ",
      "Blood pH is norm or >7,35",
      "Urine pH is acidic    < 6",
      "HCO3 in the blood is reduced"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Urine pH is acidic    < 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "characteristics of respiratory alkalosis include",
    "options": [
      "Alveolar ventilation is the primary reduction",
      "Pa CO2 increases >35 mm Hg. ",
      "Blood HCO3 is increased",
      "Blood HCO3 is increased",
      "Urine pH is acidic    < 6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blood HCO3 is increased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Characteristics of metabolic acidosis (renal) include",
    "options": [
      "Alveolar ventilation is secondary compensatory decreases",
      "Pa CO2 is decreased",
      "Blood pH is norm or >7,35",
      "Blood HCO3 is increased",
      "Urine pH is acidic    < 6"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pa CO2 is decreased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Metabolic acidosis(non-renal) includes",
    "options": [
      "Alveolar ventilation is secondary compensatory increased",
      "Pa CO2 is increased",
      "Blood pH is norm or >7,45",
      "Blood HCO3- is increased",
      "Urine pH is primaryalkaline >7.0"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Alveolar ventilation is secondary compensatory increased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Characteristics of metabolic alkalosis(renal) includes",
    "options": [
      "Alveolar ventilation is secondary compensatory increased",
      "Pa CO2 is decreased",
      "Blood pH is decreased",
      "Blood HCO3- is decreased",
      "Urine pH is primary"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Urine pH is primary"
  },
  {
    "question": "Typical sodium-water imbalances can be divided into two categories.",
    "options": [
      " Proportional changes in sodium and water and disproportional changes in sodium and water",
      "Directly proportional changes in sodium and water and inversely proportional changes in sodium and water",
      "Proportional changes in sodium and water and directly proportional changes in sodium and water",
      "Disproportional changes in sodium and water and inversely proportional changes in sodium and water",
      "right and wrong"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Proportional changes in sodium and water and disproportional changes in sodium and water"
  },
  {
    "question": "Proportional changes in sodium and water include",
    "options": [
      "isotonic dehydration ",
      "hypotonic (hypoosmotic) dehydration ",
      "hypertonic (hyperosmotic) dehydration ",
      "hypotonic (hypoosmotic) hyperhydration",
      "hypertonic (hyperosmotic) hyperhydration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "isotonic dehydration "
  },
  {
    "question": "Disproportional changes in sodium and water include",
    "options": [
      "isotonic dehydration ",
      "isotonic hyperhydration",
      "hypotonic (hypoosmotic) dehydration",
      "hypotonic (hypoosmotic) dehydration ",
      "isotonic hypohydration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypotonic (hypoosmotic) dehydration "
  },
  {
    "question": "Edema is:",
    "options": [
      "The transfer of water between the vascular and mesenchymal compartments occurs at the capillary level.",
      "The transfer of water between the vascular and lymphatic sections occurs at the capillary level.",
      "The transfer of water between the vascular and interstitial compartments occurs at the capillary level. ",
      "The transfer of water between the vascular and parenchymal sections occurs at the capillary level.",
      "The transfer of water between the vascular and endothelial sections occurs at the capillary level."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "The transfer of water between the vascular and interstitial compartments occurs at the capillary level. "
  },
  {
    "question": "There are four main forces that control the movement of water between the capillary and interstitial spaces:",
    "options": [
      "the capillary filtration pressure",
      "capillary colloid-oncotic pressure",
      "interstitial or tissue osmotic pressure",
      "interstitial colloid-oncotic pressure",
      "hydrostatic pressure"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "the capillary filtration pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "The mechanism of edema occurrence is divided into the following:",
    "options": [
      "reduce the pressure of capillary filtration,",
      "Increase the pressure of capillary filtration,",
      "reduce capillary colloid-oncotic pressure",
      "increase the pressure of capillary",
      "reduce capillary permeability,"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increase the pressure of capillary"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which condition cannot be attributed to edema?",
    "options": [
      "Ascites",
      "hydropericardium",
      "hydroperitoneum",
      "hydrothorax",
      "varicocele"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "varicocele"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most common causes of isotonic overhydration are",
    "options": [
      "slow parenteral administration of small amounts of solutions ",
      "Water and urine retention and the development of general edema occur against the background of heart failure",
      "Water and urine retention and the development of general edema occur against the background of cerebral insufficienc",
      "Water and urine retention and the development of general edema occur against the background of  palmonaryl insufficienc",
      "Water and urine retention and the development of general edema occur against the background of spleenl insufficienc"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Water and urine retention and the development of general edema occur against the background of heart failure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Edema cannot be due to the development mechanism",
    "options": [
      "cordial",
      "pulmonary",
      "shock",
      "hepatic",
      "brain"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hunger edema according to the developmental mechanism is",
    "options": [
      "renal",
      "pulmonary",
      "hepatic",
      "cordial",
      "brain"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "renal"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of hemorrhage with regular borders and destruction of tissue? ",
    "options": [
      "Hematoma",
      "Hemorrhagic infiltration",
      "Petechiae",
      "Purpura",
      "Ecchymoses"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hematoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used for hemorrhage from respiratory system?",
    "options": [
      "Epistaxis",
      "Haemoptoe",
      "Haematemesis ",
      "Maelena",
      "Metrorrhagia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Haemoptoe"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whish term used for the accumulation of fluid in the pleural cavities? ",
    "options": [
      "Hydropericardium",
      "Hydrothorax",
      "Ascites",
      "Anasarca",
      "Hydrocele"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hydrothorax"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used for the accumulation of fluid in the peritoneal cavity?",
    "options": [
      "Hydrothorax",
      "Hydropericardium",
      "Ascites",
      "Anasarca",
      "Hydrocele"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ascites"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used to refer to generalized edema subcutaneous tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Hydropericardium",
      "Hydrothorax",
      "Ascites",
      "Anasarca",
      "Hydrocele"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Anasarca"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which pigment is accumulated in the lungs in brown induration?",
    "options": [
      "Hemin",
      "Hemosiderin",
      "Hemomelanin",
      "Melanin",
      "Bilirubin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hemosiderin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used for hemorrhage from urinary system? ",
    "options": [
      "Epistaxis",
      "Haemoptoe",
      "Haematemesis",
      "Haematuria",
      "Metrorrhagia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Haematuria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used for accumulation of blood in the joint cavity?",
    "options": [
      "Hemopericardium",
      "Hemothorax",
      "Hemoperitoneum",
      "Hemarthrosis",
      "Hematoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hemarthrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term used for small (3-5 mm) hemorrhages into skin, mucous membranes or serosal surfaces?  ",
    "options": [
      "Hematoma",
      "Hemorrhagic infiltration",
      "Petechiae",
      "Purpura",
      "Ecchymoses"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Purpura"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term used for the loss of blood supply of organs and tissues?",
    "options": [
      "Necrosis",
      "Hyperemia",
      "Ischemia",
      "Edema",
      "Congestion"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ischemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Brown induration is a type of chronic venous congestion occurs in",
    "options": [
      "Liver",
      "Heart",
      "Spleen",
      "Kidney",
      "Lung"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lung"
  },
  {
    "question": "Morphologic changes in the lungs due to chronic venous hyperemia – ",
    "options": [
      "Edema",
      "Congestive hyperemia",
      "Brown induration",
      "Congestive induration",
      "Nutmeg cirrhosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brown induration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hemorrhage from nasal cavity is called:",
    "options": [
      "Maelena",
      "Haemoptoe",
      "Haematemesis",
      "Epistaxis",
      "Metrorrhagia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Epistaxis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wha is the certain variant of edematous fluid containment increasing?",
    "options": [
      "hematoma",
      "ascites",
      "petechia",
      "exicosis",
      "hemothorax"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ascites"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term ascites means: ",
    "options": [
      "Accumulation of fluid in the pleural cavities",
      "Accumulation of fluid in the pericardial cavity",
      "Accumulation of fluid in the peritoneal cavity",
      "Generalized edemawith profound subcutaneous tissue swelling",
      "Accumulation of fluid in the nasal cavity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Accumulation of fluid in the peritoneal cavity"
  },
  {
    "question": "what is the causes of  local vacant hyperemia?",
    "options": [
      "Compression of arteries by tumor",
      "Decreasing of barometric pressure",
      "Obturation of arteries by thrombus",
      "Irritation of vasorelaxant nerves",
      "Increasing of barometric pressure"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Decreasing of barometric pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cyanotic induration of kidney is characterized by:",
    "options": [
      "Enlarged, hard, brown",
      "Enlarged, hard, blue-red",
      "Small. soft, red",
      "Small, hard, red-brown",
      "Enlarged, soft, brown"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Enlarged, hard, blue-red"
  },
  {
    "question": "Causes of corrosion of the vessel wall?",
    "options": [
      "Atherosclerosis",
      "Inflammation",
      "Vascular abnormalities",
      "Hypoxia",
      "Intoxication"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Inflammation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term hydrothorax means:",
    "options": [
      "Accumulation of fluid in the pleural cavities",
      "Accumulation of fluid in the pericardial cavity",
      "Accumulation of fluid in the peritoneal cavity",
      "Generalized edemawith profound subcutaneous tissue swelling",
      "Accumulation of fluid in the nasal cavity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Accumulation of fluid in the pleural cavities"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term anasarca means:",
    "options": [
      "Accumulation of fluid in the pleural cavities",
      "Accumulation of fluid in the pericardial cavity",
      "Accumulation of fluid in the peritoneal cavity",
      "Generalized edemawith profound subcutaneous tissue swelling",
      "Accumulation of fluid in the nasal cavity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Generalized edemawith profound subcutaneous tissue swelling"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30-year-old patient underwent subclavian catheterization for the purpose of infusion therapy of severe typhoid fever. This condition was complicated by the formation of a parietal thrombus in the right subclavian vein and the development of thromboembolism of the branches of the pulmonary artery. What is the term used for the adverse effect of this treatment? ",
    "options": [
      "Etiology",
      "Pathogenesis",
      "Morphogenesis",
      "Sanogenesis",
      "Iatrogeny"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Iatrogeny"
  },
  {
    "question": "The 43-year-old patient, suffering from gastric ulcer, was died of intoxication due to diffuse purulent peritonitis, which developed as a result of ulcer perforation. What is the term used for the mechanism of the patient's death?",
    "options": [
      "Etiology",
      "Pathogenesis",
      "Morphogenesis",
      "Sanogenesis",
      "Thanatogenesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Thanatogenesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an examination of the cadaver a 62 years-old man, died from chronic heart failure, revealed generalized edema in profound subcutaneous tissue. Which type of hemodynamic disorders occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Embolism",
      "Ischemia ",
      "Ascites ",
      "Anasarca",
      "Infarction "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Anasarca"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient suffered of gastric ulcer was died of gastric hemorrhage. An autopsy showed chronic gastric ulcer in pyloric area and stomach and intestine filled with blood. What is the cause of the bleeding?",
    "options": [
      "Rupture of the vessel wall",
      "Increased permeability of the vessel wall",
      "Corrosion of the vessel wall",
      "Inflammation of vessel wall",
      "Vascular atherosclerosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Corrosion of the vessel wall"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient suffered of arterial hyprtension was suddenly died. An autopsy showed massive intracerebral hemorrhage in the right hemosphere of the brain What is the cause of the hemorrhage?",
    "options": [
      "Rupture of the vessel wall",
      "Increased permeability of the vessel wall",
      "Corrosion of the vessel wall",
      "Inflammation of vessel wall",
      "Vascular atherosclerosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rupture of the vessel wall"
  },
  {
    "question": "Patient 63 years old suffered of rheumatic valvular disease, was died of cardiopulmonary insufficiency. At autopsy: the lungs are enlarged, heavy, brown in color, hard in consistency. Which type of hemodynamic disorders occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "General arterial hyperemia",
      "Local arterial hyperemia",
      "Collateral hyperemia",
      "Chronic venous hyperemia",
      "Acute venous hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chronic venous hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Patient 52 years old suffered of cardiomyopathy was died of cardiopulmonary insufficiency. An autopsy revealed changes in the liver. Grossly: liver enlarged in size and weight, hard, with on cut surface – nutmeg appearance. Which type of hemodynamic disorders occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "General arterial hyperemia",
      "Local arterial hyperemia",
      "Collateral hyperemia",
      "Chronic venous hyperemia",
      "Acute venous hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chronic venous hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 66-year-old patient suffered from chronic ischemic heart disease died from chronic heart failure accompanied by chronic venous hyperemia of internal organs. At autopsy: the lung tissue is brown, hard, airless. Microscopically: accumulation of hemosiderin and fibrosis of the lung tissue are determined. What term is used for this pathological process in lungs?",
    "options": [
      "Nutmeg lungs",
      "Cirrhosis of lung",
      "Congestive induration",
      "Brown induration",
      "Muscat cirrhosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brown induration"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 52 year-old man suffering from liver cirrhosis underwent laparocentesis: 6 liters of fluid was removed. After manipulation patient died away. Which type of hyperemia occurred in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Neurovascular",
      "Inflammatory",
      "Postanemic",
      "Vacatus",
      "Collateral"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Postanemic"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 63-year-old patient who suffered from myocardial infarction and died from  acute heart failure. During autopsy was revealed: defect of the wall of left ventricle and blood in the pericardial cavity. Which term is used for this type of hemorrhage?",
    "options": [
      "Hemothorax",
      "Hematomesis",
      "Hemarthrosis",
      "Hemoperitoneum",
      "Hemopericardium "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hemopericardium "
  },
  {
    "question": "Virchow’s triad is etiology of which one of local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "thrombosis",
      "ischemia ",
      "pulmonary embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "thrombosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Virchow’s triad is etiology of one of local circulation disorders which includes what one of following signs?",
    "options": [
      "hypercoagubility",
      "hypocoagubility",
      "fast blood flow",
      "smoot vessel wall",
      "low oxyhemoglobin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypercoagubility"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate what one of following signs Virchow’s triad, as etiology of one of local circulation disorders, includes?",
    "options": [
      "smoot vessel wall",
      "injured vessel wall",
      "hypocoagubility",
      "fast blood flow",
      "low oxyhemoglobin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "injured vessel wall"
  },
  {
    "question": "What one of following signs Virchow’s triad, as etiology of one of local circulation disorders, includes?",
    "options": [
      "slow blood flow",
      "fast blood flow",
      "hypocoagubility",
      "low oxyhemoglobin",
      "smoot vessel wall"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "slow blood flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is the positive fate of thrombus in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "propagation",
      "recanalization",
      "suppurative lysis",
      "detachment",
      "embolization"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "recanalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is the negative fate of thrombus in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "propagation",
      "lysis",
      "recanalization",
      "organization",
      "melting"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "propagation"
  },
  {
    "question": "DIC syndrome starts from which one of following events?",
    "options": [
      "massive tissue injury",
      "massive fibrinolysis",
      "acceleration of blood flow",
      "massive hypocoagulation",
      "local vessel injury"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "massive tissue injury"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called first stage of DIC syndrome?",
    "options": [
      "hypocoagulation",
      "massive fibrinolysis",
      "hypercoagulation",
      "consumption coagulopathy",
      "intoxication"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypercoagulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called third stage of DIC syndrome?",
    "options": [
      "recovery stage",
      "hypercoagulation",
      "consumption coagulopathy",
      "hypocoagulation",
      "intoxication"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypocoagulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called first stage of DIC syndrome?",
    "options": [
      "hypocoagulation",
      "massive fibrinolysis",
      "hypercoagulation",
      "consumption coagulopathy",
      "intoxication"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypercoagulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is consequence of arterial thrombosis in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "pulmonary embolism",
      "ascites",
      "ischemia",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ischemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is consequence of venous thrombosis in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "venous hyperemia",
      "ischemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "stroke",
      "heart attack"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "venous hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one is consequence of venous thrombosis in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "ascites",
      "stroke",
      "heart attack ",
      "ischemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ascites"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embolic stroke is result of which one of local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "pulmonary embolism",
      "arterial thrombosis",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "venous thrombosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "arterial thrombosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these thrombi locations is the highest risk for thromboembolism of pulmonary artery?",
    "options": [
      "thrombi in left heart chambers",
      "thrombi in deep veins of legs",
      "thrombi in aorta",
      "thrombi in pulmonary veins",
      "thrombi in vena portae"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "thrombi in deep veins of legs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is consequence of arterial thrombosis in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "pulmonary embolism",
      "ascites",
      "ischemia",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ischemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is consequence of venous thrombosis in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "venous hyperemia",
      "ischemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "stroke",
      "heart attack"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "venous hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one is consequence of venous thrombosis in local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "ascites",
      "stroke",
      "heart attack ",
      "ischemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ascites"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embolic stroke is result of which one of local circulation disorders?",
    "options": [
      "pulmonary embolism",
      "arterial thrombosis",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "venous thrombosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "arterial thrombosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air decreased oxygen in mountain high altitude  causes which one of compensatory reaction?",
    "options": [
      "hypoventilation",
      "hyperventilation",
      "uneven ventilation",
      "diffusion disturbance",
      "stopping of ventilation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hyperventilation"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is increased numder of functional capillaries, which type of local circulation disorders it can be?",
    "options": [
      "ischemia ",
      "arterial thrombosis",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "gas embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "arterial hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a diver undergoes decompression which types of emboli can presence in his blood?",
    "options": [
      "air bubbles",
      "nitrogen bubbles ",
      "carbon bubbles",
      "oxigen bubbles",
      "carbon dioxide bubbles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "nitrogen bubbles "
  },
  {
    "question": "When patient undergoes injury of jugular veins which types of emboli can presence in his blood?",
    "options": [
      "air bubbles",
      "nitrogen bubbles ",
      "carbon bubbles",
      "oxigen bubbles",
      "carbon dioxide bubbles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "air bubbles"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a diver undergoes decompression which types of emboli can presence in his blood?",
    "options": [
      "air bubbles",
      "nitrogen bubbles ",
      "carbon bubbles",
      "oxigen bubbles",
      "carbon dioxide bubbles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "nitrogen bubbles "
  },
  {
    "question": "When patient undergoes injury of jugular veins which types of emboli can presence in his blood?",
    "options": [
      "air bubbles",
      "nitrogen bubbles ",
      "carbon bubbles",
      "oxigen bubbles",
      "carbon dioxide bubbles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "air bubbles"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is not change in number of functional capillaries, which type of local circulation disorders it can be?",
    "options": [
      "ischemia ",
      "arterial thrombosis",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "gas embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "venous hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is increased numder of functional capillaries, which type of local circulation disorders it can be?",
    "options": [
      "ischemia ",
      "arterial thrombosis",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "gas embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "arterial hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which disorder of local circulation will be distention and overfilling of capillaries?",
    "options": [
      "stasis",
      "ischemia ",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "gas embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "venous hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "During ischemia will be pale color of tissue due to which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "increased number of functional capillaries",
      "increased hemoglobin level",
      "reduced hemoglobignal level",
      "increased oxyhemoglobin",
      "decreased  number of functional capillaries"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "decreased  number of functional capillaries"
  },
  {
    "question": "When patient undergoes injury of jugular veins which types of emboli can presence in his blood?",
    "options": [
      "air bubbles",
      "nitrogen bubbles ",
      "carbon bubbles",
      "oxigen bubbles",
      "carbon dioxide bubbles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "air bubbles"
  },
  {
    "question": "A brief loss of consciousness leading to loss of muscle tone is which one of these life- threatening states?",
    "options": [
      "coma",
      "shock",
      "collapse",
      "syncope",
      "stupor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "syncope"
  },
  {
    "question": "A state of unconsciousness during prolonged time due to cerebral cortex failure is which one of these life- threatening states?",
    "options": [
      "coma",
      "shock",
      "collapse",
      "syncope",
      "stupor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "coma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Disturbance between the lumen of vessels and the blood volume  in them due to orthostatic position is which one of these life- threatening states?",
    "options": [
      "coma",
      "shock",
      "collapse",
      "syncope",
      "stupor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "collapse"
  },
  {
    "question": "Circulatory failure leading to severe generalized deficit of tissues perfusion is which one of these life- threatening states?",
    "options": [
      "coma",
      "shock",
      "collapse",
      "syncope",
      "stupor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is example of hypovolemic shock?",
    "options": [
      "Anaphylactic shock",
      "Traumatic shock",
      "Hemorrhagic shock",
      "Cardiogenic shock",
      "Septic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hemorrhagic shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of following is example of hypovolemic shock?",
    "options": [
      "Burn shock",
      "Anaphylactic shock",
      "Traumatic shock",
      "Cardiogenic shock",
      "Septic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Burn shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sepsis can cause which one of following types of shock?",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "dehydration shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "distributive shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is typical trigger mechanism of shock development?",
    "options": [
      "deficient afferent impulses",
      "excessive afferent impulses",
      "activation of hypophyseal-corticoadrenal system",
      "large amount of catecholamine releasing ",
      "Small amount of catecholamine releasing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "excessive afferent impulses"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate what is feature of intermediate (progressive) stage of shock?",
    "options": [
      "“ shock kidney” development",
      "an interstitial-to-plasma fluid shift",
      "a plasma-to-interstitial fluid shift",
      "increased kidney perfusion",
      "DIC development"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "a plasma-to-interstitial fluid shift"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate what is feature of irreversible (decompensatory) stage of shock?",
    "options": [
      "an interstitial-to-plasma fluid shift",
      "a plasma-to-interstitial fluid shift",
      "increased kidney perfusion",
      "DIC development",
      "increased skin perfusion"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "DIC development"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of following is sign of initial (compensatory) stage of shock?",
    "options": [
      "sludging of RBCs",
      "respiratory distress syndrome",
      "blood circulation centralization",
      "lung edema",
      "increased skin perfusion"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "blood circulation centralization"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of following is sign of initial (compensatory) stage of shock?",
    "options": [
      "closing of arteriovenous anastomoses",
      "opening of arteriovenous anastomoses",
      "azotemia development",
      "acidosis development",
      "alkalosis development"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "opening of arteriovenous anastomoses"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which one of following organs diminished perfusion is sign of initial (compensatory) stage of shock?",
    "options": [
      "brain",
      "kidney",
      "heart",
      "liver",
      "lungs"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "kidney"
  },
  {
    "question": "What one of following changes in blood is being observed in initial (compensatory) stage of shock?",
    "options": [
      "increased level of catecholamine ",
      "decreased level of catecholamine ",
      "hypercapnia",
      "increased fibrinolytic activity ",
      "decreased fibrinolytic activity "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased level of catecholamine "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is causative factor of hypovolemic shock?",
    "options": [
      "severe, multiple bone fractures",
      "sepsis",
      "excessive diarrhea",
      "myocardial infarction",
      "coarctation of aorta"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "excessive diarrhea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Anaphylactic shock refers to which one of following types?",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "dehydration shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "distributive shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Burn shock refers to which one of following types?",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "septic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypovolemic shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Heart tamponade can cause which one of following types of shock?",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "dehydration shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "obstructive shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Severe trauma with fractures of long bones can cause which one of following types of shock?",
    "options": [
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "anaphylactic shock",
      "cardiogenic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "distributive shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Acute heart failure can cause which one of following types of shock?",
    "options": [
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "anaphylactic shock",
      "cardiogenic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cardiogenic shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "If large amount of microbial endotoxins appearances in blood and causes shock, what type of shock it can be according pathogenesis?",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "anaphylactic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "distributive shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "If large amount of microbial exotoxins appearances in blood and causes shock, what type of shock it can be more possible according pathogenesis?",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "anaphylactic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "obstructive shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the development of shock includes following sequence of events such as absolute deficiency of intravascular  volume - heart ventricles low preload –low cardiac output, what type of shock is it? ",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "septic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypovolemic shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the development of shock includes following sequence of events such as low TPR - relative deficiency of intravascular  volume - low cardiac output, what type of shock is it? ",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "dehydration shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "distributive shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the development of shock includes following sequence of events such as heart pump failure - low cardiac output - decreased perfusion of tissues, what type of shock is it?",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "dehydration shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cardiogenic shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the development of shock includes following sequence of events such as high afterload of heart - low cardiac output - decreased perfusion of tissues, what type of shock is it?",
    "options": [
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock",
      "anaphylactic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "obstructive shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pulmonary embolism can cause which one of following types of shock?",
    "options": [
      "dehydration shock",
      "cardiogenic shock",
      "distributive shock",
      "obstructive shock",
      "hypovolemic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "obstructive shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is stimulation of carotid sinuses and aortic arch  baroreceptors, what stage of of shock development is this?",
    "options": [
      "initial  stage",
      "intermediate stage",
      "progressive stage ",
      "irreversible  stage",
      "decompensatory stage"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "initial  stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is appearance of DIC syndrome and of “ shock “ organs, what stage of of shock development is this?",
    "options": [
      "compensatory stage",
      "initial  stage",
      "intermediate stage",
      "progressive stage ",
      "irreversible  stage"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "irreversible  stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is first link in pathogenesis of blood circulation centralization during compensatory stage of shock?",
    "options": [
      "inhibition of alfa-adrenoceptors",
      "activation of alfa-adrenoceptors",
      "stimulation of carotid sinuses and aortic arch  baroreceptors",
      "inhibition of carotid sinuses and aortic arch  baroreceptors",
      "increased preload of heart ventricles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "stimulation of carotid sinuses and aortic arch  baroreceptors"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the unfourable outcome of infarction?",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Incapsulation",
      "Cyst formation",
      "Suppuration",
      "Hemosiderosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Suppuration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of shock associated with generalized reactions of hypersensitivity?",
    "options": [
      "Cardiogenic",
      "Traumatic",
      "Hypovolemic",
      "Neurogenic",
      "Anaphylactic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Anaphylactic"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called general factor of thrombosis?",
    "options": [
      "Injury of vessel wall due to trauma ",
      "Increase of blood viscosity",
      "Atherosclerotic ulcers",
      "Slowing of blood flow",
      "Turbulent blood flow"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Increase of blood viscosity"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is called local factor of thrombosis?",
    "options": [
      "Increase in number of erythrocytes",
      "Atherosclerotic ulcers",
      "Increase in number of leukocytes",
      "Increased level of proteins",
      "Decrease in number of leukocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Atherosclerotic ulcers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the characteristic sign of a thrombus? ",
    "options": [
      "Rough surface",
      "Soft",
      "Gomogenous cut surface",
      "Smooth surface",
      "Not attached to vessel wall"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rough surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the sign of a postmortem clot? ",
    "options": [
      "Ruph surface",
      "Smooth surface",
      "Homogenous cut surface",
      "Hard, dry",
      "Attached to vessel wall"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Smooth surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term is used for the formation of channels covered by endothelial cells?",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Calcification",
      "Recanalization",
      "Propagation",
      "Embolization"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Recanalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of embolism may lead to generalization of the infection?",
    "options": [
      "Thromboembolism",
      "Microbial embolism",
      "Amniotic fluid embolism",
      "Gas embolism",
      "Foreign body embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Microbial embolism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of embolism may lead to tumor spread? ",
    "options": [
      "Thromboembolism",
      "Microbial embolism",
      "Cell embolism",
      "Air embolism",
      "Foreign body embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cell embolism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of embolism can occur in bone fracture?",
    "options": [
      "Thromboembolism",
      "Microbial embolism",
      "Fat embolism",
      "Gas embolism",
      "Amniotic fluid embolism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fat embolism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the typical outcome of hemorrhagic infarction? ",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Incapsulation",
      "Cyst formation",
      "Suppuration",
      "Hemosiderosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hemosiderosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the typical outcome of cerebral infarction?",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Incapsulation",
      "Cyst formation",
      "Suppuration",
      "Hemosiderosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cyst formation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of shock is associated with the action of a strong painful stimulus?",
    "options": [
      "Cardiogenic",
      "Traumatic",
      "Hypovolemic",
      "Neurogenic",
      "Anaphylactic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Traumatic"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of shock associated with severe burns?",
    "options": [
      "Cardiogenic",
      "Traumatic",
      "Endotoxic",
      "Hypovolemic",
      "Anaphylactic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypovolemic"
  },
  {
    "question": "What morphological changes develop in the kidneys in shock?",
    "options": [
      "Infiltration of the interstitium with leukocytes",
      "Deposits of hyaline masses in the epithelium of the tubules",
      "Deposition of hyaline masses in the glomeruli",
      "Amyloid deposition in the glomeruli",
      "Degeneration and necrosis of the tubular epithelium "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Degeneration and necrosis of the tubular epithelium "
  },
  {
    "question": "What term is used for the stopping of blood flow in the microvessels?",
    "options": [
      "Infarction",
      "Hyperemia",
      "Hypoxia",
      "Stasis",
      "Atrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stasis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which outcome of thrombus is characteristic by dislodge and transport to other sites?",
    "options": [
      "Propagation ",
      "Calcification",
      "Embolization",
      "Suppuration",
      "Dissolution"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Embolization"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which outcome of thrombus is characteristic by purulent inflammation due to action of bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "Propagation ",
      "Calcification",
      "Embolization",
      "Suppuration",
      "Dissolution"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Suppuration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which outcome of thrombosis is characteristic by ingrowth of connective tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Propagation ",
      "Calcification",
      "Embolization",
      "Suppuration",
      "Organization"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Organization"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which outcome of thrombus is characteristic by removed by fibrinolytic activity?",
    "options": [
      "Propagation ",
      "Calcification",
      "Embolization",
      "Suppuration",
      "Dissolution "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dissolution "
  },
  {
    "question": "Autopsy of a 62-year-old patient suffering from melanoma of skin. Gross morphology of liver:  enlarged in size, dark brown round- shaped nodes are visible on a light yellow background. Which type of embolism is described in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Gas",
      "Cell",
      "Fat",
      "Air",
      "Microbial"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "Autopsy of a 22-year-old man, patient decease from severe hemorrhage. Revealed pale of skin, inner organs and injury of inner organs typical for shock. Which type of shock is described in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Traumatic",
      "Cardiogenic",
      "Hypovolemic",
      "Anaphylactic",
      "Septic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypovolemic"
  },
  {
    "question": "The diver died as a result of decompression due to the rapid rise to the surface of the sea. An autopsy revealed frothy blood, installed small bubbles in the venous system, multiple hemorrhages in the internal organs, foci of softening in the brain. What type of embolism occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Air",
      "Gas",
      "Fatty",
      "Microbial",
      "Tissue "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gas"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 63-year-old patient suffering from ischemic heart disease developed severe chest pains radiating to the left arm. On Autopsy: in the anterior wall of the left ventricle revealed focus yellowish in color, irregular in shape, hard in consistence. Which pathological process occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Anemia",
      "Embolism",
      "Infarction",
      "Sclerosis",
      "Dystrophy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Infarction"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 20-year-old patient has profuse hemorrhage (2 L) as a result of trauma of the femoral artery. On admission to the hospital, revealed pale of the skin, a severe decrease of blood pressure (60/30 mm Hg). Which type of shock occurs in this case? ",
    "options": [
      "Hypovolemic",
      "Cardiogenic",
      "Toxic",
      "Neurogenic",
      "Anaphylactic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypovolemic"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient 30 years old after the injection developed edema, redness and itching at the injection site, a severe decrease of blood pressure (40/20 mm Hg). Pathanatomical examination revealed: fluid blood in the vessels, accumulation of blood in microcirculatory vessels, disseminated intravascular coagulation, “shock kidney”, “shock lung”. Which type of shock occurs in this case? ",
    "options": [
      "Hypovolemic",
      "Cardiogenic",
      "Septic",
      "Traumatic ",
      "Anaphylactic "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Anaphylactic "
  },
  {
    "question": "A 73-year-old patient died of heart failure, suffered a myocardial infarction a 1 year ago. At autopsy: the postinfarction area is hard, thinned, whitish-grey with formation of aneurism. Thrombotic masses of reddish-white color, hard and smooth were found in the aneurism. What type of thrombus occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Occlusive",
      "Mural ",
      "Dilative ",
      "Ball ",
      "Vegetations "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dilative "
  },
  {
    "question": "A 37-year-old patient suffered of lung abscess. Pathanatomical examination revealed: fluid blood in the vessels, accumulation of blood in microcirculatory vessels, disseminated intravascular coagulation, “shock kidney”, “shock lung” and metastatic abscesses in the inner organs. Which type of shock occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Hypovolemic ",
      "Cardiogenic",
      "Septic",
      "Traumatic ",
      "Anaphylactic "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Septic"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 71-year-old patient suffered from ischemic heart disease and was died from chronic heart failure. Microscopic examination of the heart revealed: in the branch of the left coronary artery thrombotic masses with proliferation of connective tissue in which channels covered with endothelial cells. Which outcome of thrombus occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Dissolution",
      "Organization",
      "Calcification ",
      "Recanalization",
      "Suppuration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Recanalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 68-year-old patient who suffered from atherosclerosis of the aorta. At autopsy in the kidneys area of gray-yellow color, wedge-shaped, hard consistency was found. Which pathological process occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Infarction",
      "Amyloidosis",
      "Sclerosis",
      "Gangrene",
      "Shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Infarction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following components is a chemoattractant for neutrophils during inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "C 1",
      "C2",
      "C 3b",
      "C 5a",
      "C5b6789"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "C 5a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Acute-phase proteins induced inflammatory response include which one of following? ",
    "options": [
      "prostaglandins ",
      "Hageman factor",
      "nitric oxide",
      "C-reactive protein",
      "LTB4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "C-reactive protein"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which of these is cell-derived mediator, that causes vasodilation in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "nitric oxide",
      "C3a, C5a",
      "bradykinin",
      "prostaglandin",
      "LXA2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "prostaglandin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Preformed mediator in cell secretory granules which release in inflammatory area is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "histamine",
      "bradykinin",
      "activated oxygen species",
      NaN,
      "thromboxane A2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "histamine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these is chemotactic factor in inflammatory area?",
    "options": [
      "TNF",
      "MAC",
      "C3b",
      "P selectin",
      "LTB4  "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "LTB4  "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these inflammatory mediators relate to cytokines group?",
    "options": [
      "bradykinin",
      "complement",
      "leukotriens",
      "thromboxane A2",
      "interleukins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "interleukins"
  },
  {
    "question": "Group of newly synthesized inflammatory mediators includes which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "histamine",
      "nitric oxide",
      "serotonin",
      "acetylcholine ",
      "norepinephrine"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "nitric oxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these relate to neutrophils- derived mediators in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "cation proteins",
      "bradykinin",
      "compliment",
      "interleukins",
      "histamine"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cation proteins"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these is systemic sign of inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "swelling",
      "calor",
      "dolor",
      "fever",
      "pain"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cohnheim experiment is study about which one of following processes in inflammatory area?",
    "options": [
      "emigration of leukocytes ",
      "vascular changes ",
      "proliferation",
      "alteration",
      "exudation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "vascular changes "
  },
  {
    "question": "Mechanism of \"tumor\" in inflammation is connected with which one of listed events?",
    "options": [
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "ischemia",
      "increased capillary permeability",
      "vasoconstriction"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased capillary permeability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mechanism of \"calor\" in inflammation is connected with which one of listed events?",
    "options": [
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "ischemia",
      "increased capillary permeability",
      "vasoconstriction"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "arterial hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spasm of precapillary sphincters leading to slow blood flow in capillaries in inflammatory area is characteristic feature which of following events?",
    "options": [
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "ischemia",
      "increased capillary permeability",
      "stasis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ischemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aggregation of erythrocytes causing rheological changes in capillaries in inflammatory area is characteristic feature which of following events?",
    "options": [
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "ischemia",
      "increased capillary permeability",
      "stasis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "stasis"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is lowering of hydrostatic pressure in capillaries in inflammatory area it can be accompanied with which one of following changes? ",
    "options": [
      "increased lymph outflow",
      "blood viscosity is more",
      "decreased number of \"plasma\" capillaries",
      "increased linear velocity of blood flow",
      "spasm of precapillary sphincters"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "spasm of precapillary sphincters"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transition of arterial hyperemia to venous in inflammatory area is primarily result of increase in which of these processes?",
    "options": [
      "blood flow",
      "vascular permeability",
      "lymph outflow",
      "macrophages function",
      "capillary hydrostatic pressure"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "vascular permeability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose what is tissular factor needing in order to increase the colloid-osmotic pressure in the interstitial fluid in the focus of inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "proteolysis of tissue proteins with formation of small particles",
      "leakage of plasma proteins from the vessels",
      "increased capillary permeability",
      "increased hydrostatic pressure in capillaries",
      "endothelial cell junctions are disrupted"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "proteolysis of tissue proteins with formation of small particles"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option indicates that the difficulty of venous outflow of blood in inflammatory area facilitates process of exudation?",
    "options": [
      "hyperosmia in inflammatory center",
      "hyposmia in inflammatory center",
      "precapillary hydrostatic pressure is more",
      "post capillary hydrostatic pressure is more",
      "pressure gradient in capillaries is more"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "post capillary hydrostatic pressure is more"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option indicates that the physical and chemical changes in inflammatory area facilitates process of exudation?",
    "options": [
      "hyperosmia in inflammatory center",
      "hyposmia in inflammatory center",
      "precapillary hydrostatic pressure is more",
      "post capillary hydrostatic pressure is more",
      "pressure gradient in capillaries is more"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hyperosmia in inflammatory center"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which of these is more anticipated final result of fibrinous exudation?",
    "options": [
      "scarring",
      "suppuration",
      "resultant fibrosis",
      "resolution",
      "resultant necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "resultant fibrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cohnheim experiment is study about which one of following processes in inflammatory area?",
    "options": [
      "emigration of leukocytes ",
      "vascular changes ",
      "proliferation",
      "alteration",
      "exudation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "vascular changes "
  },
  {
    "question": "What  is common  name of  etiologic factors of  inflammation ?",
    "options": [
      "flogogens",
      "allergens",
      "pyrogens",
      "haptens",
      "mediators"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "flogogens"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is local sign of inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "dolor",
      "fever",
      "leukocytosis ",
      "increased ESR",
      "fatigue"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "dolor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vasodilation in inflammatory area is result of activity of which of listed factors?",
    "options": [
      "C3b",
      "C3a, C5a",
      "bradykinin",
      "TNF",
      "cation proteins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "bradykinin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is final product of complement system that cause direct damage of microbes during inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "C1",
      "C3b",
      "C5b6789",
      "C3a, C5a",
      "C3bBb"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "C5b6789"
  },
  {
    "question": "Scientist who first described sequence of vascular changes in infflammatory area was:",
    "options": [
      "Celsus",
      "Galenus",
      "Cohnheim",
      "Metchnicoff",
      "Virchov"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cohnheim"
  },
  {
    "question": " Mixed hyperemia can appearance in what period during inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "between spasm-hyperemia",
      "between hyperemia-congestion",
      "between -congestion-stasis",
      "before spasm",
      "after spasm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "between hyperemia-congestion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is first stage of vascular reactions in inflammation area?",
    "options": [
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "transient spasm",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "stasis",
      "mixed hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "transient spasm"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is second stage of vascular reactions in inflammation area?",
    "options": [
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "transient spasm",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "stasis",
      "mixed hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "arterial hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is third stage of vascular reactions in inflammation area?",
    "options": [
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "transient spasm",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "stasis",
      "mixed hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "venous hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What of these is characteristic feature of inflammatory mediators such as cytokines?",
    "options": [
      "perform enzyme role",
      "produced by the liver",
      "chemotactic factor",
      "perform   regulatory role on cells",
      "each leukocyte produces one type of cytokines"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "perform   regulatory role on cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Correct sequence of vascular reactions in inflammatory area is which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "spasm-congestion-hyperemia-stasis",
      "spasm-hyperemia-congestion-stasis",
      "congestion-spasm-hyperemia-stasis",
      "hyperemia-stasis- spasm-congestion",
      "stasis-hyperemia-congestion-spasm"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "spasm-hyperemia-congestion-stasis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of listed factors causes secondary alteration in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "local acidosis",
      "flogogens",
      "allergens",
      "haptens",
      "scratch"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "local acidosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which one of listed factors causes secondary alteration in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "flogogens",
      "allergens",
      "lysosomal enzymes",
      "viral enzymes",
      "haptens"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "lysosomal enzymes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose intravascular changes leading to venous hyperemia development in nflammatory area:",
    "options": [
      "destruction of venules walls desmosomes",
      "increased activity of hyaluronidase",
      "decreased activity of hyaluronidase",
      "compression of venules by escaped fluid",
      "margination of WBCs"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "margination of WBCs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Chooseextravascular changes leading to venous hyperemia development in nflammatory area:",
    "options": [
      "increase of blood viscosity",
      "endothelial cells swelling",
      "margination of WBCs",
      "destruction of venules walls desmosomes",
      "decreased activity of hyaluronidase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "destruction of venules walls desmosomes"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is blood flow rotation forward and backward in capillaries in inflammatory area, what type of vascular response is it?",
    "options": [
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "transient spasm",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "stasis",
      "mixed hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "venous hyperemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is mechanism of increased capillary permeability in inflammatory area just after injury?",
    "options": [
      "endothelial cell junctions  disruption",
      "endothelial cell contraction",
      "activation of leukocytes",
      "endothelial cell retraction",
      "endothelial cell damage by leukocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "endothelial cell contraction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is mechanism of increased capillary permeability in inflammatory area in one or two hour after injury?",
    "options": [
      "endothelial cell junctions  disruption",
      "endothelial cell contraction",
      "activation of leukocytes",
      "endothelial cell retraction",
      "endothelial cell damage by leukocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "endothelial cell retraction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following changes in inflammatory area is important to aggregation of erythrocytes and their rheological properties in final stage of vascular response?",
    "options": [
      "increased hydrostatic pressure",
      "hypooncia",
      "hypoosmia",
      "acidic environment ",
      "decreased lymph outflow"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "acidic environment "
  },
  {
    "question": "Mediators preformed in cell secretory granules in inflammation are which of these?",
    "options": [
      "prostaglandins",
      "interferons",
      "cation proteins",
      "plasmins",
      "interleukins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cation proteins"
  },
  {
    "question": "What effect on liver  IL-1 causes that is important for inflammatory process ?",
    "options": [
      "antibodies breakdown",
      "APP synthesis",
      "IL-2 synthesis",
      "glycogen synthesis",
      "glycogen breakdown"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "APP synthesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is final stage of vascular reactions in inflammation area?",
    "options": [
      "ischemic stasis",
      "congestive stasis",
      "stasis due to rheological changes ",
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "stasis due to rheological changes "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following mediators is result of activation of fibrinolitic system in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "prostaglandins",
      "bradykinin",
      "histamine ",
      "Hageman factor",
      "plasmin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "plasmin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following mediators is result of activation of kinin system in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "prostaglandins",
      "bradykinin",
      "histamine ",
      "Hageman factor",
      "plasmin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "bradykinin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following mediators is result of activation of clotting system in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "interferon",
      "bradykinin",
      "histamine ",
      "Hageman factor",
      "plasmin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hageman factor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following mediators is result of activation of complement system in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "Hageman factor",
      "plasmin",
      "properdin",
      "prostaglandins",
      "bradykinin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "properdin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Scientist who first described local signs of inflammation was:",
    "options": [
      "Celsus",
      "Selye",
      "Cohnheim",
      "Metchnicoff",
      "Virchov"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Celsus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Purulent inflammation is characterized by recruitment of large numbers of which blood cells?",
    "options": [
      "monocytes",
      "neutrophiles",
      "eosinophiles",
      "lymphocytes",
      "erythrocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "neutrophiles"
  },
  {
    "question": "Abscess formation is mainly complication of which one of following types of inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "catarrhal",
      "serous ",
      "fibrinous ",
      "purulent",
      "crupous"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "purulent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Trigger mechanism of inflammatory reactions in many cases  is which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "IL-1 activates APP synthesis",
      "APP activates TNF releasing ",
      "IL-1 activates T-cells",
      "LPS activates IL-1 releasing",
      " IL-1 activates IL-2 synthesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "LPS activates IL-1 releasing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alternative   pathway of complement system activation in inflammation is observed after action of which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "plasmin",
      "C3 component",
      "immune complexes",
      "C5b6789 component",
      "Hageman factor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "plasmin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Classical pathway of complement system activation in inflammation is observed after action of which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "C3a convertase",
      "plasmin",
      "immune complexes",
      "C-reactive protein",
      "Hageman factor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "immune complexes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate what mediator causes endothelial cell retraction leading to stable increase of capillary permeability in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "histamine",
      "bradykinin",
      "interferon",
      "plasmin",
      "interleukin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "interleukin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which vascular response mechanism realized by axon-reflex of the terminal branches of sensory axons in inflammatory area?",
    "options": [
      "venous hyperemia",
      "arterial hyperemia",
      "vasoconstriction",
      "increased capillary permeability",
      "stasis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "vasoconstriction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of options indicate stability of arterial hyperemia in inflammatory area?",
    "options": [
      "norepinephrine releasing ",
      "acetylcholine releasing",
      "histamine releasing",
      "activation of MAO",
      "accumulation of metabolites"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "accumulation of metabolites"
  },
  {
    "question": "Neurotonic mechanism of arterial hyperemia in inflammatory area is result of which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "acetylcholine releasing ",
      "bradykinin action",
      "accumulation of metabolites",
      "decreased pH ",
      "prostaglandins production"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "acetylcholine releasing "
  },
  {
    "question": "Neuroparalytic mechanism of arterial hyperemia in inflammation area is result of which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "acetylcholine releasing ",
      "activation of MAO",
      "noradrenaline releasing ",
      "accumulation of metabolites",
      "histamine releasing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "accumulation of metabolites"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following factors is forming due to cyclooxygenase enzymatic transformations of arachidonic acid and leads to vasodilation in inflammatory area?",
    "options": [
      "leukotriene B4  ",
      "nitric oxide",
      "prostaglandins",
      "bradykinin",
      "histamine "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "prostaglandins"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following factors is forming due to lipoxygenase enzymatic transformations of arachidonic acid and leads to neutrophils attraction  to inflammatory area?",
    "options": [
      "leukotriene B4  ",
      "prostaglandins",
      "complement C3b",
      "complement C3a",
      "bradykinin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "leukotriene B4  "
  },
  {
    "question": "Decrease of volumetric blood flow velocity with distention of postcapillaries in inflammatory area are characteristic features of which stage of vascular response?",
    "options": [
      "first stage",
      "second stage",
      "third stage",
      "fourth stage",
      "fifth stage"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "third stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "When part of the capillaries is \"closed\" for blood flow and part is filled with plasma in inflammatory area, it indicates to which stage of vascular response?",
    "options": [
      "first stage",
      "second stage",
      "third stage",
      "fourth stage",
      "fifth stage"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "first stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bradykinin action and nitric oxide production in inflammatory area indicates to which stage of vascular response?",
    "options": [
      "first stage",
      "second stage",
      "third stage",
      "fourth stage",
      "fifth stage"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "second stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option indicates that the difficulty of venous outflow of blood in inflammatory area facilitates process of exudation?",
    "options": [
      "hyperosmia in inflammatory center",
      "hyposmia in inflammatory center",
      "precapillary hydrostatic pressure is more",
      "post capillary hydrostatic pressure is more",
      "pressure gradient in capillaries is more"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "post capillary hydrostatic pressure is more"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option indicates that the physical and chemical changes in inflammatory area facilitates process of exudation?",
    "options": [
      "hyperosmia in inflammatory center",
      "hyposmia in inflammatory center",
      "precapillary hydrostatic pressure is more",
      "post capillary hydrostatic pressure is more",
      "pressure gradient in capillaries is more"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hyperosmia in inflammatory center"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is increase in the linear velocity of blood flow in inflammatory area it can be accompanied with which one of following changes?",
    "options": [
      "increased number of \"plasma\" capillaries",
      "blood viscosity is more",
      "distention of postcapillaries",
      "decreased lymph outflow",
      "increased lymph outflow"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "increased lymph outflow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which of these is more anticipated final result of fibrinous exudation?",
    "options": [
      "scarring",
      "suppuration",
      "resultant fibrosis",
      "resolution",
      "resultant necrosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "resultant fibrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "If express test for exudate - transudate differentiation shows turbid trail following a drop in test-tube with slightly acidic water, which of following changes is correct in this case?",
    "options": [
      "specific gravity is 1012",
      "protein content is about 1.0 g/dl",
      "pH is 7.4",
      "pH is 7.0",
      "small count of cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "pH is 7.0"
  },
  {
    "question": "If express test for exudate - transudate differentiation shows transparent trail following a drop in test-tube with slightly acidic water, which of following changes is correct in this case?",
    "options": [
      "specific gravity is 1020",
      "protein content is about 6.0 g/dl",
      "pH is 7.4",
      "pH is 7.0",
      "small amount of fibrin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "pH is 7.4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Function restriction due to adhesive strictures in organs is mainly complication of which one of following types of inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "catarrhal",
      "hemorrhagic ",
      "fibrinous ",
      "purulent ",
      "serous "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "fibrinous "
  },
  {
    "question": "What term is used for inflammation of the small intestine?",
    "options": [
      "Gastritis",
      "Enteritis",
      "Colitis",
      "Proctitis",
      "Duodenitis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Enteritis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used for inflammation of the lung tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Pneumonia",
      "Angina",
      "Furuncle",
      "Carbuncle",
      "Empyema"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pneumonia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used for inflammation of the throat?",
    "options": [
      "Pneumonia",
      "Angina",
      "Furuncle",
      "Carbuncle",
      "Empyema"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Angina"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used for inflammation of the of brain?",
    "options": [
      "Gastritis",
      "Hepatitis",
      "Enteritis",
      "Epididimitis",
      "Encephalitis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Encephalitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which the local sign of inflammation associated with the pressure of exudate on the nerve endings?",
    "options": [
      "Rubor",
      "Calor",
      "Dolor",
      "Tumor",
      "Functio laesa"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dolor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which the local sign of inflammation associated with the accumulation of exudate?",
    "options": [
      "Rubor",
      "Calor",
      "Dolor",
      "Tumor",
      "Functio laesa"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tumor"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the inflammation, characterized by the outpouring of low-protein fluid?",
    "options": [
      "Serous inflammation",
      "Fibrinous inflammation",
      "Purulent inflammation",
      "Hemorrhagic inflammation",
      "Catarrhal inflammation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Serous inflammation"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what type of inflammation does the exudate consist of much amounts of leukocytes and lymphocytes, macrophages, necrotic cells, microbes?",
    "options": [
      "Serous inflammation",
      "Fibrinous inflammation",
      "Purulent inflammation",
      "Hemorrhagic inflammation",
      "Catarrhal inflammation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Purulent inflammation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of type of acute inflammation which associated with formation of hair-like deposits? ",
    "options": [
      "Serous inflammation",
      "Fibrinous inflammation",
      "Purulent inflammation",
      "Hemorrhagic inflammation",
      "Catarrhal inflammation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrinous inflammation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of type of acute inflammation associated with the formation of a pseudomembrane on the surface of the mucous membrane?",
    "options": [
      "Serous inflammation",
      "Fibrinous inflammation",
      "Purulent inflammation",
      "Hemorrhagic inflammation",
      "Catarrhal inflammation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrinous inflammation"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is expression of adhesion molecules family like selectins on leukocytes during leukocytes emigration to inflammatory area, which one of listed ligands for binding is correct?",
    "options": [
      "ICAM-1",
      "PSGL-1",
      "GlyCAM",
      "VCAM-1",
      "PECAM-1"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "PSGL-1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What stage of leukocytes emigration to inflammatory area is result of expression of adhesion molecules family like selectins on leukocytes and endothelial cells?",
    "options": [
      "adhesion",
      "rolling ",
      "margination ",
      "transmigration",
      "chemotaxis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "rolling "
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is PECAM-PECAM (CD31-CD31)interactions between leukocytes and endothelial cells during leukocytes emigration to inflammatory area, what stage of leukocytes emigration is it?",
    "options": [
      "adhesion",
      "rolling ",
      "margination ",
      "transmigration",
      "chemotaxis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "transmigration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Expression of adhesion molecules ligands like ICAM-1 on endothelial cells during leukocytes emigration to inflammatory area indicates to what stage of leukocytes emigration?",
    "options": [
      "adhesion",
      "rolling ",
      "margination ",
      "transmigration",
      "chemotaxis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "adhesion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these cell adhesion molecules family (CAM) binds with leukocytes integrins during leukocytes emigration to inflammatory area?",
    "options": [
      "VLA-4",
      "VCAM-1",
      "sLe-X",
      "PSGL-1",
      "LFA-1"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "VCAM-1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of these cell adhesion molecules family (CAM), that is necessary for leukocytes emigration to inflammatory area, is related to immunoglobulin superfamily CAM?",
    "options": [
      "VLA-4",
      "PSGL-1",
      "LFA-1",
      "PECAM-1",
      "E-selectin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "PECAM-1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of these cell adhesion molecules family (CAM), that is necessary for leukocytes emigration to inflammatory area, is related to integrins?",
    "options": [
      "VLA-4",
      "PSGL-1",
      "PECAM-1",
      "E-selectin",
      "ICAM-1"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "VLA-4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transient sticking of leukocytes to endothelial surface during leukocytes emigration to inflammatory area is dependent on which one of listed factors?",
    "options": [
      "VLA-4",
      "VCAM-1",
      "LFA-1",
      "PECAM-1",
      "E-selectin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "E-selectin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which one of these is participant of first step of leukocyte-endothelial cells interaction during leukocytes emigration to inflammatory area?",
    "options": [
      "VLA-4",
      "PSGL-1",
      "LFA-1",
      "PECAM-1",
      "ICAM-1"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "PSGL-1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these is exogenous factor that has properties of chemoattractants for neutrophils in inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "leukotriene B4",
      "bradykinin",
      "LPS",
      "microbial adhesion molecules",
      "C5a"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "LPS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cells are found in chronic inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "Neutrophils",
      "Erythrocytes",
      "Astrocytes",
      "Giant cells",
      "Osteocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Giant cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cells are found in chronic inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "Neutrophils",
      "Epitelioid cells",
      "Epithelial cells",
      "Astrocytes",
      "Osteocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Epitelioid cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the function of macrophages?",
    "options": [
      "Phagocytosis",
      "Producing of antibodies",
      "Producing of mediators",
      "Syntesis of collagen",
      "Regeneration of epithelial cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Phagocytosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the function of fibroblasts?",
    "options": [
      "Phagocytosis",
      "Scar formation",
      "Producing of antibodies",
      "Tissue destruction",
      "Forming of giant cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Scar formation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cells are associated with producing of mediators?",
    "options": [
      "Lymphocytes",
      " Plasma cells",
      "Eosinophils",
      "Must cells",
      " Fibroblasts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lymphocytes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cells are characteristically found in inflammatory focus around animal parasites?",
    "options": [
      "Lymphocytes",
      "Plasma cells",
      "Eosinophils",
      "Must cells",
      "Fibroblasts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Eosinophils"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cells are collagen producing?",
    "options": [
      "Lymphocytes",
      "Plasma cells",
      "Eosinophils",
      "Must cells",
      "Fibroblasts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibroblasts"
  },
  {
    "question": "What disease is characterized by the presence of caseous necrosis, epithelial cells, lymphocytes, Langhans-type giant cells in the granuloma?",
    "options": [
      "Tuberculosis",
      "Rheumatic fever",
      "Rheumatoid arthritis",
      "Sarcoidosis",
      "Regional ileitis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tuberculosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What disease is characterized by the presence of glue-like necrosis, plasma cells, epithelial cells, lymphocytes in the granuloma?",
    "options": [
      "Rheumatic fever",
      "Rheumatoid arthritis",
      "Syphilis",
      "Sarcoidosis",
      "Regional ileitis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Syphilis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the of type of chronic inflammation?",
    "options": [
      "Serous inflammation",
      "Fibrinous inflammation",
      "Granulomatous inflammation",
      "Hemorrhagic inflammation",
      "Purulent inflammation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Granulomatous inflammation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the most characteristic of granuloma:",
    "options": [
      "Epithelioid cell",
      "Giant cell",
      " Fibroblasts",
      "Endothelial cell",
      "Catarrhal"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Epithelioid cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these is not a granulomatous disease",
    "options": [
      "Leprosy",
      "Tuberculosis",
      "Sarcoidosis",
      "Amebiasis",
      "Neutrophil infiltration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Amebiasis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Chronic granulomatous disease is:",
    "options": [
      "Associated with formation of multiple granulomas",
      "A benign neoplastic process",
      "A parasitic disease",
      "Acquired leukocyte function defect",
      "Margination"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Associated with formation of multiple granulomas"
  },
  {
    "question": "The epithelioid cell and multinucleated giant cells of Granulomatous inflammation are derived from:",
    "options": [
      "Basophils",
      "Eosinophils",
      "CD4-T lymphocytes",
      "Monocytes-Macrophages",
      "Proteases"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Monocytes-Macrophages"
  },
  {
    "question": "Immediate type of hypersensitivity morphologically occurs like:",
    "options": [
      "Acute immune inflammation. ",
      "Purulent inflammation",
      "Hemorragic inflammation",
      "Chronic immune inflammation",
      "Catarrhal inflammation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Acute immune inflammation. "
  },
  {
    "question": "A 14-year-old girl Radha has high grade fever. She goes to a physician Dr. Jeeva Roy who orders for some blood investigations. A complete blood count with differential implies the presence of a viral infection. Which of the following best describes the cells that indicate a viral etiology to her illness?",
    "options": [
      "They are basophilic with spherical dark-stained nuclei",
      "They are precursors of osteoclasts and liver Kupffer cells",
      "They have azurophilic granules and multilobed nuclei",
      "They contain a peripheral hyalomere and central granulomere",
      "Platelet-activating factor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "They are basophilic with spherical dark-stained nuclei"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 36-year-old man, Avnish presents with a cough, fever, night sweats, and weight loss. A chest Xray reveals irregular densities in the upper lobe of his right lung. Histologic sections from this area reveal groups of epithelioid cells with rare acid-fast bacilli and a few scattered giant cells. At the centre of these groups of epithelioid cells are granular areas of necrosis. What is the source of these epithelioid cells?",
    "options": [
      "Bronchial cells",
      "Pneumocytes",
      " Lymphocytes",
      " Monocytes",
      "Fibrin deposition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Monocytes"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 45-year-old man, Suveen presents with pain in the mid portion of his chestThe pain is associated with eating and swallowing foodEndoscopic examination reveals an ulcerated area in the lower portion of his esophagusHistologic sections of tissue taken from this area reveal an ulceration of the esophageal mucosa that is filled with blood, fibrin, proliferating blood vessels, and proliferating fibroblastsMitosis is easily found, and most of the cells have prominent nucleoliWhich of the following statements best describes this ulcerated area?",
    "options": [
      "Caseating granulomatous inflammation",
      "Dysplastic epithelium",
      " Granulation tissue",
      "Squamous cell carcinoma",
      "Emigration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Granulation tissue"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 22-year-old patient was admitted to the clinic, who had angina 1 month ago, with pain in the region of the heart, high fever, shortness of breath. On the 2-nd day of hospitalization, death occurred from heart failure. Grossly:  heart is flabby, dark red color. Microscopically: perivascular foci of fibrinoid necrosis, surrounded by inflammatory cells - lymphocytes, macrophages, epithelioid cells. What is the type of inflammation in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Granulomatous",
      "Fibrinous ",
      "Interstitial ",
      "Purulent",
      "Hemorrhagic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Granulomatous"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 65-year-old patient has a part of the stomach removed for cancer. The patient died 3 months later. Microscopic examination of the anastomotic area around the suture material shows focal accumulations of leukocytes, macrophages, giant multinucleated cells, a small number of fibroblasts. What type of inflammation developed in the anastomotic area?",
    "options": [
      "Fibrinous",
      "Purulent",
      "Productive",
      "Catarrhal",
      "Serous"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Productive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Opening of the abdominal cavity revealed enlarged, tense appendix. The serous membrane of the appendix is faded, grayish-green, with dilated vessels. The wall of the appendix is ​​sharply thinned, flabby, in the cavity of the appendix: large amount greenish mass. What type inflammation in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Abcess",
      "Empyema",
      "Phlegmon",
      "Furunkle",
      "Сarbuncle"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Empyema"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 21-year-old patient suffering from pain in the forearm, swelling, redness. The disease is associated with trauma. When opening the surgical area of ​​the lesion, 50 ml of a thick turbid greenish liquid was released. What type inflammation in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Hemorrhagic",
      "Fibrinous",
      "Catarrhal",
      "Purulent",
      "Serous"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Purulent"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 28-year-old patient has a skin area the left wing of the nose there is a cone-shaped elevation with a diameter 0.6 cm and a height of 0.5 cm, the skin is purplish red with yellowish area in the apex, painful, appeared 3 days back. What type of purulent inflammation is there in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Abcess",
      "Empyema",
      "Phlegmon",
      "Furunkle",
      "Сarbuncle"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Furunkle"
  },
  {
    "question": "On examination, a 28-year-old patient has a reddish fluid bubble on his face. Regional lymphadenitis - swollen lymph nodes. A bacterioscopy of the contents of the vesicle was carried out, an anthrax bacillus was found. What type inflammation in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Hemorrhagic",
      "Fibrinous",
      "Catarrhal",
      "Purulent",
      "Serous"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hemorrhagic"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 21-year-old patient suffers from shoulder pain, redness, swelling without clear boundaries. What type of purulent inflammation in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Abcess",
      "Empyema",
      "Phlegmon",
      "Furunkle",
      "Сarbuncle"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Phlegmon"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 16-year-old patient developed redness, pain, burning in the left hand area after contact with sulfuric acid. What factor caused the inflammation in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Physical ",
      "Chemical irritants",
      "Ischemia and hypoxia",
      "Immune reactions ",
      "Microbiological agents"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chemical irritants"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cachexia patient suffered from prolonged cough, subfebrile fever. An autopsy revealed changes in the lungs. Microscopically: the area of necrosis surrounded by lymphocytes, macrophage cells, epithelioid cells, Langhans-type giant cells. What type of inflammation in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Granulomatous",
      "Fibrinous",
      "Interstitial",
      "Purulent",
      "Serous"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Granulomatous"
  },
  {
    "question": "An autopsy of a 50-year-old deceased revealed foci up to 1-2 cm in diameter in the liver, dense, pinkish, surrounded by a fibrous capsule. Microscopically: in the center there is gummatous (glue-like) necrosis, surrounded by plasma cells, epithelioid cells, lymphocytes, and there is also vascular inflammation. What disease does this granuloma occur in?",
    "options": [
      "Brucellosis",
      "Typhoid fever",
      "Rheumatism",
      "Syphilis",
      "Tuberculosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Syphilis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 14-year-old child, suffering from rheumatism, was admitted to the clinic with complaints of pain in the region of the heart, high fever, shortness of breath. On the 2nd day of hospitalization, death occurred from heart failure. Grossly: the heart is flabby, hypertrophied. Microscopically: edema, hyperemia, blood vessels are surrounded with lymphocytes, histiocytes. What type of inflammation in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Granulomatous",
      "Fibrinous",
      "Interstitial",
      "Purulent",
      "Serous"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Interstitial"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 32-year-old female patient has formation in vulva. Microscopically: a branched tree-like proliferation of stratified squamous epithelium with a fibrous stroma. What type of inflammation in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Granulomatous inflammation",
      "Fibrinous inflammation",
      "Interstitial inflammation",
      "Purulent inflammation",
      "Inflammation with formation of condylomas"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Inflammation with formation of condylomas"
  },
  {
    "question": " What type of interaction between host and microorganisms is commensalism?",
    "options": [
      "microorganism  cause host damage",
      "presence of microorganisms without affecting host ",
      "absence of microorganisms in host",
      "microorganism and host derive benefits from the interaction",
      "only the microorganism derive benefits"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "presence of microorganisms without affecting host "
  },
  {
    "question": " What type of interaction between host and microorganisms is mutualism?",
    "options": [
      "neutral coexistence of macro- and microorganisms",
      "only the microorganism derive benefits",
      "microorganism  cause host damage",
      "presence of microorganisms without affecting host ",
      "microorganism and host derive benefits from the interaction"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "microorganism and host derive benefits from the interaction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of interaction between host and microorganisms is parasitism?",
    "options": [
      "neutral coexistence of macro- and microorganisms",
      "only the microorganism derive benefits",
      "microorganism  cause host damage",
      "presence of microorganisms without affecting host ",
      "microorganism and host derive benefits from the interaction"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "only the microorganism derive benefits"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of interaction between host and microorganisms is infectious process? ",
    "options": [
      "neutral coexistence of macro- and microorganisms",
      "only the microorganism derive benefits",
      "microorganism  cause host damage",
      "presence of microorganisms without affecting host ",
      "microorganism and host derive benefits from the interaction"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "microorganism  cause host damage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Opportunistic infections are developed in which one of listed cases?",
    "options": [
      "autoimmune disease",
      "immunodeficiency",
      "high virulence of microorganism",
      "hypersensitivity",
      "low level of probiotics"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "immunodeficiency"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is decreased. immune control in intestines, that increases risk of infectious agents penetration to blood, which one of these defensive components is damaged?",
    "options": [
      "Peyer patches",
      "Spleen",
      "Intestinal flora",
      "Paneth cells ",
      "Mucous glands"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Peyer patches"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is decreased mechanical barrier in intestines, that increases risk of infectious agents colonization, which one of these defensive components is damaged?",
    "options": [
      "Peyer patches",
      "Spleen",
      "Intestinal flora",
      "Paneth cells ",
      "Mucous glands"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mucous glands"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is decreased chemical barrier in intestines, that increases risk of infectious agents growth and proliferation, which one of these defensive components is damaged?",
    "options": [
      "Peyer patches",
      "Spleen",
      "Intestinal flora",
      "Paneth cells ",
      "Mucous glands"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Paneth cells "
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is decreased biological barrier in intestines, that increases risk of infectious agents growth and proliferation, which one of these defensive components is damaged?",
    "options": [
      "defensins",
      "T lymphocytes",
      "mucin secretion",
      "probiotics",
      "Ig A"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "probiotics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meaning of “opportunistic” infections?",
    "options": [
      "fungal  infections ",
      "protozoa infections",
      "life threatening infections",
      "low virulence infections",
      "viral infections"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "low virulence infections"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterizes adhesion factor of pathogens as virulence in infection process? ?",
    "options": [
      "ability to bind on host cell membrane",
      "ability to  penetrate through host’s cell membrane ",
      "ability to  avoid  host’s immune system ",
      "releasing of exotoxins",
      "actions of endotoxins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ability to bind on host cell membrane"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterizes evasive factor of pathogens as virulence in infection process? ?",
    "options": [
      "ability to bind on host cell membrane",
      "ability to  penetrate through host’s cell membrane ",
      "ability to  avoid  host’s immune system ",
      "releasing of exotoxins",
      "actions of endotoxins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ability to  avoid  host’s immune system "
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterizes invasive factor as virulence in infection process? ",
    "options": [
      "ability to bind on host cell membrane",
      "ability to  penetrate through host’s cell membrane ",
      "ability to  avoid  host’s immune system ",
      "releasing of exotoxins",
      "actions of endotoxins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ability to  penetrate through host’s cell membrane "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which factors produced by pathogens in infection process to keep the host's immune system from destroying the microorganism? ",
    "options": [
      " invasive",
      "avoidive",
      "adhesive",
      "colonisative",
      "toxic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "avoidive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which factors produced by pathogens in infection process relates to avoidive?",
    "options": [
      "capsules",
      "phospholipases",
      "LPS",
      "exotoxins",
      "collagenases"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "capsules"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which factors produced by pathogens in infection process relates to invasive factors?",
    "options": [
      "LPS",
      "capsules",
      "exotoxins",
      "collagenases",
      "slime"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "collagenases"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterizes  existence of saprophytes in study of infection process?",
    "options": [
      "always presence in a host",
      "never presence in a host",
      "only during disease of host",
      "reconvalenced host only",
      "injured host only"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "always presence in a host"
  },
  {
    "question": "Saprophytes mean organisms which are characterized by which one of listed?",
    "options": [
      "rarely found in healthy host",
      "harmless, free-living organisms in host",
      "high virulence organisms ",
      "helpful for host",
      "harmful for host"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "harmless, free-living organisms in host"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of following signs and symptoms of infectious process is nonspecific?",
    "options": [
      "rash",
      "jaundice",
      "diarrhea",
      "leukocytosis",
      "vomiting"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "leukocytosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of listed is first step in development of viral infection?",
    "options": [
      "inserting viral DNA ",
      "penetration",
      "uncoating",
      "host cell lysis",
      "viral replication"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "penetration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of listed is second step in development of viral infection?",
    "options": [
      "inserting viral DNA ",
      "penetration",
      "uncoating",
      "host cell lysis",
      "viral replication"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "uncoating"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of listed is third step in development of viral infection?",
    "options": [
      "inserting viral DNA ",
      "penetration",
      "uncoating",
      "host cell lysis",
      "viral replication"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "inserting viral DNA "
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of listed is fourth step in development of viral infection?",
    "options": [
      "inserting viral DNA ",
      "penetration",
      "uncoating",
      "host cell lysis",
      "viral replication"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "viral replication"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of listed is fifth step in development of viral infection?",
    "options": [
      "inserting viral DNA ",
      "penetration",
      "uncoating",
      "host cell lysis",
      "viral replication"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "uncoating"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a property of microorganisms , which causes facilitation of their penetration during infection process? ",
    "options": [
      "capsules",
      "collagenases",
      "LPS",
      "slime",
      "exotoxins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "collagenases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deficiency of which of these properties causes facilitation of pathogens penetration during infection process, if there is damage of host exogenous barrier?",
    "options": [
      "“respiratory burst” in phagocytes",
      "phagosome-lysosome fusion",
      "antimicrobal  peptides",
      "antibodies production",
      "APP production"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "antimicrobal  peptides"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deficiency of which of these properties causes facilitation of pathogens penetration during infection process, if there is damage of host native endogenous barrier?",
    "options": [
      "lysozyme in secretions",
      "acidic pH  of skin",
      "“respiratory burst” in phagocytes",
      "antimicrobal  peptides",
      "antibodies production"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "“respiratory burst” in phagocytes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deficiency of which of these properties causes facilitation of pathogens penetration during infection process, if there is damage of host specific resistance barrier?",
    "options": [
      "MAC formation",
      "lysozyme in secretions",
      "“respiratory burst” in phagocytes",
      "antimicrobal  peptides",
      "antibodies production"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "antibodies production"
  },
  {
    "question": "Damage of which one of listed causes deficiency of local specific defensive barrier in intestines that facilitates development of infection process?",
    "options": [
      "Peyer patches",
      "Spleen",
      "Intestinal flora",
      "Intestinal flora",
      "Mucous glands"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Peyer patches"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of following is sign of initial (compensatory) stage of shock?",
    "options": [
      "sludging of RBCs",
      "respiratory distress syndrome",
      "blood circulation centralization",
      "lung edema",
      "increased skin perfusion"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "blood circulation centralization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of wound healing can be termed as “keloid”?",
    "options": [
      "Atrophic scar",
      "Scar with dysplasia",
      "Hyperplastic scar",
      "Hypertrophic scar",
      "Bradykinin"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypertrophic scar"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main difference between slowly dividing and rapidly dividing cells is the duration of the next phase",
    "options": [
      "M (mitosis) phase: Phase of mitosis.",
      "G1 (gap 1) phase: The daughter cell enters G1 phase after mitosis.",
      "S (synthesis) phase: During this phase, the synthesis of nuclear DNA takes place",
      "G2 (gap 2) phase: After completion of nuclear DNA duplication, the cell enters G2 phase",
      "Platelet-activating factor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "G1 (gap 1) phase: The daughter cell enters G1 phase after mitosis."
  },
  {
    "question": "These cells continue to multiply throughout life under normal physiologic conditions:",
    "options": [
      "Labile cells",
      "Stable cells",
      "Permanent cells",
      NaN,
      "Plasma cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Labile cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "These cells decrease or lose their ability to proliferate after adolescence but retain the capacity to multiply in response to stimuli throughout adult life:",
    "options": [
      "Labile cells",
      "Stable cells",
      "Permanent cells",
      NaN,
      "Plasma cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stable cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "These cells lose their ability to proliferate around the time of birth:",
    "options": [
      "Labile cells",
      "Stable cells",
      "Permanent cells",
      NaN,
      "Plasma cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Permanent cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Labile cells include following cells:",
    "options": [
      "Epithelial cells of the alimentary tract",
      "Parenchymal cells of live",
      "Neurons of nervous systemA + d",
      NaN,
      "Myeloperoxidase"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": NaN
  },
  {
    "question": "Stable cells include following cells:",
    "options": [
      "Epithelial cells of the alimentary tract",
      "Parenchymal cells of liver",
      "Neurons of nervous system",
      "Hematopoietic cells of bone marrow",
      "Acid hydrolases"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Parenchymal cells of liver"
  },
  {
    "question": "Permanent cells include following cells:",
    "options": [
      "Epithelial cells of the alimentary tract",
      "Parenchymal cells of liver",
      "Neurons of nervous system",
      "Hematopoietic cells of bone marrow",
      "Proteases"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Neurons of nervous system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the replacement of injured tissue by fibrosis tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Regeneration",
      "Repair",
      "Metaplasia",
      " Necrosis",
      "Interleukin-2"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Repair"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following phases are observed in the formation of granulation tissue:",
    "options": [
      "Phase of inflammation",
      "Phase of clearance",
      "Phase of ingrowths of granulation tissue",
      "Phase of ingrowths of granulation tissue",
      "Cationic proteins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Phase of ingrowths of granulation tissue"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a patient operated on for shoulder phlegmon, there is extensive growth of granulation tissue in the floor of the wound from the edge of the wound, the edges of the wound do not converge. What pathological process is there in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Primary Union",
      "Simple healing",
      "Metaplasia",
      "Secondary Union",
      "Hyperplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Secondary Union"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 20-year-old man underwent surgery for appendicitis. Postoperative period without complications. How will the wound healing?",
    "options": [
      "Primary Union",
      "Simple healing",
      "Secondary Union",
      "Formation of keloid",
      "Mixed healing"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Primary Union"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient who died from a hemorrhagic insult. From the anamnesis: he had acute hepatitis 10 years ago. At autopsy, in addition to the changes characteristic of the basic disease, minimal changes in the liver were revealed. What is the recovery mechanism in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Regeneration of parenchymal cells",
      "Proliferation of connective tissue cells",
      "Synthesis of extracellular matrix proteins",
      "Remodeling of connective tissue",
      "Scar formation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Regeneration of parenchymal cells"
  },
  {
    "question": " The patient consulted a surgeon at the clinic with a wound in the area of the right shoulder joint. The bottom of the wound upon examination has a fine-grained surface of a red-pink color. Which of the following types of regeneration develops in this case?",
    "options": [
      "physiological regeneration",
      "pathological regeneration",
      "Incomplete reparative regeneration",
      "humoral regeneration",
      "complete reparative regeneration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Incomplete reparative regeneration"
  },
  {
    "question": " Patient K., 34 years old, consulted a plastic surgeon with complaints of a deforming, unaesthetic-looking scar in the area of the elbow on the left. The patient has a history of injury - rupture of the biceps tendon as a result of sudden lifting of a heavy object. Which of the following types of regeneration is typical for this patient?",
    "options": [
      "physiological regeneration",
      "pathological regeneration",
      "Incomplete reparative regeneration",
      "humoral regeneration",
      "complete reparative regeneration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "pathological regeneration"
  },
  {
    "question": "A young man of 20 got a lacerated wound on his left arm, stitched - 1 week later sutures were remained-healing continued but the site became disfigured by prominent raised irregular nodular scar, in next 2 months which of the following best describes the process:",
    "options": [
      "Organization",
      "Dehiscence",
      "Resolution",
      "Keloid formation",
      "Secondary union"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Secondary union"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient present with a large wound to his right forearm that is the result of a chain saw accident. You treat his wound appropriately and follow him in your surgery clinic at routine intervals. Initially his wound is filled with granulation tissue, which is composed of proliferating fibroblasts and proliferating new blood vessels (angiogenesis). A growth factor that is capable of inducing all the steps necessary for angiogenesis is:",
    "options": [
      "Epidermal growth factor (EGF)",
      "Transforming growth factor α (TGF-α)",
      "Platelet-derived factor (PDGF)",
      "Basic fibroblast growth factor (FGF)",
      "Transforming growth factor β (TGF-β)"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Basic fibroblast growth factor (FGF)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 58-year-old patient who suffered an acute myocardial infarction complained of shortness of breath and weakness. What regenerative capabilities of cardiac muscle cells determine the development of the consequences of acute myocardial infarction?",
    "options": [
      "Labile cells",
      "Stable cells",
      "Permanent cells",
      "Continuously dividing cells",
      "Quiescent cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Permanent cells"
  },
  {
    "question": " A 25-year-old patient consulted a surgeon at the clinic with complaints of the proliferation of red granular tissue, redness and swelling of the wound edges, and slow healing. There was a history of a large scalp wound in the right lower extremity. What are the following types of healing in this patient?",
    "options": [
      "Primary Union",
      "Secondary Union",
      "scab Union",
      "aseptic Union ",
      "tertiary Union"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Secondary Union"
  },
  {
    "question": "Patient, 32 years old, 2 days after a diagnosed fracture of the right humerus. A biopsy revealed loop-shaped vascular capillaries, cells of the reticuloendothelial system (histiocytes, polyblasts, etc.), fibroblasts, lymphocytes, the finest connective tissue fibrils and segmented leukocytes. Which of the following stages of bone healing is present in the patient?",
    "options": [
      "Hematoma formation",
      "Formation of procallus",
      "Formation of osseous callus",
      "Local inflammatory response",
      "Remodeling"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": null
  },
  {
    "question": "Disorder of of biological  component of extrinsic barriers functions is developed when is deficiency of which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "desquamation of keratinized epidermal cells",
      "acidic pH of skin",
      "mucociliary escalator",
      "contraction of smooth muscle",
      "mucosa which traps pathogens"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "mucosa which traps pathogens"
  },
  {
    "question": "Active resistance of human body is ensured by which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "skin barrier",
      "immune cells ",
      "mucous membranes ",
      "blood-brain barrier",
      "keratinocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "immune cells "
  },
  {
    "question": "General Adaptation Syndrome is the concept described by whom of these scientists?",
    "options": [
      "Rudolf Virchov",
      "Claude Bernard",
      "Ilya Metchnikoff’",
      "Hans Selye",
      "Julius Cohnheim"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hans Selye"
  },
  {
    "question": "Alarm Reaction in General Adaptation Syndrome is characterized by which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "releasing of cortisol",
      "releasing of ACTH",
      "releasing of adrenaline",
      "inhibition of adrenal medulla ",
      "activation of adrenal cortex"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "releasing of adrenaline"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following compliment factors deficiency causes disorders of adhesion microbe to phagocyte? ",
    "options": [
      "C1",
      "C3a",
      "C3b",
      "C5b6789",
      "C5b"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "C3b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Disorder of phagocytosis in deficiency of nitric oxide synthase is related to problem with which one of following types of cells?",
    "options": [
      "neutrophils",
      "eosinophils",
      "lymphocytes",
      "macrophages",
      "natural killer cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "macrophages"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one of these disorders of phagocytosis is related to problems in phagocyte itself?",
    "options": [
      "neutralization of oxygen species by bacterial catalase",
      "deficiency agents, which opsonize bacteria",
      "lazy leukocyte syndrome",
      "polysaccharide capsule around microbe",
      "deficiency of IgG"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "lazy leukocyte syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of complement factors can form a large pore that punctures the membrane and thereby promotes the destruction of microbial cell?",
    "options": [
      "C3b",
      "C5a",
      "C5b6789",
      "C1",
      "C3a"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "C5b6789"
  },
  {
    "question": "Disorder of phagocytosis in deficiency of myeloperoxidase/peroxide/chloride bactericidal system is related to problem with which one of following types of cells?",
    "options": [
      "neutrophils",
      "macrophages",
      "NK",
      "lymphocytes",
      "mast cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "neutrophils"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deficiency which of these factors may cause disorder of chemical component of extrinsic barriers functions?",
    "options": [
      "epidermis desquamation ",
      "acidic pH of skin",
      "mucociliary escalator",
      "mucosal \"traps\"",
      "dendritic cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "acidic pH of skin"
  },
  {
    "question": "If definition of reactivity includes characteristics such as “specific reaction of all representatives of one group united by age, by gender, by physique etc.” what type of reactivity is it?",
    "options": [
      "individual reactivity",
      "group reactivity",
      "physiological reactivity",
      "pathological reactivity",
      "biological (species) reactivity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "group reactivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "If definition of reactivity includes characteristics such as “each member of specie naturally resistant or non- susceptible to certain pathogens” what type of reactivity is it?",
    "options": [
      "physiological reactivity",
      "pathological reactivity",
      "individual reactivity",
      "group reactivity",
      "biological (species) reactivity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "biological (species) reactivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Increased gluconeogenesis is characteristic feature of which one of following stage of General Adaptation Syndrome?",
    "options": [
      "stage of resistance",
      "stage of adaptation",
      "alarm reaction",
      "stage of exhaustion",
      "stage of inhibition"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "stage of resistance"
  },
  {
    "question": "When phagocyte engulfs big sized target (parasites), more possible final result is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "increased susceptibility to infections",
      "frustrated phagocytosis",
      "fibrosis and pneumoconiosis ",
      "hypercoagulation in microvessels",
      "complete phagocytosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "frustrated phagocytosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these characterizes stage of Exhaustion of General Adaptation Syndrome?",
    "options": [
      "pupil dilation",
      "increased muscle contractility",
      "mucosal ulceration",
      "immune activity stimulation",
      "mucus hypersecretion"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "mucosal ulceration"
  },
  {
    "question": "When phagocytes engulf small targets, which cannot be digested (coal dust), more possible final result is which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "increased susceptibility to infections",
      "frustrated phagocytosis",
      "fibrosis and pneumoconiosis ",
      "hypercoagulation in microvessels",
      "complete phagocytosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "fibrosis and pneumoconiosis "
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is deficiency of C5a fragment of complement which one of following stages of phagocytosis is damaged?",
    "options": [
      "digestion stage ",
      "hemotaxis of phagocytes",
      "phagosome and lysosomes fusion",
      "phagosome formation",
      "adhesion and engulfment"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hemotaxis of phagocytes"
  },
  {
    "question": "If patient has Chediak-Higashi syndrome which one of following stages of phagocytosis is damaged?",
    "options": [
      "digestion stage ",
      "hemotaxis of phagocytes",
      "phagosome and lysosomes fusion",
      "phagosome formation",
      "adhesion and engulfment"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "phagosome and lysosomes fusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is deficiency of Cb fragment of complement which one of following stages of phagocytosis is damaged?",
    "options": [
      "adhesion and engulfment",
      "phagosome formation",
      "hemotaxis of phagocytes",
      "digestion stage ",
      "phagosome and lysosomes fusion"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "adhesion and engulfment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following can cause incomplete phagocytosis?",
    "options": [
      "production of chemotactic cytokines",
      "expression of C3b receptors",
      "polysaccharide microbial capsule",
      "fusion of lysosomes and phagosome",
      "activation of complement system"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "polysaccharide microbial capsule"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate different feature of hapten from allergen in their compare:",
    "options": [
      "low-molecular-weight substance",
      "free circulated in blood\n\nfree circulated in blood\n\n",
      "polysaccharide molecules",
      "large protein",
      "directly induces the immune response"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "low-molecular-weight substance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Reagins or skin-sensitizing antibodies are being produced  in which following type of hypersensitivity?\nare being produced  in which following type of hypersensitivity?\n",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Type I "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which immunoglobulin class is found on the surface of mast cells?",
    "options": [
      "IgA",
      "IgG",
      "IgM",
      "IgE",
      "IgD"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IgE"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select feature of primary (native) intrinsic allergens compare with secondary (acquired):",
    "options": [
      "native structure proteins",
      "lost immune tolerance",
      "genetic mutations in some protein synthesis",
      "combining haptens  with self-proteins",
      NaN
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "native structure proteins"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select feature of intrinsic secondary (acquired) allergens compare with primary (native):",
    "options": [
      "lost histo-hematic barriers",
      "release of sequestered self- antigens",
      "molecular mimicry",
      "lost immune tolerance",
      "native structure proteins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "lost immune tolerance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What means term idiosyncrasies?",
    "options": [
      "anaphylactoid reactions",
      "atopic diseases",
      "anaphylactic shock",
      "autoimmune diseases",
      "alloimmunity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "anaphylactoid reactions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is name of second stage of experimental anaphylaxis?",
    "options": [
      "passive sensitization",
      "active sensitization",
      "anaphylactic shock",
      "specific desensitization",
      "non specific desensitization"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "anaphylactic shock"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is name of third stage of experimental anaphylaxis?",
    "options": [
      "anaphylactic shock",
      "sensitization",
      "resolution",
      "immune stage",
      "desensitization"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "desensitization"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which hypersensitivity reaction is associated with anaphylactic reaction after bee sting?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Type I "
  },
  {
    "question": "What is name for type I hypersensitivity?",
    "options": [
      "receptor-mediated reactions",
      "T-cell depended reactions",
      "immune-complexed reactions",
      "anaphylactic reactions",
      "cytotoxic reactions"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "anaphylactic reactions"
  },
  {
    "question": "If patient has positive skin-sensitizing test to some allergens, it means elevation of which one of following immunoglobulins?",
    "options": [
      "IgA",
      "IgG",
      "IgM",
      "IgE",
      "IgD"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IgE"
  },
  {
    "question": "Immunoglobulin E or reagins may be detected by which one of following tests?",
    "options": [
      "agglutination test",
      "precipitation test",
      "complement fixation test",
      "skin-sensitizing test",
      "serological test"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "skin-sensitizing test"
  },
  {
    "question": "Waste-product particles produced by the dust mite are often responsible for etiology of which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "autoimmune diseases",
      "atopic diseases",
      "anaphylactic reactions",
      "Arthus phenomenon",
      "serum sickness"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "atopic diseases"
  },
  {
    "question": "When mast cell degranulation is provoked without immune stimulation, which one of following pathologies is it?",
    "options": [
      "anaphylactoid reactions",
      "atopic diseases",
      "anaphylactic shock",
      "autoimmune diseases",
      "alloimmunity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "anaphylactoid reactions"
  },
  {
    "question": "When IgE binds with FceRI and allergen with following mast cell degranulation, which one of following pathologies is it?",
    "options": [
      "autoimmune diseases",
      "alloimmunity",
      "atopic diseases",
      "isoimmunity",
      "idiosyncrasies"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "atopic diseases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following characterizes active sensitization in experimental anaphylaxis?",
    "options": [
      "degranulation of must cells",
      "injection of challenge dose ",
      "injection of sensitizing dose ",
      "injection of sensitized animal serum",
      "brochospasm, asphyxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "injection of sensitizing dose "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following characterizes passive sensitization in experimental anaphylaxis?",
    "options": [
      "degranulation of must cells",
      "injection of challenge dose ",
      "injection of sensitizing dose ",
      "injection of sensitized animal serum",
      "brochospasm, asphyxia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "injection of sensitized animal serum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following characterizes second stage of experimental anaphylaxis?",
    "options": [
      "APC activation",
      "antibodies production",
      "antibodies  disappearance in blood",
      "mast cell degranulation",
      "T cells activation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "mast cell degranulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which one of following characterizes second stage of experimental anaphylaxis?",
    "options": [
      "host immune system produce  antibodies",
      "antibodies titer rises gradually",
      "antibodies titer decreases gradually",
      "life threatening circulatory dysfunction",
      "injection of sensitized animal serum"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "life threatening circulatory dysfunction"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is recruitment of many neutrophils in pathochemical stage of hypersensitivity, which type is it?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type III"
  },
  {
    "question": "If antibodies persist in blood for several weeks in experimental anaphylaxis, which stage is it characteristic feature for?",
    "options": [
      "passive sensitization",
      "active sensitization",
      "specific desensitization",
      "non specific desensitization",
      "anaphylactic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "passive sensitization"
  },
  {
    "question": "If antibodies persist in blood for many years in experimental anaphylaxis, which stage is it characteristic feature for?",
    "options": [
      "passive sensitization",
      "active sensitization",
      "specific desensitization",
      "non specific desensitization",
      "anaphylactic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "active sensitization"
  },
  {
    "question": "If antibodies  disappearance in blood in experimental anaphylaxis, which stage is it characteristic feature for?",
    "options": [
      "passive sensitization",
      "active sensitization",
      "specific desensitization",
      "non specific desensitization",
      "anaphylactic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "specific desensitization"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is inhibition and neutralization of mediators in blood in experimental anaphylaxis, which stage is it characteristic feature for?",
    "options": [
      "passive sensitization",
      "active sensitization",
      "specific desensitization",
      "non specific desensitization",
      "anaphylactic shock"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "non specific desensitization"
  },
  {
    "question": "When etiology of hypersensitivity are autoallergens or haptens, what type of hypersensitivity is it?",
    "options": [
      "anaphylactic reactions",
      "cytotoxic reactions",
      "atopic reactions",
      "immune-complexed reactions",
      "receptor- mediated reactions"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cytotoxic reactions"
  },
  {
    "question": "When etiology of hypersensitivity are foreign proteins or microorganisms excess, what type of hypersensitivity is it?",
    "options": [
      "anaphylactic reactions",
      "cytotoxic reactions",
      "atopic reactions",
      "immune-complexed reactions",
      "T-cell mediated reactions"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "immune-complexed reactions"
  },
  {
    "question": "When etiology of hypersensitivity are pollen grains what type of hypersensitivity is it?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Type I "
  },
  {
    "question": "Perforin-granzyme system performs its function during type II hypersensitivity in which of following actions?",
    "options": [
      "Opsonization",
      "CDCC",
      "ADCC",
      "MAC formation",
      "Complement activation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ADCC"
  },
  {
    "question": "MAC formation during type II hypersensitivity is result of which of following actions?",
    "options": [
      "Perforin-granzyme system activation",
      "ADCC",
      "CDCC",
      "NK activation",
      "Fas-FasL"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "CDCC"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these hypersensitivity reactions is result of immune complexes formation with following deposition in tissues?",
    "options": [
      "Graves’ disease",
      "serum sickness",
      "hemolytic anemia",
      "myasthenia gravis",
      "contact dermatitis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "serum sickness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following are usual allergens  for type III hypersensitivity ?",
    "options": [
      "autoallergens or haptens",
      "foreign proteins excess",
      "pollens ",
      "dust mites",
      "bee sting"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "foreign proteins excess"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which is characteristic clinical feature of immune-comlexed type of hypersensitivity?",
    "options": [
      "serum sickness",
      "myasthenia gravis ",
      "atopic dermatitis",
      "asthma",
      "contact dermatitis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "serum sickness"
  },
  {
    "question": "T-cell mediated reaction or delayed hypersensitivity usually is provoked by which one of following? ",
    "options": [
      "food (white egg, milk)",
      "bee sting",
      "pollens and dust mite",
      "infective agents (brucellosis, syphilis, tuberculosis)",
      "blood transfusion\n\nblood transfusion\n\n"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "infective agents (brucellosis, syphilis, tuberculosis)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which is haracteristic clinical feature of T-cell depended hypersensitivity?",
    "options": [
      "serum sickness",
      "myasthenia gravis ",
      "tuberculin reaction",
      "Arthus phenomenon",
      "asthma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "tuberculin reaction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the most abundant and fastest acting mediator which is released by mast cells?",
    "options": [
      "serotonin",
      "histamine",
      "bradikinin",
      "leukotriene",
      "interferon"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "histamine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which hypersensitivity reaction is associated with serum sickness?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type III"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which hypersensitivity reaction is associated with a tuberculin reaction?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type IV"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following Ig classes is the heaviest monomer  in weight, and the lowest in level? ",
    "options": [
      "IgM",
      "IgG",
      "IgA",
      "IgE",
      "IgD"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IgE"
  },
  {
    "question": "Drug-induced hemolytic anemia can be result of which one of following hypersensitivities?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type II"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which one is characteristic clinical feature of type III  hypersensitivity?",
    "options": [
      "blood transfusion reactions",
      "autoimmune glomerulonephritis",
      "asthma",
      "contact dermatitis",
      "Arthus phenomenon"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Arthus phenomenon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose, when there is recruitment of many eosinophils in pathochemical stage of hypersensitivity, which type is it?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Type I "
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate, when there is recruitment of many cytotoxic T-cells in pathochemical stage of hypersensitivity, which type is it?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type IV"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is recruitment of NK and activation of complement system in pathochemical stage of hypersensitivity, which type is it?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type II"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is receptor- mediated reactions, which cause activation or inhibition of these receptors in pathochemical stage of hypersensitivity, which type is it?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type V"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate which is characteristic feature of immune stage of type I hypersensitivity?",
    "options": [
      "synthesis of Ig M, IgG",
      "recruitment of eosinophils",
      "recruitment of neutrophils",
      "release of lymphokines",
      "synthesis of IgE, IgG4"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "synthesis of IgE, IgG4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pathophysiologic stage of  atopic hypersensitivity is commonly characterized by whichn one of these?",
    "options": [
      "graft rejection",
      "inflammation of synovial membranes ",
      "urticaria (hives)",
      "RBCs hemolysis",
      "vasculitis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "urticaria (hives)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Deposition of immune complexes after their formation is present in which of one of following hypersensitivity types?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type III"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following types of hypersensitivity reactions is characterized by fixed antigen (allergen)?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type II"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following types of hypersensitivity reactions is characterized by fixed antibody (Ig)?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Type I "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following types of hypersensitivity reactions is characterized by proliferation and differentiation of cytotoxic T-cells?",
    "options": [
      " Type I ",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type IV"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is insufficient synthesis of T- and B cells, what type of immune pathology is it?",
    "options": [
      "autoimmunity",
      "transplant immunity",
      "immunodeficiency",
      "hypersensitivity",
      "isoimmunity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "immunodeficiency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Primary immunodeficiency – DiGeorge syndrome is characterized by which one of following signs?",
    "options": [
      "hypoplasia of thymus",
      "hyperplasia of thymus",
      "T-cells in the blood presence",
      "B-cells in the blood absence",
      "T and B-cells in the blood absence"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypoplasia of thymus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one characterizes primary immunodeficiency – DiGeorge syndrome?",
    "options": [
      "hyperplasia of thymus",
      "T-cells in the blood presence",
      "B-cells in the blood absence",
      "tetrad Fallow presence",
      "tetrad Fallow absence"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "tetrad Fallow presence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Defects in synthesis of TCR (T-cell receptors) and BCR (B-cell receptors) determines which one of these types of immune pathology?",
    "options": [
      "autoimmunity",
      "primary immunodeficiency",
      "secondary immunodeficiency",
      "isoimmunity",
      "hypersensitivity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "primary immunodeficiency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Suppression of synthesis of T-and B-cells in BM by radiation dermines which one of these types of immune pathology?",
    "options": [
      "autoimmunity",
      "primary immunodeficiency",
      "secondary immunodeficiency",
      "isoimmunity",
      "hypersensitivity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "secondary immunodeficiency"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which of these primary immunodeficiency syndromes is characterized by combined T-cell and B-cell deficiency?",
    "options": [
      "IgCSRD syndrome",
      "Nezelof  syndrome",
      "Bruton syndrome",
      "Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome",
      "DiGeorge syndrome"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is predominant type of Igs in the blood inIg-class switch recombination   deficiency syndrome(Ig-CSRD)?",
    "options": [
      "IgA",
      "IgM",
      "IgG",
      "IgE",
      "IgD"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IgM"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these primary immunodeficiency syndromes is characterized by ONLY B-cell  deficiency?",
    "options": [
      "IgCSRD syndrome",
      "Omenn syndrome",
      "Bare lymphocyte syndrome",
      "X-SCID",
      "Nezelof  syndrome"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "IgCSRD syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these primary immunodeficiency syndromes is characterized by  is characterized by combine T-cell and B- cell deficiency?",
    "options": [
      "DiGeorge syndrome",
      "IgCSRD syndrome",
      "Bruton’s syndrome",
      "Omenn syndrome",
      "Nezelof  syndrome"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Omenn syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these primary immunodeficiency syndromes is characterized by   ONLY T-cell deficiency?",
    "options": [
      "IgCSRD syndrome",
      "Nezelof  syndrome",
      "Bare lymphocyte syndrome",
      "Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome",
      "X-SCID"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nezelof  syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is immunodeficiency with congenital defect in MHC I synthesis, which one of following changes may be more possible?",
    "options": [
      "disorder of its expression  on APCs ",
      "disorder of antigen presentation  to CD4+ T cells",
      "unable exogenous antigens presentation",
      "combine immunodeficiency",
      "T cell mediated immunodeficiency"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "T cell mediated immunodeficiency"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is immunodeficiency with congenital defect in MHC II synthesis, which one of following changes may be more possible?",
    "options": [
      "disorder of its expression  on APCs ",
      "disorder of antigen presentation  to CD8+ T cells",
      "unable endogenous antigens presentation",
      "T cell mediated immunodeficiency only",
      "B  cell mediated immunodeficiency only"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "disorder of its expression  on APCs "
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is immunodeficiency with congenital defect in RAG1/RAG2 genes, which one of following changes may be more possible?",
    "options": [
      "disorder of MHC I/MHC II expression  ",
      "disorder of TCR/BCR formation",
      "unfunctional B lymphocytes with normal level in blood",
      "unfunctional T lymphocytes with normal level in blood",
      "disorder of DNA repair system in lympphocytes "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "disorder of TCR/BCR formation"
  },
  {
    "question": "In primary immunodeficiency such as Bare lymphocyte syndrome (BLS) both types of immune response may be damaged when there is which one of these genetic mutations?",
    "options": [
      "in MHC I synthesis",
      "in MHC II synthesis",
      "in TCR and BCR synthesis",
      "in IL-2, IL-4 receptors synthesis",
      "in  gamma chain synthesis "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "in MHC II synthesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following mutations damages maturation  of both types of lymphocytes in primary immunodeficiency?",
    "options": [
      "in MHC I synthesis",
      "in MHC II synthesis",
      "in TCR and BCR synthesis",
      "in IL-2, IL-4 receptors synthesis",
      "in  gamma chain synthesis "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "in TCR and BCR synthesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is primary immunodeficiency which is characterized by increased destruction of lymphocytes due to their susceptibility to injorous factors, which one of following changes may be more possible?",
    "options": [
      "WASP gene  is defected",
      "ATM gene is defected",
      "ILRs gene is defected",
      "TAP1/TAP2 gene  is defected",
      "RAG-1/RAG2 gene  is defected"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "ATM gene is defected"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is primary immunodeficiency which is characterized by disorders of T and B lymphocytes maturation, which one of following gene mutations is more possible?",
    "options": [
      "WASP gene  ",
      "ATM gene ",
      "TAP1/TAP2 gene  ",
      "RAG-1/RAG2 gene  ",
      "Btk gene"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "RAG-1/RAG2 gene  "
  },
  {
    "question": "Defect of cytoskeleton formation in all hematopoietic cells (including platelets) and low response to signals arising at the cell membran indicates to which one of following primary immunodeficiency?",
    "options": [
      "WAS",
      "X-SCID",
      "RAG-SCID",
      "CVID",
      "XLA"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "WAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Opportunistic infections in AIDS  mainly is connected with which one of following immune mechanism disorders?",
    "options": [
      "compliment system ",
      "T cell-mediated immune response",
      "B cell-mediated immune response",
      "T and B cell-mediated immune response",
      "monocytes/macrophages system"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "B cell-mediated immune response"
  },
  {
    "question": "Burkitt’s lymphoma in AIDS mainly is connected with which one of following immune mechanism disorders?",
    "options": [
      "compliment system ",
      "T cell-mediated immune response",
      "B cell-mediated immune response",
      "T and B cell-mediated immune response",
      "monocytes/macrophages system"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "T cell-mediated immune response"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is immune response against self-antigens, what type of immune pathology is it?",
    "options": [
      "autoimmunity",
      "transplant immunity",
      "immunodeficiency",
      "hypersensitivity",
      "isoimmunity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "autoimmunity"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is immune response  against nonself-antigens of the same species, what type of immune pathology is it?",
    "options": [
      "immunodeficiency",
      "hypersensitivity",
      "isoimmunity",
      "autoimmunity",
      "immune response to foreign antigens"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "isoimmunity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is an autoimmune disease?",
    "options": [
      "Diabetes mellitus type I ",
      "Serum sickness",
      "Hay fever",
      "Graft rejection",
      "Hemolytic disease of newborns"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Diabetes mellitus type I "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is chronic disease characterized by dry eyes (keratoconjunctivitis sicca) and dry mouth (xerostomia) resulting  from  immunologically mediated destruction of  the lacrimal and salivary glands?",
    "options": [
      "SLE",
      "Type I diabetes",
      "Sjögren Syndrome",
      "Serum sickness",
      "Rheumatoid arthrithis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Sjögren Syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which of these is example of local autoimmune diseases that affects primarily the joints?",
    "options": [
      "SLE",
      "Sjögren Syndrome",
      "Type I diabetes",
      "Serum sickness",
      "Rheumatoid arthrithis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rheumatoid arthrithis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lack of responsiveness to an individual's own antigens is known as:",
    "options": [
      "self-reaction",
      "self-tolerance",
      "self-resistance",
      "self-immunity",
      "self-defence"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "self-tolerance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is a characteristic of environmental factors in autoimmune diseases development?",
    "options": [
      "immunologically privileged sites",
      "antigenic molecular mimicry",
      "HLA -DR3 genes",
      "forbidden clone",
      "sequestered self- antigens"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "antigenic molecular mimicry"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is a characteristic of  central immune tolerance impairment in autoimmune diseases development?",
    "options": [
      "immunologically privileged sites",
      "antigenic molecular mimicry",
      "HLA -DR3 genes",
      "forbidden clone",
      "sequestered self- antigens"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "forbidden clone"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following is a characteristic of  peripheral immune tolerance impairment in autoimmune diseases development?",
    "options": [
      "clonal selection breakdown",
      "forbidden clone",
      "the deletion of regulatory T cells",
      "sequestered antigens",
      "deficiency of CD5 expression"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "the deletion of regulatory T cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "The primary highest level of graft accepting in transplantology is observed in which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "Autograft",
      "Isograft",
      "Allograft",
      "Xenograft",
      "Normograft"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Autograft"
  },
  {
    "question": "If classical activation of compliment system is effector stage of autoimmune pathology on which type of hypersensitivity it is based?",
    "options": [
      "Type I",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type II"
  },
  {
    "question": "If effector stage of autoimmune pathology includes activation of NK via Fc receptor, what type of hypersensitivity is basis for it?",
    "options": [
      "Type I",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type II"
  },
  {
    "question": "If effector stage of autoimmune pathology includes release of lymphokines causing attraction and activation of macrophages, what type of hypersensitivity is basis for it?",
    "options": [
      "Type I",
      "Type II",
      "Type III",
      "Type IV",
      "Type V"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Type IV"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is undesirable reaction of transplant rejection, which is trigger that provokes it?",
    "options": [
      "the recepient’s HLA antigens",
      "the donor’s HLA antigens",
      "the recepient’s TCR/BCR",
      "the donor’s TCR/BCR",
      "the recepient’s MHCI/MHCII"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "the donor’s HLA antigens"
  },
  {
    "question": " Immune system in alloimmunity attacks which one of following factors in compare with autoimmunity?",
    "options": [
      "self-proteins",
      "microbial proteins",
      "haptens binding to self-proteins",
      "donor’s proteins  ",
      "recipient’s proteins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "donor’s proteins  "
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is conflict between Rh-negative mother and Rh-positive fetus, which one type of following pathologies it can be? ",
    "options": [
      "autoimmunity syndrome",
      "immunodeficiency syndrome",
      "isoimmunity syndrome",
      "hypersensitivity type I",
      "hypersensetivity type IV"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "isoimmunity syndrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there are undesirable reactions after  hemotransfusion, what type pathology is it?",
    "options": [
      "hypersensitivity ",
      "autoimmunity",
      "isoimmunity",
      "immunodeficiency",
      "species reactivity"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "isoimmunity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following undesirable reactions relates to  isoimmune response ?",
    "options": [
      "thymus hyperplasia",
      "thymus aplasia",
      "antibodies agains fetal tissues",
      "release of sequestered self- antigen",
      "partial destruction of self-proteins"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "antibodies agains fetal tissues"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these  immune responses  is correct mechanism of isoimmunity?",
    "options": [
      "against foreign antigen",
      "against self-antigen",
      "insufficient immune response",
      "against cryptic antigen",
      "against hapten-binding own proteins "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "against foreign antigen"
  },
  {
    "question": "HVGD- host-versus-graft disease, as an example of isoimmunity syndrome, is developed in which one of following cases?",
    "options": [
      "response to donor’s HLA antigens",
      "transplantation of BM",
      "immune donor cells attack recipient cells",
      "recipient is immunologically compromised",
      "transplant rich in lymphoid tissue"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "response to donor’s HLA antigens"
  },
  {
    "question": ".Сongenital absence of thymus is called:",
    "options": [
      "Aplasia",
      "Hypoplasia. ",
      "Dysplasia. ",
      ".Atrophy. ",
      "Thymomegaly."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Aplasia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital incomplete development of thymus is called:",
    "options": [
      ".Aplasia",
      "Hypoplasia.",
      "Dysplasia. ",
      "Atrophy. ",
      "Thymomegaly."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypoplasia."
  },
  {
    "question": "Aquired decrease in weight of thymus is called:",
    "options": [
      "Aplasia.",
      "Hypoplasia. ",
      "Dysplasia. ",
      "Atrophy. ",
      "Thymomegaly."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Atrophy. "
  },
  {
    "question": "Abnormal development of thymus is called:",
    "options": [
      "Aplasia. ",
      "Hypoplasia",
      "Dysplasia. ",
      "Atrophy",
      "Thymomegaly."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dysplasia. "
  },
  {
    "question": ".Decrease in size and weight of thymus under different stress situations including infectious diseases, intoxications, traumas is called: ",
    "options": [
      "Aplasia. ",
      ".Hypoplasia",
      "Dysplasia. ",
      "Atrophy. ",
      "Accidental involution."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Accidental involution."
  },
  {
    "question": "Immediate type of hypersensitivity morphologically occurs like:",
    "options": [
      "Acute immune inflammation. ",
      "Purulent inflammation",
      "Hemorragic inflammation",
      "Chronic immune inflammation",
      "Catarrhal inflammation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Acute immune inflammation. "
  },
  {
    "question": "Increase in size and weight of thymus more than age level with normal histological structure is called: ",
    "options": [
      ".Aplasia. ",
      "Hypoplasia",
      "Thymomegaly. ",
      "Atrophy",
      "Accidental involution."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Thymomegaly. "
  },
  {
    "question": "Collection of B-lymphocytes and plasma cells with formation of lymphoid follicles in the intralobular perivascular spaces of thymus parenchyma is called:",
    "options": [
      "Aplasia. ",
      "Hypoplasia. ",
      "Thymomegaly. ",
      "Hyperplasia with lymphoid follicles. ",
      "Accidental involution."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hyperplasia with lymphoid follicles. "
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in peripheric lymphoid tissue under antigene stimulation include are all the following processes, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Macrophageal reaction. ",
      ".Hyperplasia of lymphocytes. ",
      "Plasma cell transformation.",
      "Edema of interstitium. ",
      "Infarction."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Infarction."
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in peripheric lymphoid tissue under antigene stimulation include are all the following processes, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Macrophageal reaction. ",
      "Hyperplasia of lymphocytes. ",
      "Dysplasia of lymphocytes. ",
      "Plasma cell transformation.",
      "Edema of interstitium.  "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dysplasia of lymphocytes. "
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in peripheric lymphoid tissue under antigene stimulation include are all the following processes, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Macrophageal reaction. ",
      "Anaplastic transformation of lymphocytes.",
      "Hyperplasia of lymphocytes. ",
      "Plasma cell transformation. ",
      "Edema of interstitium"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Anaplastic transformation of lymphocytes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in lymph nodes under antigene stimulation include are all the following processes, EXCEPT",
    "options": [
      "Hyperemia. ",
      "Edema. ",
      "Accumulation of plasma cells. ",
      ".Accumulation of neutrophils.",
      "Accumulation of macrophages"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": ".Accumulation of neutrophils."
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in lymph nodes under antigene stimulation include are all the following processes, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      ".Hyperemia. ",
      "Ischemia. ",
      ".Edema. ",
      "Accumulation of plasma cells. ",
      "Accumulation of macrophages."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ischemia. "
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in spleen under antigene stimulation include are all the following processes, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Hypoplasia of red pulp",
      "Hyperplasia of red pulp. ",
      "Plasmatization of red pulp. ",
      "Accumulaton of macrophages",
      "Hypoplasia of red pulp.Hyperplasia of follicles."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypoplasia of red pulp"
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in spleen under antigene stimulation include are all the following processes, EXCEPT",
    "options": [
      "Hyperplasia of red pulp. ",
      "Hypoplasia of follicles. ",
      "Plasmatization of red pulp. ",
      "Accumulaton of macrophages.",
      "Hyperplasia of follicles."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypoplasia of follicles. "
  },
  {
    "question": "Changes in spleen under antigene stimulation include are all the following processes, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Hyperplasia of red pulp",
      "Plasmatization of red pulp. ",
      "Accumulaton of giant cells.",
      "Accumulaton of macrophages. ",
      "Hyperplasia of follicles."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Accumulaton of giant cells."
  },
  {
    "question": "Delayed type of hypersensitivity morphologically occurs as:",
    "options": [
      "Acute immune inflammation",
      "Purulent inflammation",
      "Chronic immune inflammation",
      "Hemorragic inflammation",
      "Catarrhal inflammation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chronic immune inflammation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Signs of acute immune inflammation are all the following processes, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Fast development",
      "Prevalence of alterative changes. ",
      "Slow development. ",
      ".Prevalence of exudative changes.",
      "Slow reparation."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Slow development. "
  },
  {
    "question": "Morphologically immediate type of hypersensitivity occurs as:",
    "options": [
      "Fibrinoid necrosis. ",
      "Lympho-hystiocytic infiltration. ",
      ".Macrophageal infiltration.",
      "Cytoplasmic bridges between lymphocytes and macrophages.\n\n",
      "Granulomatosis."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrinoid necrosis. "
  },
  {
    "question": "Morphologically immediate type of hypersensitivity occurs as:",
    "options": [
      ".Lympho-hystiocytic infiltration.",
      "Macrophageal infiltration",
      ".Granulomatosis.",
      "Plasmatic saturation.",
      "Slow development."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Plasmatic saturation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the proposed options oncogenic virus",
    "options": [
      "Influenza virus",
      "Parainfluenza virus",
      "Chikenpox virus",
      "AIDS virus",
      "Hepatitis B virus"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hepatitis B virus"
  },
  {
    "question": " Classification of neoplasms by WHO is based on",
    "options": [
      "Etiology of tumors",
      "Morphogenesis of tumors",
      ".Localization of tumors.",
      "Histogenesis of tumors.",
      "Differentiation of tumors"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Histogenesis of tumors."
  },
  {
    "question": "The term of a benign tumor is constructed by combining the word designating the tumor cell origin plus which of the following endings or words:",
    "options": [
      " genic",
      "emia",
      "oma",
      " itis",
      "osis(-asis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "oma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Growth of tumor without regular borderline is called:",
    "options": [
      "Exophytic",
      "Unicentric",
      "Endophytic.",
      "Expansive.",
      "Invasive."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Invasive."
  },
  {
    "question": "Growth of tumor with regular borderline is called",
    "options": [
      "Exophytic",
      "Unicentric",
      "Endophytic.",
      "Expansive.",
      "Invasive."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Expansive."
  },
  {
    "question": "Spreding of malignant tumors through the bloodstream is called",
    "options": [
      "Seeding",
      "Hematogenous metastasis",
      ".Lymphogenic metastasis",
      "Perineural metastasis",
      "Through the natural passages"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hematogenous metastasis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lack of differentiation is characteristic of which of the following",
    "options": [
      "Hyperplasia",
      "Hypoplasia",
      "Anaplasia",
      "Hypertrophy",
      "Dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Anaplasia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Growth of tumor into the lumen of hollow organ is called",
    "options": [
      "Exophytic",
      "Unicentric",
      "Expansive",
      "Invasive",
      "Endophytic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Exophytic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Growth of tumor into the wall of hollow organ is called",
    "options": [
      "Exophytic",
      "Unicentric",
      "Expansive",
      ".Invasive",
      "Endophytic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Endophytic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spreding of malignant tumors through the serosal surfaces is called",
    "options": [
      "Seeding",
      "Hematogenous metastasis",
      "Lymphogenic metastasis",
      "Perineural metastasis",
      "Through the natural passages"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Seeding"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cancer is the",
    "options": [
      "First leading cause of death",
      "Second leading cause of death",
      "Third leading cause of death",
      "Fourth leading cause of death",
      "Fifth leading cause of death"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Second leading cause of death"
  },
  {
    "question": "Anaplastic cells are characterized by",
    "options": [
      "Nuclear-cytoplasmic ratio is 1:1",
      "Nuclear-cytoplasmic ratio is 1:3",
      "Nuclear-cytoplasmic ratio is 1:5",
      "Nuclear-cytoplasmic ratio is 1:7",
      "Nuclear-cytoplasmic ratio is 1:9"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nuclear-cytoplasmic ratio is 1:1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sign of benign tumors is",
    "options": [
      "Pleomorphic cells",
      "Rapidly growing",
      "Atypical mitoses",
      "Slowly growing",
      "Invasive type of growth"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Slowly growing"
  },
  {
    "question": " Sign of benign tumors is",
    "options": [
      "Pleomorphic cells",
      "Rapidly growing",
      "Atypical mitoses",
      "Expansive type of growth",
      "Invasive type of growth"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Expansive type of growth"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sign of malignant tumors is",
    "options": [
      "Well differentiated",
      "Few mitoses.",
      "Slowly growing",
      "Invasive type of growth",
      "Expansive type of growth."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Invasive type of growth"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sign of malignant tumors is",
    "options": [
      "Pleomorphic cells",
      "Few mitoses",
      "Slowly growing",
      "Regular cells.",
      "Expansive type of growth"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pleomorphic cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Histologic origin of tumors is called",
    "options": [
      "Morphogenesis",
      "Histogenesis",
      "Thanatogenesis",
      "Pathogenesis",
      "Cancerogenesis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Histogenesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Oncogenic virus is",
    "options": [
      "Influenza virus",
      "Parainfluenza virus",
      "Chikenpox virus",
      "AIDS virus",
      "Human papilloma virus"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Human papilloma virus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Most common localization of cancer in men in Western countries is:",
    "options": [
      "Stomach.",
      "Prostate gland.",
      "Thyroid gland.",
      "Lungs",
      "Large intestine."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Prostate gland."
  },
  {
    "question": "Most common localization of cancer in women in Western countries is",
    "options": [
      "Uterus",
      "Ovaries.",
      "Thyroid gland.",
      "Lungs.",
      "Breasts."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Breasts."
  },
  {
    "question": "Most common localization of cancer in men in Kyrgyzstan is",
    "options": [
      ".Esophagus",
      "Stomach",
      "Thyroid gland",
      "Lungs.",
      "Large intestine."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Stomach"
  },
  {
    "question": " Most common localization of cancer in women in Kyrgyzstan is",
    "options": [
      "Uterus.",
      "Ovaries",
      "Breasts",
      "Thyroid gland.",
      "Lungs"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Breasts"
  },
  {
    "question": " Signs of malignant tumors are all of the following, EXCEPT",
    "options": [
      "Pleomorphic cells",
      "Rapidly growing",
      "Atypical mitoses",
      "Slowly growing",
      ".Invasive type of growth"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Slowly growing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most characteristic manifestation of malignant tumor is which of the following",
    "options": [
      "Cellular atypia and pleomorphism",
      "Compression of surrounding tissue",
      "Necrosis",
      "Large size",
      "Metastases"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Metastases"
  },
  {
    "question": "A secondary change in tumors is:",
    "options": [
      "Necrosis",
      "Pathological cell regeneration",
      "The appearance of giant tumor cells",
      "Appositional cell growth",
      "Dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Necrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The repeated occurrence of a tumor after surgical treatment at the site of primary localization is designated by the term",
    "options": [
      "Relapse",
      "Metastases",
      "Malignization",
      "Reversion",
      "Dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Relapse"
  },
  {
    "question": "The effect of a benign tumor on the body:",
    "options": [
      "Germination of organs",
      "Cachexia",
      "Compression of organs",
      "Intoxication",
      "Destruction of organs"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Compression of organs"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transfer of tumor cells from the site of initial localization with the formation of secondary nodes in other organs is denoted by the term",
    "options": [
      "Relapse ",
      " Implantation ",
      " Embolism",
      "Germination",
      "Metastasis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Germination"
  },
  {
    "question": "Obligate precancerous pathology is:",
    "options": [
      "Chronic inflammation ",
      " Dysregeneration ",
      " Pathological regeneration",
      "Specific inflammation",
      " Dysplasia of the 3rd degree"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Specific inflammation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Expansive tumor growth is called",
    "options": [
      "Germination of surrounding tissues",
      "Tumor growth \"by itself\"",
      "Transformation of normal cells into tumor cells",
      "Tumor germination of blood vessels",
      "Compression of the surrounding tissues by the tumor"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tumor growth \"by itself\""
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40-year-old man has a positive stool guaiac test during a routine physical examination. A colonoscopy is performed and a 0.9-cm, circumscribed, pedunculated mass on a short stalk is found in the upper rectum. Which of the following terms best describes this lesion",
    "options": [
      "Adenoma",
      " Carcinoma",
      "Choristoma",
      "Hamartoma",
      "Melanoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Adenoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Pap smear obtained from a 29-year-old woman dur_x001F_ing a routine health maintenance examination is abnormal. She is currently asymptomatic. She has a history of multiple sexual partners. Cervical biopsy specimens are obtained and the microscopic appearance is shown in the figure. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis",
    "options": [
      "Adenocarcinoma",
      "Carcinoma in situ",
      "Dysplasia",
      "Squamous cell carcinoma",
      "Anaplasya"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Squamous cell carcinoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 69-year-old woman has experienced increasing mal_x001F_aise and a 10-kg weight loss over the past year. She dies of massive pulmonary thromboembolism. The gross appearance of the liver at autopsy is shown in the figure. Which of the fol_x001F_lowing best describes the lesions seen in her liver",
    "options": [
      "Invasive angiosarcoma",
      "Hepatocellular carcinoma",
      " Leukemic infiltration",
      "Metastatic adenocarcinoma",
      "Squamous cell carcinoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Metastatic adenocarcinoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 66-year-old man with chronic cough has an episode of hemoptysis. On physical examination, there are no abnormal findings. A chest radiograph shows a 6-cm mass in the right lung. A sputum cytologic analysis shows neoplastic squamous cells. Metastases from his lung lesion are most likely to be found at which of the following sites",
    "options": [
      "Cerebral hemisphere",
      "Chest wall muscle",
      "Hilar lymph nodes",
      "Splenic red pulp",
      "Kidney"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hilar lymph nodes"
  },
  {
    "question": " An epidemiologic study of cancer deaths recorded in the last half of the 20th century is conducted. The number of deaths for one particular type of cancer had been decreas_x001F_ing in developed nations, despite the absence of widespread screening and prevention programs. Which of the following neoplasms was most likely to be identified by this study",
    "options": [
      "Cerebral glioma",
      "Gastric adenocarcinoma",
      "Hepatic angiosarcoma",
      "Leukemia",
      "Colonic adenocarcinoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gastric adenocarcinoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "An epidemiologic study of cancer deaths recorded in the last half of the 20th century is conducted. The number of deaths for one particular cancer had increased markedly in developed nations. More than 30% of cancer deaths in men, and more than 24% of cancer deaths in women, were caused by this neoplasm in 1998. In some nations, prevention strate_x001F_gies reduced deaths from this cancer. Which of the following neoplasms was most likely identified by this study",
    "options": [
      " Cerebral glioma",
      "Bronchogenic carcinoma",
      "Hepatocellular carcinoma",
      "Colonic adenocarcinoma",
      "Gastric adenocarcinoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bronchogenic carcinoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 59-year-old man has noticed blood in his urine for the past week. Cystoscopy shows a 4-cm exophytic mass involv_x001F_ing the right bladder mucosa near the trigone. After biopsy specimens are obtained, he undergoes a radical cystectomy. Examination of the excised specimen shows an anaplastic car_x001F_cinoma that has infiltrated the bladder wall. Which of the fol_x001F_lowing techniques applied to the cells from his neoplasm is most likely to categorize the cell of origin",
    "options": [
      "Chromosomal karyotyping",
      "Cytologic smear",
      "DNA microarray",
      "Immunohistochemistry",
      "Biochemical blood analysis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Immunohistochemistry"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 69-year-old man has noted a chronic cough for the past 3 months. On physical examination, there is mild stri_x001F_dor on inspiration over the right lung. A chest radiograph shows a 5-cm right hilar lung mass, and a fine-needle aspi_x001F_ration biopsy specimen of the mass shows cells consistent with squamous cell carcinoma. If staging of this neoplasm is denoted as T2N1M1, which of the following findings is most likely in this man",
    "options": [
      "Brain metastases",
      " Elevated corticotropin level",
      " Infiltration of the chest wall",
      "Obstruction of a mainstem bronchus",
      "Invasive angiosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Brain metastases"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 44-year-old woman notes a lump in her left breast while taking a shower. The nurse practitioner palpates a 3 cm firm, irregular, non-movable mass in the upper outer quadrant of her left breast on physical examination. A fine needle aspiration of this mass is performed, and cytologically the cells are consistent with infiltrating ductal carcinoma. The mass is removed with lumpectomy along with an axillary lymph node dissection. Which of the following findings will best predict a better prognosis for this patient?",
    "options": [
      "Tumor cells strongly estrogen receptor positive",
      "No metastases in the sampled lymph nodes",
      "Flow cytometric analysis with aneuploidy and a high S-phase",
      "One relative who had a similar type of breast cancer",
      "Elevated corticotropin level"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "No metastases in the sampled lymph nodes"
  },
  {
    "question": "A study is performed to analyze characteristics of malignant neoplasms in biopsy specimens. The biopsies were performed on patients who had palpable mass lesions on digital rectal examination. Of the following microscopic findings, which is most likely to indicate that the neoplasm is malignant",
    "options": [
      " Pleomorphism",
      "Atypia",
      "Invasion",
      " Increased nuclear/cytoplasmic ratio",
      "Dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Invasion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dysplastic cells are characterized by all of the following, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Loss of cell uniformity.",
      "Formation of tumor giant cells",
      "Hyperchromatic enlarged nuclei",
      "Architectural anarchy",
      "Increased mitotic figures."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Formation of tumor giant cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dysplastic cells are characterized by all of the following, EXCEPT",
    "options": [
      "Loss of cell uniformity",
      "Hyperchromatic enlarged nuclei.",
      ".Increased normal mitotic figures.",
      "Mitoses are numerous and atypical.",
      "Architectural anarchy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mitoses are numerous and atypical."
  },
  {
    "question": "Dysplastic cells are characterized by all of the following, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Hyperchromatic enlarged nuclei.",
      ".Loss of cell uniformity",
      "Increased normal mitotic figures",
      "Architectural anarchy.",
      "Marked pleomorphism"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Marked pleomorphism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dysplastic cells are characterized by all of the following, EXCEPT",
    "options": [
      "Loss of cell uniformity.",
      "Hyperchromatic enlarged nuclei.",
      "Nuclei are variable and bizarre in size and shape",
      "Increased normal mitotic figures",
      "Architectural anarchy."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nuclei are variable and bizarre in size and shape"
  },
  {
    "question": " Lack of cell differentiation (anaplasia) in malignant tumor is characterized by all of the following, EXCEPT",
    "options": [
      "Cellular and nuclear pleomorphism",
      "Hyperchromatic nuclei",
      "Increased nuclear-to-cytoplasmic ratio",
      "Coarsely clumped chromatin",
      "Metastases"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Metastases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Anaplastic cells are characterized by all of the following, EXCEPT",
    "options": [
      "Marked pleomorphism",
      ".Mitoses are numerous and atypical",
      "Nuclei are variable and bizarre in size and shape",
      "Cells resemble very closely their normal counterparts",
      "Nucleoli are of astounding size."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cells resemble very closely their normal counterparts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Anaplastic cells are characterized by all of the following, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Marked pleomorphism.",
      "Mitoses are numerous and atypical",
      "Nuclei are variable and bizarre in size and shape",
      "Formation of tumor giant cells",
      "Formation of Langhans giant cells."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Formation of Langhans giant cells."
  },
  {
    "question": "Anaplastic cells are characterized by all of the following, EXCEPT",
    "options": [
      "Marked pleomorphism.",
      "Mitoses are numerous and atypical",
      "Nuclei are variable and bizarre in size and shape",
      "Loss of functions is not correlated with degree of anaplasia",
      "Loss of functions is correlated with degree of anaplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Loss of functions is not correlated with degree of anaplasia"
  },
  {
    "question": "All of the following statements correctly describe cell oncogenes, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Oncogenes are derived from viral DNA that has been incorporated into the genome",
      "Oncogenes encode proteins that resemble the products of normal genes",
      "Some oncogene products are the analogues of growth factors",
      " Some oncogene products are the analogues of growth factor receptors",
      "Some oncogene products activate nuclear transcription"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Oncogenes are derived from viral DNA that has been incorporated into the genome"
  },
  {
    "question": "The sequence of events in the tumor cell invasion into the basement membranes includes all of the following, EXCEPT:",
    "options": [
      "Loosening of intercellular junctions",
      "Attachment to the basement membrane",
      "Accumulation of the neutrophils",
      "Degradation of the basement membrane",
      "Tumor cell migration"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Accumulation of the neutrophils"
  },
  {
    "question": "A child is born with a single functional allele of a tumor suppressor gene. At the age of five the remaining normal allele is lost through a point mutation. As a result, the ability to inhibit cell cycle progression until the cell is ready to divide is lost. Which of the following neoplasms is most likely to arise via this mechanism",
    "options": [
      "Breast ductal carcinoma",
      "Pulmonary small cell anaplastic carcinoma",
      "Ocular retinoblastoma",
      "Cerebral astrocytoma",
      "Chondrsarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ocular retinoblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 45-year-old woman has noted a lump on her left shoulder that has enlarged over the past 4 months. On physical examination there is a palpable non-tender supraclavicular lymph node. A biopsy of the node is performed and on microscopic examination there is a metastatic neoplasm. Which of the following is the most likely primary for this neoplasm",
    "options": [
      "Cerebral glioma",
      "Adenocarcinoma of the stomach",
      "Fibroadenoma of the breast",
      "Liposarcoma of the retroperitoneum",
      "Carcinoma in situ"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Adenocarcinoma of the stomach"
  },
  {
    "question": "A gastroscopic examination of a patient in the lesser curvature revealed a tumor formation with a diameter of 1.5 cm on the pedicle. Which type of tumor growth occurs in this case",
    "options": [
      "Exophytic",
      "Expansive",
      "Invasive",
      "Endophytic",
      "Multicentric"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Exophytic"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 45-year-old patient suffering from gastric carcinoma, ultrasound examination revealed secondary tumorous nodes in the liver, lungs and lymph nodes. Which term used for this process?",
    "options": [
      "Metastasis",
      "Recurrence",
      "Implantation",
      " Embolism",
      "Ingrowth"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Metastasis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient who underwent a course of treatment for skin cancer, after 5 years, skin defects in the form of ulcers reappeared. A skin biopsy was taken. Microscopically: atypical cells with numerous mitotic figures were found. What pathological process has developed in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Metastasis",
      "Recurrence",
      "Dermatitis",
      "Metaplasia",
      "Hyperplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Recurrence"
  },
  {
    "question": "A biopsy of the gastric mucosa was taken from a patient suffering from indigestion and abdominal pain. Microscopically: atypical epithelial cells, many mitotic figures. What is the pathological process in this case",
    "options": [
      "Gastritis",
      "cancer",
      "Ulcer",
      "Metaplasia",
      "Erosion"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cancer"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 42-year-old patient died from gastric carcinoma. At pathanatomical examination revealed thickening and hardning of the stomach wall. Microscopically: atypical cells of the gastric epithelium located in the mucosa, submucosa, muscular membrane were found. Which type of tumor growth occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Exophytic",
      "Unicentric",
      "Invasive",
      "Multicentric",
      "Endophytic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Invasive"
  },
  {
    "question": "The patient a 55 years-old man, suffered from abdominal pain, dyspepsia, weight loss of 10 kg during the year. A biopsy of the large intestine was taken. Microscopically:  anaplastic cells, new blood vessels, few mitotic figures. What pathological process described in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Ulcer",
      "Inflammation",
      "Atrophy",
      "Neoplasia",
      "Metaplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Neoplasia"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the gastroscopic examination of the patient, a tumor formation with a diameter of 2 cm was found in the area of small curvature.Pronounced cellular atypism is visible under the microscope. What type of tumor growth takes place in this case",
    "options": [
      "Exophytic",
      "carcinoma in situ",
      "Invasive",
      "Multicentric",
      "Endophytic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "carcinoma in situ"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the colonoscopic examination of a 55-year-old patient revealed a tumor formation with a diameter of 2 cm on the pedicle. What type of tumor growth takes place in this case",
    "options": [
      "Exophytic",
      "Expansive",
      "Invasive",
      "Multicentric",
      "Endophytic"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Exophytic"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of benign tumor arising from connective tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Hybernoma",
      "Leiomyoma",
      ".Lipoma",
      "Fibroma",
      "Osteoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibroma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of benign tumor arising from fatty tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Hybernoma.",
      "Leiomyoma",
      "Lipoma",
      "Fibroma",
      "Osteoma."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lipoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of benign tumor arising from fibrous tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Leiomyoma",
      " Myoma",
      "Chondroma",
      "Rhabdomyoma",
      "Fibroma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibroma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tumor histological consisting of lobules of mature adipose cells separated by delicate fibrous septa, called",
    "options": [
      " Chondroma",
      "Rhabdomyoma",
      " Leiomyoma",
      "Lipoma",
      " Fibroma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lipoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of benign tumor arising from brown fat?",
    "options": [
      "Hybernoma.",
      "Leiomyoma",
      "Lipoma",
      ".Fibroma",
      "Osteoma."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hybernoma."
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name benign tumor arising from smooth muscles?",
    "options": [
      "Hybernoma",
      "Leiomyoma.",
      "Rhabdomyoma.",
      "Fibroma.",
      "Osteoma."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Leiomyoma."
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name benign tumor arising from striated muscles?",
    "options": [
      "Hybernoma",
      "Leiomyoma.",
      "Rhabdomyoma.",
      "Fibroma.",
      "Osteoma."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rhabdomyoma."
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name benign tumor arising from blood vessels?",
    "options": [
      "Hybernoma",
      "Leiomyoma.",
      "Rhabdomyoma.",
      "Hemangioma.",
      "Lymphangioma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hemangioma."
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name benign tumor arising from lymph vessels?",
    "options": [
      "Hybernoma",
      "Leiomyoma.",
      "Rhabdomyoma.",
      "Hemangioma.",
      "Lymphangioma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lymphangioma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name benign tumor arising from bone?",
    "options": [
      "Osteoma",
      "Chondroma",
      "Synovioma",
      "Mesothelioma",
      ".Osteosarcoma."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Osteoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of benign tumor arising from cartilage?",
    "options": [
      "Osteoma.",
      "Chondroma",
      "Synovioma",
      "Mesothelioma",
      "Chondrosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chondroma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of benign tumor arising from  inner layer of joints?",
    "options": [
      ".Osteoma.",
      "Chondroma",
      "Synovioma",
      "Mesothelioma",
      "Hybernoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Synovioma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of malignant tumor arising from cartilaginous tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Chondrosarcoma",
      "Adenocarcinoma",
      " Osteosarcoma",
      "Fibrosarcoma",
      "Papilloma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chondrosarcoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of malignant tumor arising from connective tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Angiosarcoma.",
      "Leiomyosarcoma.",
      ".Liposarcoma",
      "Fibrosarcoma",
      "Osteosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrosarcoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of malignant tumor arising from fibrous tissue?",
    "options": [
      " Leiomyosarcoma",
      "Papilloma",
      "Chondrsarcoma",
      "Rhabdomyoma",
      "Fibrosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Fibrosarcoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of malignant tumor arising from fatty tissue?",
    "options": [
      "Angiosarcoma.",
      ".Leiomyosarcoma.",
      "Liposarcoma.",
      "Fibrosarcoma.",
      "Osteosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Liposarcoma."
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of malignant tumor arising from bones?",
    "options": [
      "Angiosarcoma.",
      "Leiomyosarcoma.",
      ".Liposarcoma",
      "Fibrosarcoma",
      "Osteosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Osteosarcoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of malignant tumor arising from  blood vessels?",
    "options": [
      "Angiosarcoma",
      "Leiomyosarcoma",
      "Liposarcoma",
      ".Fibrosarcoma",
      "Osteosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Angiosarcoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of malignant tumor arising from  smooth muscles?",
    "options": [
      "Angiosarcoma.",
      "Leiomyosarcoma",
      "Liposarcoma",
      "Fibrosarcoma",
      "Osteosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Leiomyosarcoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the name of a malignant tumor originating from smooth muscle cells",
    "options": [
      "Leiomyosarcoma",
      " Papilloma",
      "Chondrsarcoma",
      "Rhabdomyoma",
      "Fibrosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Leiomyosarcoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of malignant tumor arising from  striated muscles?",
    "options": [
      "Angiosarcoma",
      "Leiomyosarcoma.",
      "Liposarcoma.",
      "Fibrosarcoma",
      "Rhabdomyosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rhabdomyosarcoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tumor histological consisting of large, round or oval cells with granulated, an eosinophilic cytoplasm; and, as a rule, transversal stripes are in some cells, called:",
    "options": [
      "Leiomyosarcoma",
      " Papilloma",
      " Chondrsarcoma",
      "Rhabdomyoma",
      "Fibrosarcoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Rhabdomyoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Benign tumor arising from melanocytes cells is called",
    "options": [
      "Chondroma",
      "Adenoma",
      " Nevus",
      " Fibroma",
      " Papilloma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Nevus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Commonest type of pigmented nevus is",
    "options": [
      "Junctional nevus.",
      "Compound nevus",
      "Intradermal nevus",
      "Blue nevus",
      "Juvenile nevus."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Compound nevus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of nevus often quite rich in melanin pigment",
    "options": [
      "Junctional nevus",
      "Compound nevus",
      "Intradermal nevus",
      "Juvenile nevus",
      "Blue nevus."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blue nevus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of nevus consists of epithelioid-like cells",
    "options": [
      ".Junctional nevus",
      "Compound nevus",
      "Intradermal nevus.",
      ".Juvenile nevus",
      "Blue nevus"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": ".Juvenile nevus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of nevus has increased risk of progression to malignant melanoma",
    "options": [
      ".Junctional nevus",
      "Compound nevus",
      "Intradermal nevus",
      ".Juvenile nevus",
      "Dysplastic nevus"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dysplastic nevus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of melanoma is essentially a malignant melanoma in situ",
    "options": [
      "Lentigo maligna melanoma",
      "Superficial spreading melanoma",
      "Acral lentigenous melanoma.",
      "Pagetoid melanoma",
      "Nodular melanoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Lentigo maligna melanoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of melanoma occurs more commonly on the soles, palms and mucosal surfaces",
    "options": [
      ".Lentigo maligna melanom",
      "Acral lentigenous melanoma",
      "Pagetoid melanoma",
      "Nodular melanoma",
      "Superficial spreading melanoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pagetoid melanoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Developmental tumor is",
    "options": [
      "Teratoma.",
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Neuroblastoma."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Teratoma."
  },
  {
    "question": ".Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is:",
    "options": [
      ".Chordoma.",
      "Ameloblastoma.",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Branchial cysts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Medulloblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is",
    "options": [
      "Chordoma",
      "Ameloblastoma",
      ".Craniopharingeoma",
      "Nephroblastoma.",
      ".Branchial cysts."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nephroblastoma."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which embryonic tumor is benign?",
    "options": [
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Neuroblastoma",
      "Ameloblastoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ameloblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which malignant embryonic tumor may transform to benign",
    "options": [
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Hepatoblastoma",
      "Melanoma",
      "Angiosarcoma",
      "Neuroblastoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Neuroblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carcinoma histologically - appear signet ring cells (excessive mucin accumulates in the cell and the nucleus is pushed towards the periphery). Which type of carcinomas is it?",
    "options": [
      "scirrhous carcinoma",
      "solid carcinoma",
      "mucous or colloid carcinoma",
      "medullary carcinoma",
      "small cell carcinoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "mucous or colloid carcinoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following defeats of the reproductive system of women is a precancerous",
    "options": [
      "Cystic atrophy of the endomethum",
      "Endocervical polyps",
      "Endometrial polyps",
      "Condyloma acuminatum of the vulva",
      "Atypical hyperplasia of the endometrium"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Atypical hyperplasia of the endometrium"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most characteristic feature of a malignant neoplasm in contrast to a reactive or inflammatory overgrowth is which of the following:",
    "options": [
      "Growth factor production",
      " Necrosis",
      "Localization",
      "Autonomous growth following the removal of all provoking factors",
      "Adjacent tissue compression"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Autonomous growth following the removal of all provoking factors"
  },
  {
    "question": "Microscopic examination of thyroid gland biopsy revealed changes in the structure of the gland: a well-differentiated epithelium of the glands with few mitoses and consist of groups of cells. Which type of adenoma occurs in this case",
    "options": [
      "Acinar adenoma",
      "Cystadenoma",
      "Tubular adenoma",
      " Fibroadenoma",
      "Trabecular adenoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Trabecular adenoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A woman of Asian ethnicity has a 0.5x0.3 cm dark node, elevated above the skin, with a smooth surface. Microscopic examination shows dendritic cells with high melanin content. Which type of tumor occurs in this case?",
    "options": [
      "Hybernoma",
      "Lentigo",
      "Hemangioma",
      "Blue nevus",
      " Dysplastic nevi"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blue nevus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A tumor of the uterus was removed in 40-year-old patient. Pathanatomical examination the tumor presented by grey-white masses, 5x5 cm in size firm in consistency, with regular borders. Microscopically: whorled bundles of smooth muscle cells admixted with small amount of connective tissue. Which type of tumor occurs in this case",
    "options": [
      "Fibroma",
      " Leiomyoma",
      "Fibrosarcoma",
      "Histiocytoma",
      "Chondroma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Leiomyoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "RNA oncogenic viruses, which can cause tumor growth, include which one of following?",
    "options": [
      "experimental Rause’s hen’s sarcoma",
      "Epstein-Barr viruses",
      "human papilloma viruses",
      "herpesviruses",
      "papovirus"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "experimental Rause’s hen’s sarcoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Oncogenic viruses, which can cause tumor growth, cause which one of following effect on cells?",
    "options": [
      "kill cells",
      "damage of mitochondria",
      "damage of DNA",
      "damage of membrane",
      "swelling cells"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "damage of DNA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these are chemical carcinogenic factors?   ",
    "options": [
      "nitrosamines",
      "chronic trauma",
      "radiation therapy",
      "Epstein-Barr viruses",
      "herpesvirus"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "nitrosamines"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate, which one of following is chemical carcinogenic factor?    ",
    "options": [
      "chronic trauma",
      "radiation therapy",
      "Epstein-Barr viruses",
      "aflotoxin",
      "HTLV"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "aflotoxin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is the biological carcinogenic factor?   ",
    "options": [
      "aflotoxin",
      "“milk factor”",
      "radiation therapy",
      "nitrosamine",
      "nitrosamide"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "“milk factor”"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these belong to the physical carcinogenic factors?     ",
    "options": [
      "nitrosamines",
      "HTLV",
      "UV exposure",
      "papovirus",
      "polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "papovirus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose which of these are biological carcinogenic factors?",
    "options": [
      "nitrosamines",
      "HTLV",
      "UV exposure",
      "polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons",
      "radiation"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "HTLV"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate what are most common chemical carcinogenic factors which may be inhaled during long time?",
    "options": [
      "free radicals",
      "polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons",
      "aflotoxin",
      "nitrosamines",
      "nitrosamides"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons"
  },
  {
    "question": "Indicate what is chemical carcinogenic factor, which is product of mold and may accumulate in liver?",
    "options": [
      "aromatic amines",
      "polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons",
      "aflotoxin",
      "nitrosamines",
      "nitrosamides"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "aflotoxin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of following carcinogenic factors predominate in air pollution?",
    "options": [
      "aromatic amines",
      "polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons",
      "aflotoxin",
      "nitrosamines",
      "nitrosamides"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are intrinsic risk factors for tumor growth?",
    "options": [
      "ultraviolet exposure",
      "chronic trauma",
      "radiation therapy",
      "immunosuppression",
      "DNA viruses"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "immunosuppression"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of these characterizes initiation stage of carcinogenesis in  tumor growth?  ",
    "options": [
      "neoplastic transformation of cells",
      "loss of differentiation",
      "activation of proto-oncogens",
      "metastasis",
      "invasion"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "activation of proto-oncogens"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mutation in which of growth control genes can cause neoplasia development due to overstimulation of signal-transducing proteins synthesis?",
    "options": [
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "antioncogenes",
      "tumor suppressor genes",
      "apoptosis regulatory  genes",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "proto-oncogenes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mutation in which of growth control genes can cause neoplasia development due to inhibition of antioxidant enzymes synthesis? ",
    "options": [
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "antioncogenes",
      "tumor suppressor genes",
      "apoptosis regulatory  genes",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "tumor suppressor genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mutation in which of growth control genes can cause neoplasia development due to inhibition of TP53 synthesis?",
    "options": [
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "tumor suppressor genes",
      "apoptosis regulatory  genes",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes",
      "oncogens"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "tumor suppressor genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of following growth control genes stimulate the entry of cells into mitosis and alteration of them can cause tumor growth development? ",
    "options": [
      "apoptosis regulatory  genes",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes",
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "oncogens",
      "tumor suppressor genes "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "oncogens"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are genes responsible for the mechanisms of defense against tumor growth by the way to improve enzymes activity in cell nucleus?",
    "options": [
      "apoptosis regulatory  genes",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes",
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "oncogens",
      "tumor suppressor genes "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "DNA repair regulatory genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are genes responsible for the mechanisms of defense against tumor growth by the way to kill mutated cell?",
    "options": [
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "antioncogenes",
      "tumor suppressor genes",
      "apoptosis regulatory  genes",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "apoptosis regulatory  genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are genes responsible for the mechanisms of defense against tumor growth by the way to inhibit the entry of cells into mitosis?",
    "options": [
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "antioncogenes",
      "tumor suppressor genes",
      "apoptosis regulatory  genes",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "tumor suppressor genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transformation of normal cell into a tumor cell occurs as a result of which one of these?",
    "options": [
      "inhibition of oncogenes",
      "inhibition of anti-oncogenes",
      "activation of apoptosis genes ",
      "activation of DNA repair systems",
      "activation of suppressor genes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "inhibition of anti-oncogenes"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the normally developing embryo, aortic arches are apparent by the end of the fourth week. Which of the following arteries is derived from the third pair of aortic arche",
    "options": [
      "Carotid",
      "Pulmonary",
      " Stapedial",
      "Subclavian",
      "Aorta thoracica"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Carotid"
  },
  {
    "question": "An embryonic eye is developing normally. A retina is present on the posterior aspect of the globe. What is the embryologic origin of the portion of retina containing nerve cell bodies",
    "options": [
      "Diencephalon",
      "Mesoderm",
      "Notochord",
      "Pharyngeal arch",
      "anencephaly"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Diencephalon"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a developing embryo, neural crest cells form adjacent to the neural tube. These neural crest cells then undergo migration. Which of the following structures is derived from these migrating cells",
    "options": [
      "Dorsal root ganglion",
      "Dura mater",
      "Epidermis covering the back",
      "Intervertebral disk",
      "cerebellum"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dorsal root ganglion"
  },
  {
    "question": "A fetus at 18 weeks gestation is normally formed and appropriately sized. No fetal or placental anomalies are present. Which of the following parts of the fetal vasculature is most likely to have the greatest oxygen concentration?",
    "options": [
      "Aorta",
      " Ductus arteriosus",
      "Pulmonary vein",
      "Umbilical vein",
      "Carotid"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Umbilical vein"
  },
  {
    "question": "The malformation of the central nervous system includes",
    "options": [
      "apus",
      "acrania",
      " syndactyly",
      "hydrocele",
      "piocephaly"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "acrania"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which variant of neonatal respiratory distress syndrome is associated with severe blockade of gas exchange",
    "options": [
      "Massive aspiration of amniotic fluid",
      "Primary atelectasis.",
      "Secondary atelectasis.",
      "Intra-alveolar edema and hemorrhages",
      "Hyaline membrane disease"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hyaline membrane disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which variant of neonatal respiratory distress syndrome is associated with сongenital surfactant deficiency",
    "options": [
      "Massive aspiration of amniotic fluid",
      "Primary atelectasis.",
      " Secondary atelectasis",
      "Intra-alveolar edema and hemorrhages",
      "Hyaline membrane disease"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Primary atelectasis."
  },
  {
    "question": "The presence of stillborn lungs with a greenish tinge, as well as the appearance of dense greenish masses on the incision under pressure, points to:",
    "options": [
      " bronchopulmonary dysplasia",
      "diseases of hyaline membranes",
      "syndrome of massive aspiration of amniotic fluid and meconium",
      "atelectasis of the lungs",
      "congenital bronchiectasis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "syndrome of massive aspiration of amniotic fluid and meconium"
  },
  {
    "question": "After the completion of what week of pregnancy does the calculation of the perinatal period begin",
    "options": [
      "20 weeks",
      "22 weeks",
      "24 weeks",
      "25 weeks",
      "28 weeks"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "22 weeks"
  },
  {
    "question": "A newborn examination is performed. The tympanic membranes are visualized bilaterally. What is the embryologic origin of the structure that forms the canal connecting the external ear to the tympanic membrane?",
    "options": [
      "First pharyngeal cleft",
      "Bony labyrinth",
      "Endolymphatic duct",
      "Otic pit",
      "auditory ossicles"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Bony labyrinth"
  },
  {
    "question": " Mutations affecting germ cells produce",
    "options": [
      "Cancers",
      "Inherited diseases",
      " Congenital malformations",
      "Aneuploidy",
      "Hylinosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Inherited diseases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Polyploidy is generally not a feature of dividing cells of the following type",
    "options": [
      "Megakaryocytes",
      "Tubular cells",
      "Hepatocytes",
      "Conceptus of abortions",
      "nephrons"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tubular cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Teratogens are defined as agents which induce",
    "options": [
      "Mitosis",
      "Carcinogenesis",
      "Birth defects",
      "Fallot’s tetralogy",
      "Cancers"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": null
  },
  {
    "question": "Duration of blastogenesis is:",
    "options": [
      "1st-15th days of prenatal development.",
      "1st-20th days of prenatal development",
      "5th-20th days of prenatal development",
      "5th-25th days of prenatal development.",
      "1st-25th days of prenatal development."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "1st-15th days of prenatal development."
  },
  {
    "question": "Duration of embryogenesis is:",
    "options": [
      "16th-66th days of prenatal development.",
      "15th-75th days of prenatal development",
      "20th-80th days of prenatal development.",
      "16th-75th days of prenatal development.",
      "16th-80th days of prenatal development."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "16th-75th days of prenatal development."
  },
  {
    "question": "Duration of early fetogenesis is:",
    "options": [
      "80th-180th days of prenatal development",
      "76th-180th days of prenatal development.",
      "70th-170th days of prenatal development",
      "76th-175th days of prenatal development.",
      "70th-180th days of prenatal development."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "76th-175th days of prenatal development."
  },
  {
    "question": "Duration of late fetogenesis is:",
    "options": [
      "180th-250th days of prenatal deveelopment",
      "170th-280th days of prenatal development",
      "185th-285th days of prenatal development",
      "180th-280th days of prenatal development",
      "181st-280th days of prenatal development."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "181st-280th days of prenatal development."
  },
  {
    "question": "Down’s disease - is",
    "options": [
      "Gametopathy.",
      " Blastopathy",
      "Embryopathy",
      " Early fetopathy",
      "Late fetopathy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Gametopathy."
  },
  {
    "question": "Ectopic pegnancy - is:",
    "options": [
      "Gametopathy.",
      "Blastopathy",
      "Embryopathy",
      "Early fetopathy.",
      "Late fetopathy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blastopathy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Siamese twins - is",
    "options": [
      "Gametopathy.",
      "Blastopathy",
      "Embryopathy",
      "Early fetopathy.",
      "Late fetopathy"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Blastopathy"
  },
  {
    "question": "In lysosomal storage diseases, the following cells are particularly involved:",
    "options": [
      "Hepatocytes",
      "Skeletal muscle",
      "Macrophages",
      "White pulp of spleen",
      "Red pulp of spleen"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Macrophages"
  },
  {
    "question": "Blastomas are childhood tumours seen more often in the age range of",
    "options": [
      "<4 years",
      "5-9 years",
      "10-14 years",
      "14-16 years",
      "16-20 days"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "<4 years"
  },
  {
    "question": "Endogenic etiologic factors of kymatopathies are:",
    "options": [
      "Genic mutations",
      " Radiation.",
      "Alcohol",
      " Metals",
      " Infections."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Genic mutations"
  },
  {
    "question": "Exogenic etiologic factors of kymatopathies are",
    "options": [
      "Genic mutations",
      "Endocrine diseases of mother.",
      "Drugs using during pregnancy.",
      "Gonads overriping",
      "Critical periods of parents age."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Drugs using during pregnancy."
  },
  {
    "question": "Noninfectious fetopathy is:",
    "options": [
      "Syphilis",
      "Listeriosis",
      " Toxoplasmosis",
      "Mucoviscidosis",
      "Cytomegaly."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Mucoviscidosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Noninfectious fetopathy is:",
    "options": [
      "Syphilis",
      "Listeriosis",
      " Toxoplasmosis",
      "diabetic fetopathy",
      "Cytomegaly."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "diabetic fetopathy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Infectious fetopathyis",
    "options": [
      "Mucoviscidosis",
      "diabetic fetopathy",
      " Toxoplasmosis",
      "hemolytic disease of newborn",
      "fibroelastosis of endocardium"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Toxoplasmosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Infectious fetopathyis",
    "options": [
      "Mucoviscidosis",
      "diabetic fetopathy",
      "hemolytic ddisease of newborn",
      "Syphilis",
      "fibroelastosis of endocardium"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Syphilis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Noninfectious fetopathy is:",
    "options": [
      "fibroelastosis of endocardium",
      "Syphilis",
      "Listeriosis",
      " Toxoplasmosis",
      "Cytomegaly."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "fibroelastosis of endocardium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Infectious fetopathyis",
    "options": [
      "Cytomegaly.",
      "Mucoviscidosis",
      "diabetic fetopathy",
      "fibroelastosis of endocardium",
      "hemolytic disease of newborn"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Cytomegaly."
  },
  {
    "question": "For chromosomal study, the dividing cells are arrested by colchicine in the following phase of cell cycle",
    "options": [
      "Prophase",
      "Metaphase",
      "Anaphase",
      "Telophase",
      "phagacytosis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Metaphase"
  },
  {
    "question": "For chromosomal study, it is best to use the following nucleated cells",
    "options": [
      "Polymorphs",
      " Lymphocytes",
      "Epithelial cells",
      "Fibroblasts",
      "erythrocytes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Lymphocytes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Denver classification divides chromosomes based on their length into the following groups",
    "options": [
      "A to C (3 groups)",
      "A to E (5 groups)",
      "A to G (7 groups)",
      "A to I (9 groups)",
      "A to K (11 groups)"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "A to G (7 groups)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Out of the following glycogenosis, the following is example of lysosomal storage diseasse",
    "options": [
      "von Gierke’s disease",
      "Pompe’s disease",
      " Forbe’s disease",
      "Anderson’s disease",
      "Addison disease"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Pompe’s disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - accumulation of excessive cerebrospinal fluid  within  the ventricular system  of the brain:",
    "options": [
      "Anencephaly",
      " Exencephaly",
      "Inioncephaly.",
      "Microcephaly",
      "Hydrocephaly"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hydrocephaly"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital heart disease which associated with abnormal division of cardiac cavities is",
    "options": [
      "Common truncus arteriosus",
      "Coarctation of aorta",
      "Ventricular septal defect.",
      "Patent ductus arteriosus",
      " Transposition of great arteries"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ventricular septal defect."
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital heart disease which associated with anomalies of great arteries is:",
    "options": [
      "Atrial septal defect.",
      "Ventricular septal defect",
      "Tricameral heart",
      "Bicameral heart.",
      "Transposition of great arteries"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Transposition of great arteries"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital heart disease which associated with anomalies of great arteries is:",
    "options": [
      "Atrial septal defect.",
      "Ventricular septal defect.",
      " Patent ductus arteriosus",
      "Tricameral heart",
      "Bicameral heart"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Patent ductus arteriosus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital heart disease which associated with abnormal division of cardiac cavities is",
    "options": [
      "Common truncus arteriosus",
      "Coarctation of aorta.",
      "Tricameral heart",
      "Patent ductus arteriosus",
      " Transposition of great arteries"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Tricameral heart"
  },
  {
    "question": "How soon after fertilization occurs within the uterine tube does the blastocyst begin implantation?",
    "options": [
      "Within minutes",
      "By 12 hours",
      "By day 1",
      "By day 5",
      "By day 7"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "By day 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - complete absence of an organ is called:",
    "options": [
      "Agenesis",
      "Aplasia",
      "Hypoplasia",
      " Hyperplasia",
      " Dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Agenesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - absence of development of an organ with presence of anlage (rudiment) is called",
    "options": [
      "Agenesis",
      "Aplasia",
      "Hypoplasia",
      " Hyperplasia",
      " Dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Aplasia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - incomplete development of an organ is called:",
    "options": [
      "Agenesis",
      "Aplasia",
      "Hypoplasia",
      " Hyperplasia",
      " Dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hypoplasia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - overdevelopment of an organ is called:",
    "options": [
      "Agenesis",
      "Aplasia",
      "Hypoplasia",
      " Hyperplasia",
      " Dysplasia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Hyperplasia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - absence of lumen in follow organs is called",
    "options": [
      " Atresia.",
      "Stenosis.",
      "Dysraphia",
      " Extrophia.",
      "Ectopia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Atresia."
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - defect resulting from failure of fusion (in a middle line of organ) is called",
    "options": [
      " Atresia.",
      "Stenosis.",
      "Dysraphia",
      " Extrophia.",
      "Ectopia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Dysraphia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - abnormal location of an organ is called: ",
    "options": [
      " Atresia.",
      "Stenosis.",
      "Dysraphia",
      " Extrophia.",
      "Ectopia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ectopia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - absence of brain is called:",
    "options": [
      "Anencephaly.",
      "Exencephaly.",
      "Inioncephaly",
      "Microcephaly",
      "Hydrocephaly"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Anencephaly."
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - absence of occipital bone and location of brain in posterior cranial fossa is called:",
    "options": [
      "Anencephaly.",
      "Exencephaly.",
      "Inioncephaly",
      "Microcephaly",
      "Hydrocephaly"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Inioncephaly"
  },
  {
    "question": "Congenital malformation - absence of gyri and sulci of brain is called",
    "options": [
      "Anencephaly",
      "Agyria",
      "Microgyria",
      "Microcephaly.",
      "Porencephaly"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Agyria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The malformation of the genito-urinary organs is:",
    "options": [
      "epispadia",
      "Simpus",
      "simpodium",
      "apus",
      "focomelia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "epispadia"
  },
  {
    "question": "The malformation of the osteoarticular system includes",
    "options": [
      "focomelia",
      "acrania",
      " hydrocephaly",
      " hypospadia",
      "cyclopia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "focomelia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Simpus is:",
    "options": [
      "fusion of fingers",
      "fusion of toes",
      "fusion of the lower extremities",
      "fusion of upper extremities",
      "absence of upper and lower extremities"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "fusion of the lower extremities"
  },
  {
    "question": " From which day antenatal phase of perinatal period is started",
    "options": [
      "150th day",
      "154th day",
      "156th day.",
      "160th day",
      "180th day"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "154th day"
  },
  {
    "question": "Body weight of premature newborn is less than:",
    "options": [
      "2000 gr",
      "2300 gr",
      "2500 gr.",
      "2600 gr",
      "2650 gr"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "2500 gr."
  },
  {
    "question": "Body length of premature newborn is less than",
    "options": [
      "35 сm",
      "40 сm",
      "45 сm",
      "48 сm",
      "50 сm."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "45 сm"
  },
  {
    "question": "The malformation of the facial skull is",
    "options": [
      "Syndactyly",
      "simpodium",
      "synoty",
      " Monarchism",
      " focomelia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "synoty"
  },
  {
    "question": "The malformation of the facial skull is",
    "options": [
      "cyclopia",
      "Syndactyly",
      " hypospadia",
      "amelia",
      "epispadia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "cyclopia"
  },
  {
    "question": " The malformation of the genito-urinary organs is",
    "options": [
      "hypospadia",
      "acrania",
      "amelia",
      " hydrocephaly",
      "cyclopia"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "hypospadia"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ascending route of infection of the fetus is more:",
    "options": [
      "Staphylococcus",
      "viruses",
      "Listeria",
      "anaerobic infection",
      "All listed"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Staphylococcus"
  },
  {
    "question": ".Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is:",
    "options": [
      ".Chordoma.",
      "Ameloblastoma.",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Branchial cysts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Medulloblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is",
    "options": [
      "Chordoma",
      "Ameloblastoma",
      ".Craniopharingeoma",
      "Nephroblastoma.",
      ".Branchial cysts."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nephroblastoma."
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is",
    "options": [
      "Chordoma.",
      "Ameloblastoma.",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      "Neuroblastoma",
      "Branchial cysts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Neuroblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is",
    "options": [
      "Chordoma.",
      "Ameloblastoma.",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      "Hepatoblastoma",
      "Branchial cysts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hepatoblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic vestiges is",
    "options": [
      "Nephroblastoma.",
      "Ameloblastoma.",
      ".Retinoblastoma",
      "Medulloblastoma.",
      "Neuroblastoma."
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ameloblastoma."
  },
  {
    "question": "Developmental tumor is",
    "options": [
      "Teratoma",
      " Nephroblastoma",
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Neuroblastoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Teratoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is:",
    "options": [
      "Chordoma",
      "Ameloblastoma",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      " Medulloblastoma",
      "Branchial cysts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Medulloblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is",
    "options": [
      "Chordoma",
      "Ameloblastoma",
      " Craniopharingeoma",
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Branchial cysts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Nephroblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is",
    "options": [
      "Chordoma",
      "Ameloblastoma",
      " Craniopharingeoma",
      "Neuroblastoma",
      "Branchial cysts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Neuroblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues is",
    "options": [
      "Chordoma",
      "Ameloblastoma",
      " Craniopharingeoma",
      "Hepatoblastoma",
      "Branchial cysts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Hepatoblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic vestiges is",
    "options": [
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Ameloblastoma",
      " Retinoblastoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Neuroblastoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Ameloblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic vestiges is",
    "options": [
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Chordoma",
      " Retinoblastoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Neuroblastoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Chordoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Embryonic tumor arising from embryonic vestiges is",
    "options": [
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      " Retinoblastoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Neuroblastoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Craniopharingeoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tumor arising from hindbrain is called",
    "options": [
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Neuroblastoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Medulloblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tumor arising from parapituitary residues is called",
    "options": [
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Neuroblastoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Craniopharingeoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tumor arising from notochord organ is called:",
    "options": [
      "Ameloblastoma ",
      " Retinoblastoma",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      "Neuroblastoma",
      " Chordoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": " Chordoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of following growth control genes are responsible for error correction during mitosis and alteration of them can cause tumor growth development?",
    "options": [
      "apoptosis regulatory genes ",
      "growth suppressor genes",
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "oncogens",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "DNA repair regulatory genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of following growth control genes are responsible for elimination of cell with error during mitosis and alteration of them can cause tumor growth development?",
    "options": [
      "apoptosis regulatory genes ",
      "growth suppressor genes",
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "oncogens",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "apoptosis regulatory genes "
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of following growth control genes prevent excessive cell mitosis and alteration of them can cause tumor growth development?",
    "options": [
      "apoptosis regulatory genes ",
      "growth suppressor genes",
      "proto-oncogenes",
      "oncogens",
      "DNA repair regulatory genes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "growth suppressor genes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What means term“antioncogenes” in tumor pathogenesis?",
    "options": [
      "genes for unregulated cell division",
      "genes for metabolism control",
      "genes for growth",
      "genes for reduce cell division",
      "modified protooncogenes  "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "genes for reduce cell division"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which term used to indicate developmental tumor?",
    "options": [
      "Teratoma",
      "Nephroblastoma",
      "Retinoblastoma ",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Neuroblastoma"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Teratoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What the name of embryonic tumor arising from embryonic tissues?",
    "options": [
      "Chordoma",
      "Ameloblastoma",
      "Craniopharingeoma",
      "Medulloblastoma",
      "Branchial cysts"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Medulloblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the endogenous etiological factor of kymatopathies? ",
    "options": [
      "Genic mutations",
      "Radiation",
      "Alcohol",
      "Metals",
      "Infections"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Genic mutations"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the exogenic etiological factor of kymatopathies?",
    "options": [
      "Genic mutations",
      "Endocrine diseases of mother",
      "Drugs using during pregnancy",
      "Gonads overriping",
      "Critical periods of parents age"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Drugs using during pregnancy"
  },
  {
    "question": "From what day of pregnancy, the antenatal phase of the perinatal period begins?",
    "options": [
      "From day 150",
      "From day 154",
      "From day 156",
      "From day 160",
      "From day 170"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "From day 154"
  },
  {
    "question": "On what day after the birth of the child does the postnatal phase of the perinatal period end?",
    "options": [
      "Day 5",
      "Day 6",
      "Day 7",
      "Day 8",
      "Day 9"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "Day 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is characteristic feature of carcinogenesis stage such as progression in tumor growth?",
    "options": [
      "monoclonal character of tumor growth",
      "angiogenesis in neoplastic tissues",
      "inhibition of tumor suppressor genes",
      "activation of tumor suppressor genes",
      "conversion of proto-oncogenes to oncogenes"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "angiogenesis in neoplastic tissues"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is characteristic feature of carcinogenesis stage such as promotion in tumor growth?",
    "options": [
      "unstable state of individual genotype",
      "mutation of tumor suppressor genes ",
      "mutation of proto-oncogenes",
      "metaplasia of tumor cells",
      "invasion and metastasis"
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "metaplasia of tumor cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Presence which of listed cells indicates to carcinogenesis stage such as promotion in tumor growth?",
    "options": [
      "initiating cells",
      "metastatic cells",
      "neoplastic cells",
      "embryonic stem cells",
      "suppressor cells "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "neoplastic cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Appearance which of listed cells indicates to carcinogenesis stage such as progression in tumor growth?",
    "options": [
      "initiating cells",
      "metastatic cells",
      "neoplastic cells",
      "embryonic stem cells",
      "suppressor cells "
    ],
    "correctAnswer": "metastatic cells"
  }
]